<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse about the pretious blood and sacrifice of Iesus Christ.</title>
            <author>Moore, Thomas, Senior.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 264 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89269</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2592</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E360_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201196</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861731</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861731</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113873</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89269)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113873)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 58:E360[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse about the pretious blood and sacrifice of Iesus Christ.</title>
                  <author>Moore, Thomas, Senior.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 103 [i.e. 105], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Thomas Moore, who has signed the foot of A1v, which is entitled "Christian reader".</note>
                  <note>A1r is blank; title from caption title, leaf A2r.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in pagination; actual pagination deduced from signature collation.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-N⁴ O² .</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: at foot of A1r: "Nouemb: 6th London 1646".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Blood --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113873:1"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Having fore-written about the extent of the death, and ſacrifice of Chriſt; That it might be more uſefully underſtood, I have here preſented to thy view, this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Tract, deſiring, that is good, may be received; And, what ſwarveth from Truth, that I may be lovingly informed thereof, which I ſpall heartily accept at the hands of any; or, if evident truth be faulted, ſhall with meekneſſe give anſwer if I may be permitted; And that God may graciouſly diſcover to us, and leade us into all truth; Is the deſire of the leaſt of his mercies, and ſervants.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho: Moore.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:113873:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A DISCOVRSE ABOUT THE PRETIOVS BLOOD AND SACRIFICE OF IESVS CHRIST.</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The Preface.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſidering how our Saviour, when he was about to leave his Diſciples, whom he ſo dearly loved; left with them by his inſtitution, His Supper, in which they might ſpiritually enjoy his preſence; And then ſaid to them: Do this in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of mee, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.19. And that the Apoſtle ſaith, That in ſo doing we ſhew forth the Lords death till he come, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25.26.</p>
               <p>And likewiſe; That the Apoſtle affirmeth, that as many as are baptized into Chriſt, were baptized into his death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3. ſo that to be taught, and ſubdued to the acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and brought into the faith of Chriſt, and unto confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity with him; Is to be taught, and ſubdued to the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement, and brought into the faith of the death of Chriſt,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113873:2"/>and conformed to him in fellowſhip of his death, as that wherein the vertue of his Reſurrection is met with, Rom. 6.4.8. Gal. 2.20. Phil. 3.2.7.8.9. 2 Cor. 4.10.11.12. 2 Tim. 2.11.</p>
               <p>And the Scripture affirmeth of all the Prieſthood, Sacrifices, Atonement, and Purifications under the Law; That they were but figures, types, and ſhadowes of that to be found in Chriſt; He being the body, Col. 2.17. And the truth of all typed in the ſhadowes found in him, Heb. 9.9.23. Chap. 10.1. And ſo that, there was more vertue, Power, and Prevalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with God in Chriſt, his offering himſelfe, and preſenting the vertue of his blood before his Father, than in all the offerings of the other Prieſts, Heb. Chap. 10.14. And that there is more Power, vertue, and prevalency, with, and in men for purge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the conſcience, in the ſpirituall ſprinkling of the vertue of the blood, and ſacrifice of Chriſt therein; than was in all thoſe ſhadowing purifications, and ſprinklings to purifie the fleſh, Heb 9.12.13.14.</p>
               <p>Yea thoſe who in being taught of God, have experimented the truth hereof, call the blood of Chriſt pretious, 1 Pet. 1.19. And have profeſſed in their Preachings, not to determine to know any thing among their hearers, ſave Jeſus Chriſt, and him crucified, 1 Cor. 2.2. And not to glory, and rejoyce, ſave in the Croſſe of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, Gal. 6.14. It gives me to conceive, that a ſober reader will be perſwaded; that there is ſomthing in the blood, death, and ſacrifice of Chriſt, of infinite vallue, and worthy our hartieſt, and deepeſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, moſt wiſte view, beſt remembrance, and choyſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation: and ſo I am encouraged to preſent the ſame to conſideration, and for more orderly proceeding to conſider.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. What is comprehended in theſe termes, the ſufferings, Blood, Death, and Sacrifice of Chriſt?</item>
                  <item>2. The manifold ends of his ſuffering, Blood, Death, and Sacrifice, as the Scripture diſtinctly ſets them forth.</item>
                  <item>3. The neceſſity of the ſufferings, Blood, Death, and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>4. The Excellency, Dignity, and worth of this blood, and ſacrifice.</item>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113873:2"/>
                  <item>5. The vertue, operation, and prevalency thereof, preſented, and applyed.</item>
                  <item>6. The uſefulneſſe of the ſame, knowne, and believingly remembred.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>What is comprehended in theſe tearmes? The Sufferings, Blood, Death, and Sacrifice of Chriſt.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IN theſe together, and every of theſe tearmes, in Scripture is ment;</p>
               <p>Somtime fully, and almoſt onely, and alwayes incluſively. The very ſuffering of Chriſt it ſelfe; The ſhedding of his blood, and his death, Eſa. 53.4.5. Surely he hath borne our griefes, and carryed our ſorrowes, — He was wounded for our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, the chaſtiſement of our peace was upon him, Rom. 4.25. He was delivered for our offences, 1 Cor. 15.3. Chriſt dyed for our ſins according to the Scripture, Gal. 3.13. Being made a curſe for us, 1 Pet. 3.18. <hi>Chriſt hath once ſuffered for our ſins, the juſt for the unjuſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.14.15. <hi>He dyed for All,</hi> Heb. 2.9. <hi>By the grace of God he taſted death for every man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Somtimes together with this former ſence of the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, the Blood-ſhed, and Death of Chriſt it ſelfe; is ment, Alſo in the ſame tearmes of ſuffering, Blood, and Death of Chriſt, the vertue, and efficacy of this ſuffering, Blood-ſhed, and death of Chriſt as he is riſen from the Dead, free, and juſt from all our ſins imputed to him, and a victor over all our curſe, and death impoſed on him; As namely:
<list>
                     <item>1. The fulfilling the truth of God in the death of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; for ſo we judge, if one dyed for all; then are all dead, and he dyed for all, that they which live, ſhould live to him, &amp;c. 2 Cor. 5.14.15. Gen. 2.17.</item>
                     <item>2. The ſatisfying Divine Juſtice, in that all have ſuffered the curſe in one publike man being made a curſe, and having
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113873:3"/>overcome it for them, Gal. 3.10-13. with Eſa. 53.5. and 2 Cor. 5.19.21.</item>
                     <item>3. The ſatisfying, and fulfilling the Law, accompliſhing a righteouſneſſe for us, that Way may be made for the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of the law to be fulfilled in us, Gal. 1.4. Rom. 8.3.4.</item>
                     <item>4. The overcoming death, and him that had the power of death, And ſo takeing out of the way, that which was in the way between God, and us; contrary to us, 2 Tim. 1.10. Heb. 2.14. Col. 2.14.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>So as in him, mercy and truth are met, righteouſneſſe and peace have kiſſed, Pſal. 85.10. ſuch the vertue of the ſufferings, blood, and death of Jeſus Chriſt, being riſen from the dead.</p>
               <p>And thus he is ſaid to be riſen for our Juſtification, Rom. 4.25. And ſo is he juſtified in the roome of all mankind, that they are all in him as in the publike perſon, juſtified, Rom. 3.23.24. <hi>All have ſinned, and come ſhort of the glory of God; Being juſtified freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Rom. 5.18. <hi>As by the offence of one unto all men, to Codemnation, even ſo by the righteouſneſſe of one to all men to juſtification of life;</hi> And he by himſelfe, purged, (or made purgation for) our ſinns, and then ſate downe, &amp;c. Heb. 1.3. And ſo hath taken away our ſins by the ſacrifice of himſelfe, Heb. 9.26. Iohn 1.29. 1 Iohn 3.5. And through death deſtroyed him that had the power of death, Heb. 2.14. And all this, the vertue and efficacy of the death, and reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of him that is riſen from the dead, 1 Cor. 15. tot</p>
               <p n="3">3. Somtimes; together with both the former ſences; by the ſuffering, blood, death, and ſacrifice of Chriſt, is ment, His offering, and preſenting himſelfe in heaven before his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by and with the vertue of this his ſuffering, blood, and death, as the price, the Ranſome, the propitiatory-ſacrifice for atonement and purchaſe to God for men: So Heb 8.3. It is of neceſſity that he have ſomwhat alſo to offer, Heb. 9 26. now once in the end of the world hath he appeared to take away ſin by the ſacrifice of himſelfe, verſ. 12. By his own blood he entred in once into the holy place, verſe 14. who through the eternall Spirit offered himſelfe without ſpot to God: ſee Heb. 10.1.—12. Tit. 2.14. <hi>Who gave himſelfe for us,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113873:3"/>that he might redeem us,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.6. <hi>who gave himſelfe a ranſome for all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Somtime, together with all theſe former ſences; by the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, Blood, Death, and Sacrifice of Chriſt, is ment; The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valency, and effectuallneſſe thereof, as preſented to God with God for mankind, ſo as he hath made peace, ſlaine enmity, obtained e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Redemption, and received fulneſſe of ſpirit to make it knowne, and diſpenſe it, Epheſ. 2.15. <hi>Having aboliſhed in his fleſh the enmity, ſo making peace;</hi> verſe 16. <hi>Having ſlaine the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,</hi> Heb. 9.12. <hi>having obtained eternall redemption,</hi> and Pſal. 68.18. <hi>Received gifts in the man,</hi> (<hi>and for men,</hi> Epheſ. 4.8.) <hi>even the rebellious alſo, that the Lord God might dwell amongſt them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this prevalency, and effectualneſſe of his pretious Blood, and Sacrifice offered to his Father for men; appeares in many things; eſpecially.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In that the Father hath accepted of him, and his Sacrifice, for the ends, for which he offered the ſame to him, and hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and exalted him with, and at his right hand, Mat. 17.5. <hi>My beloved Sonne in whom I am well pleaſed,</hi> Iohn 16.8.10. <hi>The Spirit ſhall convince the world of righteouſneſſe, becauſe I go to my Father, and ye ſee me no more; That is, He is received, and his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice accepted, and ſo ſent forth no more to ſuffer, and offer Sacrifice for ſinns, as he ſhould have been, if he had not ſatisfied for all</hi> (Heb. 9.7.8.) <hi>And wrought a perfect righteouſneſſe,</hi> and ſo it is ſaid, Heb. 1.3. <hi>After he had by himſelfe purged; (or made purgation of) our ſins, he ſat downe on the right hand of the Majeſty on high</hi> Heb. 10.12. <hi>After he had offered one ſacrifice for ſinns for ever, he ſat downe on the right hand of God;</hi> yea the Lord in Teſtimony of his well-pleaſedneſſe with him, hath ſaid to him, Pſal. 110.1. <hi>Sit thou on my right hand till I, &amp;c.</hi> Heb. 1.13.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In that the Father hath releaſed, and given over all to his Sonne, and given all power, and authority into his hands, and made him Lord of all, ſo as he ſhall judge all men; And he hath filled him with Immeaſurable fulneſſe of the Holy-Ghoſt in the humane nature; to diſpenſe to men, to make known his grace, and that he may according to the Goſpel abſolve all that believe, and condemn all that will not believe, Pſal. 2.8. <hi>I ſhall give thee, the Heathen for thine Inheritance, and the utmoſt parts of the earth for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113873:4"/>thy poſſeſſion,</hi> Mat. 11.27. <hi>All things are delivered to me of my Father,</hi> Iohn 16.15. <hi>All things that the Father hath are mine,</hi> Mat. 28.18. <hi>All power is given to me in Heaven, and in Earth,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.22. <hi>Angels, Authorities, and powers being made ſubject to him,</hi> Act. 2.36. <hi>God hath made Jeſus both Lord and Chriſt,</hi> Act. 10.36. <hi>He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Lord of all, and this by vertue of his death, reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and aſcention,</hi> Rom. 14.8.9. <hi>And he is the Judge,</hi> Iohn. 5.27. Act. 17.31. <hi>And is filled with ſpirit to ſend forth in the meanes,</hi> Act. 2.32.33. Epheſ. 4.7.-12. That ſo he may abſolve and judge according to the Goſpel, Rom. 2.16. Iohn 12.48.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In that the Holy-Ghoſt in the Scripture avoucheth ſuch full ſufficiency, compleatneſſe and vertue in this pretious Blood, Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and ſacrifice, as it is by Chriſt, in preſenting, and offering himſelfe, preſented, and offered to the Father, and by him accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and received, that Jeſus Chriſt is hereby become, appointed, and accepted of God, even Gods ſalvation to the ends of the earth,<note place="margin">Eſa. 49. Ioh. 4.42.</note> Act. 13.47. <hi>The Saviour of the world,</hi> 1 Iohn 4.14. <hi>The Mediatour between God and men,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.5. <hi>The great High-Prieſt, Prophet, and Advocate for his Church,</hi> Heb. 3.1.-6. and 7. 1 Iohn 2.2.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In the appearing and forth-coming of love, and grace through the effectualneſſe, and fruitfulneſſe of his pretious Blood, Ranſome, and Sacrifice, as it hath been, and is preſented to God; from whom it procureth ſuch Kindneſſe, and grace to be extended to manward, that hereby, even by Chriſt, and for his ſake, and through the vertue of his Sacrifice;</p>
               <p n="1">1 The earth with the Inhabitants are upheld for men, and mens lives reprived, and ſpace afforded, even to Rebels, that they might repent, Pſalm. 75.3. <hi>The Earth and all the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants thereof are diſſolved, I bear up the pillars of is.</hi> Heb. 1.3. <hi>upholding all things by the Word of his Power, when he had by himſelf purged our ſins, &amp;c. Col.</hi> 1.17. <hi>By him all things conſist.</hi> Joh. 1.4. <hi>In him was life, and the life was the light of men,</hi> Rev. 2.21. <hi>I gave her ſpace to repent,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.9. <hi>He is long-ſuffering to us<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that All ſhould come to repentance.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Patience, and forbearance is extended to men that are yet found ſinning: and bounty, and many mercies vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113873:4"/>which carry forth in them the teſtimony of his goodneſſe, and that to this end, <hi>To lead men to repentance,</hi> Act. 14.16, 17. He in times paſt ſuffered All Nations to walke in their owne wayes: Nevertheleſſe, he left not himſelf without witneſſe, in that he did good, and gave us rain from Heaven, and fruitfull Seaſons, filling our hearts with food, and gladneſſe, Rom. 2.4. <hi>The goodneſſe of God leadeth thee to repentance:</hi> And this riches of the goodneſſe of God, and forbearance, long-ſuffering, and fruits of mercy, being extended through the ſacrifice offered, and redemption obtained by Chriſt, and carrying in it the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of his goodneſſe, and leading to repentance, and that to this end, <hi>that men might ſeek after the Lord,</hi> Act. 17, 26. It is grace, and free grace, and univerſally extended, and that to a gratious end: And as the giving of Chriſt to be the <hi>Saviour of the world,</hi> 1 Joh. 4.14. <hi>was a fruit of Gods rich mercy, pitty, and love to man-kind,</hi> John 3.16, 17. So this is a fruit of the preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the ſacrifice of Chriſt with God, <hi>And his kindneſſe to manward for Christ his ſake,</hi> Tin. 3.4 And ſo far as it is to all men, it is generall, and univerſall ſure; Matth. 5.44, 45. Pſalm. 17.14.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The giving of his Word, and oracles, with his ordinances to many men; wherein the Saviour with his peace, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſalvation is ſet forth, <hi>That men might through him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and in believing have life.</hi> Joh. 1.4, 5, 7. And ſo it is he that hath made peace, <hi>That comes in the Word preaching peace,</hi> Epheſ. 2.17. This was peculiar to <hi>Iſrael</hi> from <hi>Abrahams</hi> time, till Chriſt his Aſcenſion, Pſalm. 147.19, 20. <hi>And ſince extended to the Gentiles,</hi> Epheſ. 3.5, 6.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The affording ſome light, and motion of his Spirit, in, and according to the meanes vouch ſafed, whether in the Book of Creatures onely, or the Book of Scriptures alſo: <hi>For calling All men,</hi> Prov. 8.4 5. <hi>Iſa</hi> 45.22. <hi>And willing them, and ſtriving with them at one time or other,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.12. Gen. 6.3. And ſo Chriſt is the true Light, that lighteth every man that cometh into the world, John 1.9. And ſo in the workes of Creation, It is ſaid, Rom. 1.19. <hi>That which may be known of God is manifeſt in them, for God hath ſhewed it to them;</hi> And of the preaching of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel it is ſaid, 2 Cor. 2.14. God maketh manifeſt the ſavour of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113873:5"/>his knowledge, &amp;c. <hi>And ſuch as reſiſt the light, and motion in either of theſe meanes, reſiſt the holy Spirit,</hi> Prov. 1.23, 24. Act. 7.51.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The liberty of giving life to all that believe on him,</hi> 17. Iohn 2. And all theſe come through the efficacy and prevalencie of the Blood, and Sacrifice of Chriſt preſented unto God, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of him; In which reſpect, The Goſpel, where it comes, ſets him forth, as indeed he is; The propitiation for our ſins, <hi>and the Sinnes of the whole world,</hi> Rom. 3.25 1 Iohn 2.2. <hi>The upholder of the world made by him,</hi> Heb. 1 2, 3. <hi>The laver of regeneration, or new birth,</hi> Iohn 3.5.15. Tit. 3.4, 5. <hi>I he Fountain of leanſing, and purificatioons for defilements,</hi> 1 <hi>Iob</hi> 1.7 Zach. 13.1. <hi>The Fountain of life,</hi> Pſal. 36.9. <hi>He in whom God hath given us eternall life, ſo as he that hath him, hath life,</hi> 1 Iohn 5.10, 10, 11, 12. and as page 5. under this figure 3.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Sometimes together with all theſe four former ſences, by the Sufferings, Blood, Death, and Sacrifice of Chriſt ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to, and prevailing with God, is alſo farther meant the ſpirituall Diſcovery and Application of it to, and prevailing efficacy in the hearts and conſciences of ſuch, as through the appearance of grace are brought to believe, Heb. 12.24 To the bloud of ſprinkling, 1 Pet. 1.2. Unto obedience, and ſprinkling of the bloud of Jeſus Chriſt, verſ. 19. The pretious blood of Chriſt, which indeed prevaileth with, and and in thoſe who in ſpirituall Diſcoveries are ſprinkled, and waſhed therewith, in, and with whom it is ſo powerful, and effectuall, That it verily pierceth and melteth the heart for all its ſinfulneſſe, and follies againſt him, and all its hard thoughts, and oppoſitions wherewith it hath pierced him, Zach. 12.10, Acts 2.37. Reconcileth the heart, and powers in their inclination to God, 2 Cor. 5.18, 20. Giveth an eſcape from the intangling pollutions that are in the world, and holding from God through luſts, 2 Peter 1.4. and 2.20, Rev. 5.9. Speaketh peace to the Conſcience, ſo as the Believer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth juſtification, and peace with God thereby, Heb. 12.24. Rom. 4 25. and 5.1.2. Purgeth the Conſcience, Heb. 9.13.14. from the accuſations of ſinne, and charges of the Law, putting in feare, Rom. 7.4.6. and 8.2.3, 34. from its former
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113873:5"/>corrupt way of dictating to ſeek peace, and righteouſneſſe with God, by frames, and performances of its own accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Law. "And alſo from ſpeaking peace from ſuch at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments, Gal. 2.21. Phil. 3 3 7, 8, 9. Iob. 9.15.32.</p>
               <p>Purifieth the heart to a child-like love of God, and Chriſt, and his Government, Heb. 9.14. Gal. 2.20, 21. And ſo renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it with ſpring: of ove ce brethren, 1 Pet. 1.19, 21, 22. And omen, 2 Cor. 5.14. And inclinations to ſerve the living God Tit 3 4.5. Conforming to Chriſt, 2 Cor. 3.3, 18.</p>
               <p>Waſheth, and cleanſeth from ſuch pollutions, as befall Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, 1 John 2.7.</p>
               <p>Sealeth to the Day of redemption, Exod. 12.13, with Epheſ. 1.13. and 4 30.</p>
               <p>And giveth boldneſſe and courage in acceſſe to God, Rom: 5.2. Epheſ. 2.16 18 Heb. 4 16.</p>
               <p>All which are the efficacies of the pretious bloud of Chriſt, ſpiritually applied to, and ſprinkled on the heart; And meant when the Bloud is ſpoken of, as Believers are ſaid to be ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led (redeemed from the world, or vain converſation) and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with it, Heb. 12.24. 1 Pec. 1.19. Acts 20.28. Rev. 5.9. and 1.5.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Sometimes, by theſe tearms, the Sufferings, Blood, Death, and Sacrifice of Chriſt, is ſignified, encluded, and meant; The immenſe, rich, and free mercy, love, or grace of God, in finding out a ranſome, and giving his Son, <hi>That he might ſhew forth love,</hi> Job. 33.24. John 3.15, 16, 17. Epheſ. 2 4 5, 6, 7. And ſo this love made known in the gift of his Sonne, and teſtified in the application of the vertue of his blood, Rev. 1.5. and 5, 9. <hi>In forgiveneſſe of ſinnes,</hi> Epheſ. 1.6.7. <hi>And there-through ſhedding abroad his love in the heart by the holy Ghoſt, begetting love and confidence</hi> Rom: 5 5, 10. <hi>Vniting to, comforting in, and conforming to Chriſt, writing his mind in the heart</hi> 1 Pet. 8.21, 22. 2 Cor. 3.3.18. And herein is love, <hi>That he loved us, and ſent his Son to be the propitiation for our ſins,</hi> 1 John 4.10. and 3 16 And herein is love communicated, <hi>That he hath waſhed us from our ſins in his blood,</hi> Rev. 1.5.</p>
               <p>And ſo when we ſpeak, or in the Scripture read, of the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, Bloud, Death, and Sacrifice of Chriſt, and the love of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113873:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>God to manward, and the hope, and benefit ſet forth to all men thereby; wee are to underſtand it as of the bloud of Chriſt: 1 That ſhed it, and dyed for our ſins, 2 That overcame Death, and roſe for our Juſtification. 3 That by, and with the vertue of this bloud, did through the eternall Spirit effer up himſelf without ſpot to God, and hath thereby obtained eternall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; And 4 that thereby procureth favour, and meanes for the Sons of men, That they might believe, and in belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving be ſaved: And when the Scripture ſpeaketh of ſo much, and no more in any Propoſition for Faith, it ſpeaketh of it, as for the world, John 1.29. <hi>Mer,</hi> 1 Tim: 2.6. <hi>Sinners,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. And ſuch like generall tearms it uſeth, 2 Cor. 5.19. But when we ſpeake, or in the Scripture reade of the Sufferings, Bloud, Death, and ſacrifice of Chriſt, as the vertue and efficacy thereof is found in any, And the peculiar love, and choice pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges thereof affirmed of; Then wee are to underſtand it farther. 5 Of the vertue of that pretious Bloud applyed to, and working in the heart; And 6 of the rich and free love of God teſtified to, and ſhed abroad in the heart thereby; And then, and ſo we are to underſtand it, not only in the foure former ſences, but both in them, and theſe two latter alſo; And ſo it is never ſpoke of in generall for all men, but for the Church, Act, 20.28. Epheſ. 5.25.26, 27, <hi>Believers,</hi> 1 John 1.7. <hi>His called, and choſen ones,</hi> Heb. 9.14 Revel. 1.5. and 5.9.</p>
               <p>And ſo the ſame vertue, and grace of Chriſt by Spirit given and made effectuall.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <q>In reſpect of Chriſt his dying for our ſinnes, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his entring into Heaven by his own bloud, And in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his Application of it to the conſcience And in reſpect of the firſt effects of it ſpeaking Peace,</q> and anſwering Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charges; it is expreſſed by Bloud, or Death, Rom. 8 34.</p>
               <p n="2">2 And in reſpect of the free, and rich love of God appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there-through, and entring the heart; with its cleanſing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing, and renewing operations; It is expreſſed by water, clean water, living water, or water of life, Iſa: 43.3. Epheſ. 3.23. Heb. 10.23. Iohn 4 10. and 7.38.</p>
               <p>And ſo the ſame waſhing is affirmed, as a fruit of his love, <hi>by his Bloud,</hi> Rev. 1.5. <hi>with clean water,</hi> Ezek. 36.25. and Chriſt is
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:113873:6"/>called, <hi>The Fountain of living Waters,</hi> Jer. 17.13.</p>
               <p>And as theſe tearms of Bloud and Water, are uſed to ſet forth the ſame grace diſtinctly, in divers and diſtinct reſpects; ſo one of theſe tearmes, ſometimes comprehends both; As <hi>Bloud,</hi> in Rev. 1.5. and <hi>Waters,</hi> in John 3.5. Tit. 3.4, 5.</p>
               <p>And ſo as Jeſus Chriſt in reſpect of his ſacrifice with the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of it, as offered to God; And by the efficacy of it, as apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to men, was ſhadowed, figured, and typed out by Water, and Bloud, Heb. 9.8, 12, 13, 14, 19. Even ſo his firſt coming, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing the work, his Father gave him to do on Earth:
<list>
                     <item>1 Becauſe of the great, rich, and free love of God, in which he ſent his Son into the World; John 3.16. <hi>To be the Saviour of the world,</hi> 1 John 14.14. <hi>By which he taſted death for every man,</hi> Heb. 2 9. <hi>And in love laid down his life for us;</hi> He is ſaid to have come by water.</item>
                     <item>2 Becauſe of the ſatisfaction he made for us by ſuffering, and dying for our ſins, 1 Cor: 15.3.4. 2 Cor: 5.21. Gal: 3.13. He is ſaid, to have come by Bloud.</item>
                     <item>3 Becauſe, by the eternall Spirit he roſe from the dead, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended, and offered himſelf without ſpot to God, and ſo was ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in the Spirit, Ro: 6.4. 1 Pet: 3.18. Ro: 1.4. 1 Tim: 13.16. <hi>And by that Spirit teſtifieth of himſelf,</hi> Iohn 14.26. and 15.26, 27. It is ſaid, <hi>The Spirit beareth witneſſe,</hi> 1 Iohn 5.6. <hi>This is he that came by water and bloud; not by water only, but by water and bloud, and it is the Spirit that beareth witneſſe, becauſe the Spirit is Truth.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo as there is one God, and three Perſons in one God: <hi>The Father who hath loved us, and given his Son for us,</hi> 1 Iohn 4.10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Son who was made fleſh, and ſo dyed for our ſins, and roſe for our justification,</hi> Iohn 1.14 Rom: 5.25.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Holy Ghoſt, who proceedeth from, and maketh known the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Son,</hi> Matth. 16.16. Ioh. 14.26. and 16.13. So it is ſaid, 1 Iohn 5.7. <hi>There are three that bear record in Heaven; the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Word, and the Holy Ghoſt; And theſe three are one, and ſo the Record is the record of one God.</hi> 1 Iohn 5.10.</p>
               <p>And anſwerably, there are three that bear record on Earth to men, and in the hearts of Believers.</p>
               <p>The Spirit that diſcovers in, and through the Goſpell this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113873:7"/>grace, and enlightens the heart to ſee, and believe, and ſo begets a ſpirituall diſpoſition, <hi>bringing out of darkneſſe into his light,</hi> Matth. 16.16. Iohn 16.7-15. 1 Cor. 2.9.—15.</p>
               <p>The Water, even that rich, free, and immenſe love of God in the Spirits exaltation of Chriſts appearing, Iſa 55.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
               <p>The Bloud, even the propitiation made, ſatisfaction given, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption obtained, righteouſneſſe wrought, and preſented to God, and accepted of him, and now applyed for ſatisfaction to the Believer, Rom: 3.25, 26. and 4.5.24.25. and 5.1.—11. And all theſe agreeing in one; And ſo it is ſaid, 1 Iohn 5.8. There are three that bear witneſſe in Earth; The <hi>Spirit, and the Water, and the Bloud,</hi> and theſe three agree in one: All theſe witneſſes agree in one, and bear forth one record, and the Spirit is he that beareth forth the witneſſe, and he doth it with Water &amp; Bloud, in diſcovery and application of the free grace of God, and the vertue of the precious bloud of Chriſt, Tit. 3.4, 5. And ſo the whole record is the record of God, 1 Iohn 5.10, 11, 12. And this is the record that God hath given of his Sonne, Tha God hath given us eternall life, and this life is in his Son; <hi>He that hath the Son hath life, and he that hath not the Son, hath not life:</hi> And ſo by this whole Diſcourſe, wee may underſtand: That</p>
               <p n="1">1 When the Scripture ſpeakes of grace, or free-love; though for the clearneſſe, purity, refreſhing, and cleanſing effects, it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes it by that metaphor of water; yet it means of that grace, &amp; love, in which Chriſt was given to be a ranſome, and which is teſtified through Chriſt; who by his bloud ſhedding, and with the vertue thereof preſenting, and offering himſelf a ſpotleſſe ſacrifice to his Father, hath obtained eternall redemption, and procured favour to be diſpenſed, and the way of diſpenſation, 1 Iohn 4.10. Rom: 5.5, 6.</p>
               <p n="2">2 And when the Scripture ſpeakes of the Bloud, Death, and Sacrifice of Chriſt, or the redemption effected thereby: It means the Bloud of Chriſt, which through love or grace was ſhed, and preſented to God for us, and is diſcovered to us; and ſo the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption through grace wrought, and in, and through which, grace, or free-love appeareth, Rom: 5.8.-11. Gal: 2.20.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:113873:7"/>
               <p n="3">3 And ſo when the Scripture ſpeaketh of the teaching, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſing, and operation of the holy Ghoſt; It meaneth, that teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, witneſſing, &amp; operation of the Spirit of Chriſt, which by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his Sacrifice, Chriſt ſendeth forth from the Father, and in which he diſcovereth, and witneſſeth the things of Chriſt; and ſo with water and bloud diſcovering free-grace, through the vertue of that pretious Bloud, Iohn 15.26. and 16.7.—15.</p>
               <p>And theſe things are well to be heeded, and digeſted in our hearts, as they are comprehended, and meant; alwayes the moſt of them, and often all of them, in uſing theſe tearms and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions: The Sufferings, Bloud, Death, Ranſome, and Sacrifice of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHHP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The manifold ends of the Sufferings, Bloud, Death, and Sacrifice of Chriſt, as the Scripture diſtinctly ſets them forth.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>FOr the right underſtanding the diſtinct ends of the Death, and Sacrifice of Chriſt, according to Scripture ſence, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion: There are ſome things the Scripture mentions to be fore-underſtood, and heeded of us.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 Of Jeſus Chriſt, according to his double miſſion from the Father into the world; and alſo, according to his double buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in leaving the World, and offering himſelfe to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</item>
                  <item>2 Of Mankind: In reſpect of the double miſery, and enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, they are through the firſt <hi>Adem</hi> fallen into.</item>
                  <item>3 Of the Church: In reſpect of the double need they ſtand in, of the contiouall helpfulneſſe of Chriſt Jeſus.</item>
               </list>
               <p>In the underſtanding, and diſtinct conſideration of all theſe, the divers and diſtinct ends of the Death, and Sacrifice of Jeſus Chriſt will appear clearly.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Concerning Jeſus Chriſt, his coming into the world, and leaving the world.</p>
               <p>Firſt, in reſpect of his miſſion from the Father into the world, it was two-fold:</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:113873:8"/>
               <p n="1">1 He came, and was ſent into the world to be the Saviour of the world, 1 Iohn 4.14. <hi>To ſave finners,</hi> 1 Tim: 1.15. That is, In the nature of man, ſubjected to humane infirmities, Heb. 10.5. <hi>To be made under the Law, to redeeme ſuch as were under the Law,</hi> Gal. 4.4. <hi>And ſo to bear their ſins,</hi> Pſaſm: 40.12. <hi>And ſuffer their Curſe,</hi> Gal: 3.13. <hi>And dye the death of, and for All,</hi> 2 Cor: 5.14. Heb: 2.9. <hi>And ſo dying for their ſins, to riſe for their justifiea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> Rom: 5.25. And ſo he ſaid, Iohn 10.14. <hi>I have power to lay down my life, and I have power to take it again: This Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have I received of my Father:</hi> And ſo he dyed, and roſe to the ends fore-ſhown, page 2 and 3. And in reſpect of this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, his death and ſacrifice was to take away, and be the propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation for, the ſins of the whole world, Heb. 9.26. Iohn 1.29. 1 Iohn 2.2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He came, and was ſent into the world to bear witneſſe to the truth,</hi> Iohn 18 37. <hi>And ſo to be a Preacher of the Goſpell, in the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this great Grace, and Salvation,</hi> Heb: 1.2. and 2.3. <hi>And by his good workes and miracles to winne men to the beliefe and receipt thereof,</hi> Iohn 5.36. and 14.11. <hi>And to give the promiſes of the New Teſtament, and of eternall life, to thoſe that were prevailed with, to believe on him,</hi> Iohn 17.6, 7, 8. and 14.26. and 16.7. And of his miſſion to this Miniſtration, it is ſaid, Rom: 15.8. <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt was a Miniſter of the Circumciſion</hi> (that is, of the Jewes) for the truth of God, &amp;c. And of this miſſion, (when ſome came to him for ſome fruits of the miniſtration thereof) it is, that he ſaid, Matth. 15.24. <hi>I am not ſent, but unto the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of Iſrael.</hi> And larger Commiſſion he gave not to his Diſciples, till he had finiſhed his own courſe, Matth. 10.5, 6. But then he enlarged this miſſion for all Nations, <hi>All the World,</hi> Matth. 28.19. Mark. 16.15. <hi>And ſent them into the world, even as the Father had ſent him into the world.</hi> Iohn 17.18. which can be underſtood but of this his miſſion for miniſtration (for onely himſelf is the propitiation,) Ioh. 20.21. And of this miniſtration alſo he ſaith, John 12 49, 50. <hi>I have not ſpoken of my ſelf, but the Father which ſent me; he gave me a commandement what I ſhould ſay, and what I ſhould ſpeake, And I know that his commandement is life everlaſting; whatſoever I ſpeak therefore, even as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaid unto me, ſo I ſpeake,</hi> John 14.10. And thus he dyed in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113873:8"/>teſtimony of obedience, love, and faithfulneſſe to his Father, Phil. 2.8.—10. <hi>And of love and faithfulneſſe to his ſheep, that had been taught by him,</hi> John 10.15. And ſo to confirme the truth of his Doctrine, 1 Tim. 6.13. And to give us an example to follow his ſteps, in teftifying love, and faithfulneſſe to God, and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, John 15.12, 13. 1 Pet: 2.21. 1 John 3.16. Not to make propitiation for hem, for be it; but to confirme the truth, &amp; te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> love, and faithfulneſſe, and give good example, Epheſ. 5.2.</p>
               <p>But now, if wee conſider of Jeſus Chriſt, according to both his Miſſions together, as to make Propitiation; And in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpell, to give the Promiſes of the New Teſtament to his Diſciples; Then we ſhall find alſo, that he ſo dyed, to confirm, ratifie, and ſeale the New Teſtament of precious Promiſes, <hi>and ſo it was for his called and choſen ones,</hi> Luke 22.20. Heb. 9.15, 16. Gal. 3.15. And thus of his miſſion into the world.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In reſpect of his buſineſſe, in leaving the world, and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring himſelf to the Father; it was alſo two-fold, as Scripture ſheweth.</p>
               <p n="1">1 It was to preſent himſelf as the ranſome, and ſacrifice, with the vertue of his bloud to God for Mankind; and thereby to obtain, and receive to himſelf (or into his owne hands to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) as the publike perſon in the roome of Mankind, remiſſion of ſins, juſtification, fulneſſe of ſpirit, and authority, and to bee the Mediator between God &amp; M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, Heb: 9.12, 14.24 1 Tim: 2.5. <hi>And ſo to be our Peace,</hi> Epheſ: 2.14, 16. <hi>The propitiation for our ſins, and the ſins of the whole world,</hi> 1 John 2.2. <hi>And Wiſdome, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teonſneſſe, Sanctification, and Reslemption for men, and to all that believe in him,</hi> John 1.4. 1 Cor: 1.30.</p>
               <p n="2">2 It was to take on him, and execute his office of Lord and Mediator, and high Prieſts, &amp;c. To ſend forth, tender, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe of the grace and Spirit, which he, as the publike perſon hath received in the humane nature glorified, to enlighten, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, and draw even the rebellious, that they might believe, &amp;c. Pſalm. 68.18. John 1.7.9. and 16.8, 9, 10. And to ſprinkle and waſh the conſciences of Believers, with the ſpiritnall applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his precious bloud, and ſhedding abroad in the heart of Believers, the free, and rich grace appearing there-through, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113873:9"/>comforting, and leading them into all truth, Heb. 12.24 and 9.14. Rev. 1.5. Tit. 3.4 5. Himſelf remaining a husband, and Advocate for them, Epheſ. 5.25, 26, 27. 1 Iohn 2.1. In both which appeares a two-fold end of his blood, &amp; ſacrifice offered:</p>
               <p>The one, the obtaining redemption, &amp;c. to make known, &amp; ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to men, that they might believe, Iohn 3.17. Epheſ. 2.5, 6, 7.</p>
               <p>The other, The communication thereof too, and effectuall operation in Believers, Iohn 17.3. Epheſ 5, 26, 27.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Concerning Mankind, in reſpect of the double miſery, and enmity againſt God, which by falling into ſinne, they fell into.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The firſt is, the miſery and enmity in the very ſtate and condition, into which mankind by ſinne were fallen, which was ſuch as ſtood croſſe to the merciful God, to keep him back from ſhewing any favour, or grace at all to mankind; for the Truth of God requites the Death of man <hi>ſinne being entred,</hi> Gen. 2.17. <hi>And the Iuſtice of God requires the execution of the Curſe on man, that hath fayled of his duty,</hi> Gal. 3.10. And ſo, though God did not upon the fall of man, turne enemy to mankind; But in his beart did pitty him, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.4. And his bowels of compaſſion moved for mankind: ſo as hee would not for that fall, make him as the Divell and his Angels, (ſomething like that ſaid of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Hoſ. 11.6-9.) Yet Truth, and Iuſtice ſtood againſt the ſhewing forth of this mercy, and extending of peace to man-kind: yea, had not the nature of man-kind been polluted and filled with averſneſſe and eumity againſt God upon the fall (as indeed it was;) yet by reaſon of ſinne committed, though it had been but once, and paſſed, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving only guiltineſſe behind it, even that put ſuch enmity in the ſtate and condition of mankind, and made ſuch a pertition between God and mankind, that Truth and Iuſtice would not (without a ſatisfaction) that any mercy ſhould be ſhewed, or peace given him, who had by that offence ſold himſelf from God to Sathan, and thrown himſelf under guilt of ſinne, and deſert of Curſe, and Death; ſo as it brought a neceſſity of infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting curſe and death upon him; which if men ſuffer in their own particular perſons, they can never over-come; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuffering, they can have no remiſſion, Heb. 9 22.</p>
               <p>Now to remedy this miſery, and take away this enmity in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113873:9"/>the ſtate and condition of mankind, Jeſus Chriſt, by the will of God, even the will of his Father, and his own free-will, it being one, and the ſame, with the will of his Father, hath taken the nature of mankind, ſubjected to infirmities, and the cauſe of mankind upon him; and in their ſtead, being made under the Law, under which they were fallen, hath borne all their ſins, and ſuffered all their curſe and ſo dyed for All, That all were dead, and hath riſen again juſt, and free from all their ſins imputed to him; And a vict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rer over all their curſe, and death impoſed on him, and ſo aſcended, and offered up himſelf to God a ſpotleſſe ſacrifice, and a ranſome to God for all men, and God hath acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted it; ſo that for mankind in him, mercy, and truth are met, righteouſneſſe and peace have kified, <hi>Pſul.</hi> 85 10. <hi>And he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the propitiation for the ſins of the whole world,</hi> 1 Iohn 2.2. <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſlaine the enmity,</hi> Epheſ. 2.10. <hi>Having taken out of the way All that (was onely between God, and us, and ſo) was contrary to us,</hi> Col: 2.14. <hi>And ſo hath given himſelf aranſome for All to God, and bought all men of God,</hi> 1 Tim <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 6. 2 Pet. 2.1. And here is the infinite wiſedome, and great love of God, in finding out this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for mankind; which from the beginning, was in himſelf hidden in his own Boſome; And this he brought to paſſe, ſo put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all to death, in the death of his Son, and ſetting them in heavenly places in him, <hi>That he might ſhew forth the riches of his grace,</hi> Epheſ. 2.5, 6, 7. <hi>And ſo war God in Chriſt, reconciling the World to himſelf, not imputing their treſpaſſes to them,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.14, 19. <hi>And ſo hath made a way for himſelf, to ſhew mercy to whom hee will, And opened the doore to life, and immortality for mankind,</hi> 2 Tim. 1.10.</p>
               <p>And thus hath Ieſus Chriſt, by ſhedding his blood, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting it to his Father, redeemed all men of God, and taken the enmity out of their ſtateand condition, and is become their Lord, <hi>Having wrought redemption, and ſalvation in his own body for them, even for all men,</hi> 1 Tim. 2. 5. <hi>Sinners,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. <hi>Vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and his enemies,</hi> And that while they were ſuch, Roan. 5.6. <hi>That he might bring them to God,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.24. and 3.18. And yet unleſſe he proceed to do more for men, then all this, none of them will come into God, Iohn 6.44, 45. For,</p>
               <p n="2">2 There is a miſery, and enmity in the nature of mankind
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113873:10"/>through which he is ſo averſe to God; That though the enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the ſtate and condition be ſlain: And all that which was (between God and Mankind) contrary to them taken out of the way, Epheſ. 2.16. Col. 2.14. yet will not mankind come into God, but remain ſinners, and ungodly ſtill, fooliſh, diſobedient, and deceived, living to themſelves, and after their own luſts, and ſo in enmity againſt God. Rom. 3.10.—19. Epheſ. 2.1, 2, 3. Tit. 3, 2, 3. And ſuch (however ranſomed by Chriſt:) neither can, nor ſhall enter his Kingdom, nor have any inheritance with Chriſt, 1 Cor. 6.9, 10. Gal. 15.19, 20, 21. But if not brought out of this enmity (which is as impoſſible to them to do of themſelves, as to have ranſomed themſelves) their condemnation will bee more fearfull, 2 Theſ. 1.8.</p>
               <p>Now to remedy this miſery, and take this enmity out of the nature of man, Jeſus Chriſt aſcended to Heaven, and with the vertue of that bloud he ſhed for mankind, having offered up himſelf a ſpotleſſe Sacrifice to God, and obtained eternall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and received all fulneſſe of Power, Authority, and Spirit, as the publike perſon in the humane nature glorified. Act. 2.31.32. Pſalm. 68.18. Doth ſend forth of that Spirit (in the meanes he uſeth) at one time or other, to enlighten, and move at the hearts of men, Iohn 1.9. To reprove, and convince them of the ſinfulneſſe in themſelves, &amp; the vanity of all their Idols, and all righteouſneſſe of their own working, and of the fulneſſe of that righteouſneſſe, and life in him, Iohn 16.8, 9, 10. And ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them, Prov. 8.4.5, 6. Iſa 45.22. and 55.1, 2. That in their tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at his reproofe, he may power out his Spirit, and make known his words to them, Prov. 1.23. That ſo through him they might believe, and be ſaved, Iohn 1.5, 7. and 3.7. And though all reſiſt, and go out of the way, Rom. 3.10.—19. And that this is the great condemnation, when light comes, to love, or chuſe darkneſſe rather, Iohn 3.19. And he might juſtly give them all up, and be righteous, Rom: 3.5, 6. yet for a time, he uſeth pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſtriveth with them, Gen. 6.3. That they might repent, Rom: 2.4. And to ſome he giveth more abundance of his grace, and overcomes them, as Bullocks unaccuſtomed to the yoke; Ier. 31.18, 20. Iſa 30.18. And brings them in to believe, Epheſ. 2.7, 8, 9, 10. Phil: 1.29. And theſe he redeemeth with his preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113873:10"/>blood, by preſenting, and applying it cloſe to their heart, ſprinkling it thereon, and diſcovering ſuch free, and infinite riches of grace therethrough, that all things elſe, though never ſo fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought of as gainfull; appeares to them as loſſe in compariſon of this grace, allureing to win Chriſt, and be found in him: And ſoe (as we by of our Children from their vanities to their bookes,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.7, 8, 9.</note> &amp;c. with gifts) he buyeth, and purchaſeth us with his blood from our vaine luſts, hopes, and converſations, and from among men unto God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18.19. <hi>Reu.</hi> 5.9. And then by the ſpirituall application of the vertue of his blood purgeth the conſcience from dead workes to ſerve the living God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. And ſo in his love, waſheth us from our ſins in his own blood, <hi>Reu.</hi> 1.5. And thoſe whom he hath not onely bought of God, (as he hath done all men, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6.) but alſo purchaſed them unto God from among men, and waſhed them in his love from their ſinns, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Reu.</hi> 5.9. and 1.5. <hi>Iohn</hi> 13.8. Theſe, and theſe onely are his Church, and pecular people, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.27. In whoſe ſoule and body he worketh ſalvation, through the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of that ſalvation which the hath wrought in his own body.</p>
               <p>And in this conſideration of the double enmity to God into which man fell, and the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>cy in Chriſt appeares three ends of the Sufferings, Blood, Death, and Sacrifice of Chriſt: namely two ends of the preſentation, and offering it to God; one to take away the enmity that was in the State, and condition of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.16. The other, to receive ſpirit to ſend forth in the declaration of this grace, to reconcile men to God, that the enmity in there nature might be removed, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.7. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. and one end of the ſpirituall preſentation, and applycation of it to the heart, and conſcience of men, namely, to purge the conſcience, and waſh them from their ſins, and renew them to God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. Concerning the Church of God on earth, in reſpect of the double need they ſtand in of the continuall helpfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The believers, though made free in Chriſt, and their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence purged, their heart renewed, and ſpirit made alive for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe ſake, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.36. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.10. yet for the time of their warfare, there is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining of the old Diſpoſition, although unthroned from the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113873:11"/>heart, and weakned yet working in all the powers, and facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſoule, and parts and members of the body, luſting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſpirit, and to ſatisfie the affections, and luſts of the fleſh, and attempting to leade Captive to the law of ſin, and death, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14.—24. Beſides the manifold temptations from the world, by Cuſtoms, Promiſes, Threats, Aſurements, Terrors, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2 16. And alſo from Satan takeing advantage from the fleſh, and the world, and adding ſtrength to the luſts, and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations thereof, adding his own fiery and he liſh ſuggeſtions, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. whereby it falleth out, that in many things, we (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Believers) offend all, <hi>Iames</hi> 3 1. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.8 10.</p>
               <p>Which remaining evill, and off nees overtaken, which doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file and make unmeete to appeare before God; and if they be not pardoned and purged away, they will exclude from his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and bring to death againe, <hi>Pſal</hi> 5.4, 5, 6.</p>
               <p>Now the Blood of Jeſus, and the grace therethrough extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is the onely thing that can purifie, and cleanſe from theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filements, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. <hi>Reu.</hi> 1.5. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.9. So that here is ſtill need of coming to Chriſt for his cleanſing herewith, <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.1. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.9.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The believers having ſo many, &amp; great enemies fighting againſt them <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.12. ſo many and great ſufferings to undergoe, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.22. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12. And ſo many, and great ſerviſes of love to goe forth in, till they be wholly conformed to Chriſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6. and 3.12.-16. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.1.-6. And they having no good thing dwelling in their fleſh. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18. nor ability in themſelves for a good thought, as of themſelves, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5. ſo as unleſſe he work all for, and in them, there will be no abiding peace, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 26.12.</p>
               <p>Great need have they therefore of his continuall preſence, and ſending forth ſupplyes of ſpirit to overcome their enemyes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.19 20. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20. to ſupport in ſufferings, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 43.1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. to ſanctifie them throughout, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23.24. And to comfort, teach, and lead into all truth, and to the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 54 13.14. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.26 and 16.13.14.15. And ſo to perfect all that concerneth them, <hi>Pſal</hi> 138.8. And for this cauſe is he by vertue of his precious Blood, and Sacrifice, an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate, and great High-Prieſt, and Mediatour of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113873:11"/>at his Fathers right hand for believers that are his called and choſen ones, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.1.-6. &amp; 8. &amp; 9.15.</p>
               <p>And in this conſideration of the Churches need of Chriſt, and his way of ſupply, we may ſee one end of his continual preſenting the vertue of his Blood and Sacrifice before his Father, and apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to the hearts and conſciences of his people both together, to keep them cleane before his Father, and to cleanſe, purifie, and conform them to himſelfe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. And ſo in reſpect of both his preſentation of his Sacrifice to his Father, and his gracious and ſpirituall application of the ſame to believers. It is ſaid, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5-25, 26.27. Chriſt alſo loved the Church, and gave himſelfe for it, that he might ſanctifie and cleanſe it with the waſhing of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. by the word; that (as he preſents it in himſelfe ſpotleſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Father, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.22. ſo) he might preſent it to himſelfe a glorious Church, not having ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing, but that it ſhould be holy and without blemiſh, And in the right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of theſe things, we may underſtand the ends of the Sufferings, Blood, Death, and Sacrifice of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the ends of the ſheeding his blood, and ſo of his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and dying, was
<list>
                     <item>1. To ſatisfie for the ſinne of the world, and ſo to fulfill the truth of God, and ſatisfie Diuine Juſtice, and anſwer the Law, and aboliſh death, as is foreſhewn, page 2.</item>
                     <item>2. To confirm and ratifle the new Teſtament of pretious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, for all that through the heavenly call beleeve on him, as is ſhewn page 14.</item>
                     <item>3. To teſtifie obedience, love, and faithfulneſſe in his Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo to confirme his doctrine, and give all his Diſciples an example, as is ſhewn, p. 13.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, the ends of the vertue of this his pretious blood and death in offering himeelfe a ſpotleſſe ſacrifice to his Father, Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſheweth to be
<list>
                     <item>1. That he might be the Propitiation for the ſins of the world, as page 3.4.6.7.</item>
                     <item>2. That he might obtain eternall redemption for mankind, and procure ſome mercy, means, and patience to be uſed towards them, as pages, 5, 6, &amp; 13.</item>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:113873:12"/>
                     <item>3. That he might be the Mediator between God and men, as page 4.12.</item>
                     <item>4. That he might be the great high Prieſt, Prophet, King, and ſo the Advocate for, and of his Church, p. 15.16.12.</item>
                     <item>5. That through him by his Spirit there might be a ſhewing, declaration, and tender of the grace of God to men, to call them, leſſe clearly in his workes of creation, and providence, and more fully and clearly in the Goſpel of ſalvation preached to men, as p. 6.12.14.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, the ends of his ſpirituall diſcovery, tender, and appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of his pretious blood, and ſacrifice to men, Scripture ſhews to be,
<list>
                     <item>1. To convince men of ſinne, and the vileneſſe of ſin in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the vanity of all thier own wiſdome, and righteouſneſſe to help them, and of the compleat righteouſneſſe that is in him; thereby to empty them, and pierce their hearts, and ſubmit them to himſelfe, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.21. Phil. 3.7, 8. Joh. 16.8-10. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.34.</item>
                     <item>2. To purchaſe and redeem theſe convinced from among men, and from their Idols, and vain converſation, unto God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18.19. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. &amp; 26.18.</item>
                     <item>3. To waſh, and cleanſe theſe his ſo purchaſed, in the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the freeneſſe and abundance of his grace, through his pretious blood, enlightning, enlivening, comforting, ſanctifying and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them to the inheritance, <hi>Eoh.</hi> 5.25, 26.27.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>And theſe things conſidered diſtinctly, as the Scripture ſets them forth, lead to the right underſtanding of the ends of Chriſts death and ſacrifice, when it is ſpoke of in reſpect of his dying, and blood-ſhedding. And when it is ſpoke of in reſpect of that, and alſo his preſenting himſelfe with the vertue of that, to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and when it is ſpoke of in both theſe former reſpects, and alſo together therewith, in reſpect of his ſpirituall diſcovery, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and application thereof to men; in which is variety of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the ſenſe and ſignification.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:113873:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A Digreſſion, ſhewing how theſe things were ſhadowed in the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and Ordinances of the firſt Teſtament, or the Law.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>A Perfect image made by a curing limmer may clearly preſent the viſage &amp; complexion of him whoſe Image it is, though it have no life, and ſo neither ſee nor breathe, &amp;c. But a ſhadow, or the firſt rude draught will not doe ſo much; onely may diſcover, that it is to be of a man, or a woman, and not of a beaſt: but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man or woman, or whom it ſheweth not as the Image finiſht (in which the ſhadow paſſeth) doth. Now the law had the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of good things to come, but not the very image of the things: they were paterns and figures of heavenly things for the time preſent, but not a full demonſtration of them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.1. &amp; 9.9.23. Now, then, if we call to mind,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The offering for ſin, to make Atonement, was firſt ſlain, and after that the blood ſprinkled at the Altar, and on the Atonement-day, before the Mercy-ſeat; and the people afflicted in themſelves, and bleſſed by the Prieſt, <hi>Lev.</hi> 9.—15.22. &amp; 16. <hi>per totum,</hi> ſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; Jeſus delivered to death for our ſinnes, and preſenting himſelfe with the vertue of his blood to the Father, to make the Atonement, &amp; obtain redemption for us; and his bleſſing us, in ſprinkling his blood on our hearts, melting and purging the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. &amp; 9.12.14.24. &amp; 10.1.—19.</p>
               <p>The Paſſover, a <hi>Lamb without blemiſh,</hi> &amp; ſlain, and then the blood wth a bunch of hyſſop dipt therin, ſprinkled on the two ſide-Poſts, and the upper doore Poſts, that the ſtriking Angel might paſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. And then the fleſh roaſted with fire, eaten; Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed Jeſus Chriſt the Lamb of God, that taketh away the ſin of the world, <hi>John</hi> 1.29. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.26. His dying for our ſins, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.3.4. And by his Spirit ſprinkling the vertue of his blood on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving heart, without which no ſafety, <hi>Heb,</hi> 12.24. and our feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on him by faith, without which no eternall life, <hi>John</hi> 6.35.36. ſo that bloodſhed preſented to the Lord, and applied to ſuch as come to the Sacrifices, are all held forth diſtinctly, as diſtinct and divers works.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For the people that came to theſe Sacrifices, for whom
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113873:13"/>blood was not onely ſhed, but preſented to God, and who had the atonement, and ſuch reconciliation as was thereby affoorded, there was yet provided a water of Purification to cleanſe them from defilements, when they befell them, and the defiled perſon not cleanſed with it, might not approach to the holy things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out danger of death: now it was not enough, There was for them a water of purification, and it was right, nor that it was put in a veſſell, and running water put thereto; unleſſe a clean perſon dip with a branch of Hiſſop, and ſprinkle him that is uncleane, hee remains unclean, and muſt die: by Sprinkling, is Cleanſing.</p>
               <p>And doth not this ſhadow out Jeſus Chriſt, the fountain of cleanſing, and Laver of regeneration, and purification right with with God, yet cleaſing none in their own hearts, &amp;c. with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out application and ſpirituall ſprinkling, <hi>Heb</hi> 9.13, 14. &amp; 12, 24. <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.4, 5. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25. Conſider and compare the Scriptures, and ſay,
<list>
                     <item>1, Did not the red Hyfer ſlain without the Camp, and her fleſh burnt,<note place="margin">Numb. 19.2.3.5.</note> 
                        <hi>Numb.</hi> 19.2, 3, 5. ſhadow out Jeſus that knew no ſin, made ſin for us, and ſuffering without the gate: and after in the power of the Spirit, and fire of his love, offering up his whole ſelfe a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to God for us? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21, <hi>Heb,</hi> 9.14. &amp; 10.12. &amp; 13.12.</item>
                     <item>2.<note place="margin">Verſ. 9.</note> Did not the remainders, or aſhes of the Heyfer, ſhadow forth the remaining Records, Teſtimonies, and vertues of the death and ſacrifice of Jeſus, who died for our ſinnes, and roſe for our juſtification,<note place="margin">Verſ. 4.</note> and preſented his ſacrifice to God, and applieth it to us, (as was ſhadowed by the blood ſprinkled before the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 15.1-4. <hi>Heb,</hi> 9.12.13.14. And is not this the water of Separation, or Purification from uncleanneſſe, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5</item>
                     <item>3.<note place="margin">Verſ 9.</note> Did not the clean Place without the Camp, where theſe aſhes were kept for a purification for ſin, ſhadow forth the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of Chriſt, or word of grace, which J. Chriſt by his Spirit hath breathed, and cauſed to be written, and therein declared and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and kept as in record, the truth and vertue of the blood-ſhed, death and ſacrifice of Chriſt, and the offering it to the Father, and its prevalency with him, and for whom; and his tender and appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of it, and the vertue thereof, and in whom; Are not all the ſayings hereabout plain,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.1.—4.</note> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.12.13. &amp; 1.2. Faithfull, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi>
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:113873:13"/>1.15. True, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16.—19. And in righteouſneſſe nothing fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, perverſe, equivocall, or wreathed in them, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.6, 7, 8, 9. &amp; 22.20, 21. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.10. That we may rather take thoſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings as they expreſſe the matter, then any other ſayings, or gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they are very righteous and faithfull; his word is very pute, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.138. The inſpiration of the Spirit of truth, 2 Tim. 3.16.</item>
                     <item>4. Did not the aſhes of the burnt Heyfer of Purification for ſinne, and running water put thereto in a veſſell, ſhadow forth the Word of Grace, ſetting forth the vertue of the death and ſacrifice of Chriſt inſpired, and put in the hearts of the ſervants of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.18.19. and his free and rich grace, and love appearing therein, ſhed abroad thereby by the holy Ghoſt in the heart of thoſe, whom he hath brought to beleeve in Chriſt, and ſo united them to him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. and ſo filled them with his love, that it ſprings up like love in them, that conſtrains them to declare this grace, and beſeech others to accept it, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14, 15.19. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21, 22. for which cauſe they are called Stewards and Miniſters of this grace, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. and ſaid to have this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in earthen veſſels, that the excellency of the power may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be of God, and not of them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. and ſo are called choſen veſſels unto God, to beare his name, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.15.</item>
                     <item>5 Did not the clean perſon, taking Hiſſop, dipping it in the water, &amp; ſprinkling the unclean; ſhadow forth <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> the juſt, who by his own Spirit ſtirreth this grace in the hearts of his ſervants, and giveth them what to ſpeak, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. &amp; 5.14. 1 <hi>Cor,</hi> 2.12.13. and giveth proof of his own ſpeaking in their miniſtration, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. Making manifeſt the ſavour of his knowledge by them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. and himſelfe by his Spirit turning the heart of men to God, <hi>Acts</hi> 11, 21. and weighing his mind in the heart of theſe ſo turned to beleeve in him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. further minding and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them that they have heard, <hi>John</hi> 14.26. and taking off the things of Chriſt, and ſhewing to them, <hi>John</hi> 16.14 and ſo ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and waſhing them with this water of purification (the vertue of the pretious blood of Chriſt, and his infinite love ſtreaming there-through) melting, cleanſing, comforting, renewing, &amp;c, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.13.14. &amp; 12.24. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25. without which a man, (notwithſtanding all the former) remains unclean ſtill.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:113873:14"/>
               <p>In all this alſo is ſhadowed the ſeverall diſtinct ends of the death and ſacrifice of Chriſt, as preſented to God, and as applied to men.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the Iſraelites needing, and having in their travels the Cloud, as the teſtimony of Gods preſence to guide them, and his mighty arm to lead them, uphold and defend them, and Manna from heaven, and water out of the Rock to ſuſtain and refreſh them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.21, 22. &amp; 15.2.12. &amp; 16.17. ſhadowed forth our need of, and Chriſt his gracious vouchſafing to be our Advocate, (by vertue of his ſacrifice) at his Fathers right hand, from thence ſending forth his holy Spirit to continue his preſence with us, and give in his promiſes, and ſo to teach, guide, comfort and ſtrengthen us againſt temptations, and to goe through all ſufferings in alll ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of love, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.1, 2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14.15, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.14.26. &amp; 15.26. &amp; 16.14.</p>
               <p>And ſo in this digreſſiu to ſee how things were ſhadowed, we may view the ends of Chriſts ſacrifice fore-mentioned, as alſo that which followes to be ſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The neceſſity of the Sufferings, Blood, Death, and Sacrifice of Chriſt. It is ſhewn in that already ſaid.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>FIrſt, for Chriſt his ſhedding of his bloud, and dying for us, it was altogether neceſſary: for (<hi>Heb.</hi> 9.22.) without ſhedding of blood is no remiſſion of ſinnes. The truth of God makes a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity for the ſinner to die, and without the death of the ſinner cannot be fulfilled, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.20. The juſtice of God makes a neceſſity for the ſinner to ſuffer the curſe, and without the ſinner doe ſuffer, the curſe cannot be ſatisfied, <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.15-26. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. And as nothing without ſhedding of blood &amp; death, can fulfill truth, and ſatisfie juſtice: ſo no blood and death, but the blood and death of Man, the very nature that ſinned, can ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.4. And if particular men ſhould ſuffer this curſe and death in their own perſons, they could never overcome, but muſt periſh in that ſuffering for ever, and ſo can neither ſuffer for themſelves nor for another, to procure a way for remiſſion of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113873:14"/>ſinns, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.7 8. neither indeed to make ſatisfaction for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, will the Blood, and Death of any man ſerve, unleſſe the ſame be a juſt, and an innocent man that hath no ſin of his own to ſatisfie for, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.26.27. Yea even the blood of a juſt man, unleſſe he be, as the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall, a publike man, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. And made (as all men by the fall became under the law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4. yea unleſſe this man be alſo the Sonne of God, even God-man,) it will not be ſufficient <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.5-10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21.23.</p>
               <p>And this man, God-man, even Ieſus Chriſt being come, and as the publike perſon made under the law, when he had lived thirty-three yeares, and upward an innocent life, ſo as noman could accuſe him of ſinne, <hi>Iohn</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 46. yea in all righteouſneſſe, and holyneſſe, and fulneſſe of good workes, and ſpent about three yeares in miniſtration of the Goſpel; yet would not all this his righteous working, though accompanied with many miracles, and with frequent faſting, prayers, and teares make ſatisfaction for the ſin of mankind, without his Death, and Blood; to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct us wherein (and not in any unwillingneſſe to ſuffer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the will of the Father, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.5.-10.) He uttered this prayer, <hi>Mat</hi> 26.39. If it be poſſible; let this Cupp paſſe from me, &amp;c. And ſo that which the High-Prieſt ſpake not of himſelfe, but by propheſie concerning the nation of the Jewes, <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.50. It is true; for all mankind; It was altogether, neceſſary for mankind, that Jeſus Chriſt ſhould dye, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10.13.</p>
               <p n="2">2 For Jeſus Chriſt once dead to riſe againe, and aſcend to the right hand of God, and to preſent the vertue of this his own blood, in offering himſelfe a ſpotleſſe ſacrifice to his Father for mankind; This alſo was altogether neceſſarie: for, however truth had fulfilling, and juſtice had ſatisfying in his blood-ſhed, and death; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. Yet if he had not riſen from the Dead, and aſcended with the vertue of his own blood into the Heavens, and there offered himſelfe a ſpotleſſe Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to God for mankind; There could have been no Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, no redemption, no eternall life, and inheritance obtained, and received by Chriſt into his own hands to diſpenſe to men, nor any dore opened to ſhew forth, and diſpenſe this grace to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113873:15"/>men, that by repentance, and faith they might come into Chriſt, and receive the ſame, nor could there have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſurrection of their bodyes after Death, nor exerciſe of Chriſts Lordſhip over them, in abſolving, or condemning ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Goſpel, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.25. He was raiſed againe for our juſtification, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.17. If Chriſt be not raiſed; ye are yet in your ſinns, verſe 20. But now Chriſt is riſen from the Dead: <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12. By his own blood he entred in once into the moſt h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly place: having obtained eternall redemption, verſe 24. He entred into Heaven it ſelfe, <hi>Reu.</hi> 1.18. I am he that liveth, and was Dead, and beholde I am alive for evermore, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.11. God hath given us eternall life, and this life is in his Sonne, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. who hath aboliſhed Death, and brought life, and mortality to light by the Goſpel, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.7. &amp;c. It is expedient for you that I goe away; for if I goe not away the Comforter will not come unto you: But if I depart, I will ſend him to you; he ſhall reprove the world, &amp;c. verſe 18.11. He will guide you into all truth, &amp;c. verſe 13.14.15. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. Thou haſt aſcended on high, thou haſt led Captivity Captive, thou haſt received gifts in the man (for men, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.33. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8.) yea even for the Rebellious, that the Lord God might dwell among them, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.30.31. Him hath God exalted at his right hand, to be a Prince, and a Saviour to give repentance unto <hi>Iſrael</hi> and forgivneſſe of ſinns, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.30. God raiſed him from the dead &amp;c. to verſe 39. verſe 47. I have ſet thee to be a light to the Gentiles, that thou ſhouldeſt be for ſalvation to the ends of the Earth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.18. And he ſhall ſhew Judgement to the Gentiles; If there be no reſurrection from the Dead, then Chriſt is not Riſen, and if Chriſt be not Riſen; then our preaching is vaine, and your faith is alſo vaine, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.13.-20. But now Chriſt is riſen from the dead, and become the firſt fruits of them that ſleep. verſe 21. for ſince by man came Death, By man alſo the reſurrection from the dead, and verſe 22. &amp;c. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.9 to this end, Chriſt both dyed, and roſe, and revived that he might be the Lord, both of dead, and living, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.36. He is Lord of all, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. For we muſt all appeare before the judgement-Seat of Chriſt, &amp;c. And of this he hath given aſſurance to all men in that he hath
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113873:15"/>raiſed him from the Dead. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31.</p>
               <p>All which ſhewes the neceſſity of Chriſts reſurrection, and aſcenſion, and with the verrue of his own bloud, preſenting and offering himſelfe to God in the Heavens for men: to the ends fore-ſhown.</p>
               <p n="3">3 For Jeſus Chriſt that hath dyed, and riſen, and with the vertue of his own bloud entred the Heaven, and by the eternall Spirit offered himſelf a ſpotleſſe ſacrifice to God for men, Alſo by the ſame Spirit to diſcover this grace, thereby to call, and draw in men to him, and then to ſprinkle and waſh them with the preſentation, and application of the vertue of his pretious bloud; And by his grace there-through diſcovered to renew them, unite, and conforme them to Chriſt. This alſo is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſary in reſpect of men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eceit, and enjoyment of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, eternall life, and inheritance; for however, this ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which Jeſus Chriſt hath wrought, the redemption, juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and eternall life he by himſelf in his own body, as the Publike man obtained for men with God, be ſuch, and ſo recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by him for mankind, That it may be truly ſaid of him, and in reſpect of what he hath, as the Publike perſon done, obtained received, and hath in his own hands to diſpenſe, that he is the Saviout of the world, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.42. And hath by himſelf made pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of our ſins, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. and 9.26. and obtained eternall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12.50. That as <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23, 24. All have ſinned, and come ſhort of the glory of God, being juſtified freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Chriſt Jeſus, and Rom. 5.18. As by the offence of one, unto all men to condemnation, even ſo by the righteouſneſſe of one, unto all men to juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of life; yea, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.11. God hath given us eternall life, and this life is in his Son: yet notwithſtanding all this, Unleſſe this grace be ſo diſcovered by the Spirit to men, that they be drawn in to Chriſt, and hee by his Spirit ſprinkle his bloud on their heart, and ſhed abroad his love therein, and ſo waſh, and renew them, they cannot in their own particular perſons be juſtified, and partake of eternall life, and receive the inheritance with him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25, 26. Tit. 3.4.5. And this neceſſity of his ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and waſhing the Conſcience with his pretious bloud, may be ſeen true, in many reſpects.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:113873:16"/>
               <p n="1">1 In reſpect of ſinne, It ſufficeth not for bringing mens par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons into the Kingdome of Heaven, That ſinne is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, for by the ſacrifice of Chriſt, and ſo purged away by him as the publike perſon, that he in the room: of all mankind ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpotleſſe at the Throne of God; But its requiſite alſo, that it be purged out of the Conſcience, and out of the nature, and converſation of ſuch particular perſons as enter that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; yea, and though this work be not as the former, done at once in the very act of his preſentation, and offering himſelf to God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. and 9.12. and 10.10, 12. But by degrees; yet thoſe Degrees are according to the entrance, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11. Rom. 8.23. And ſo its ſaid, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.21. There ſhall in no wiſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into it any thing that defileth, neither whatſoever worketh abomination, or a lye, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9. The unrighteous ſhall not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Kingdome of God. Be not deceived, neither Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, nor Idolater, nor Adulterers, nor effeminate, nor abuſers of themſelves with mankind, nor Theeves, nor covetous, nor Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, nor Revilers, nor Extortioners, ſhall inherit the Kingdom of God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19, 20, 21. The work of the fleſh are manifeſt, which are Adultery, Fornication, uncleanneſſe, laſciviouſneſſe, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, witchcraft, hatred, variance, emulation, ſtrife, ſeditions, hereſies, envyings, murthers, drunkenneſſe, revilings, and ſuch like, They which doe ſuch things ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.5. no Whoremonger, nor unclean perſon, nor co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous man who is an Idolator, hath any inheritance in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt, and of God; ſo that ſuch, unleſſe they be waſhed, juſtified, purged, and ſanctified, they cannot enter; nor can any ſorrowes, tears, ſacrifices, works of righteouſneſſe of their owne waſh of the guilt, and take away the venome of theſe ſinnes, nor make their hearts and natures new, It is only the pretious bloud and ſacrifice of Chriſt, which by the eternall Spirit he offered to God: by the ſame Spirit diſcovered to, and ſprinkled on the heart, enabling to believe, in which Peace is ſpoken to the heart remiſſion of ſins received, and liberty by faith to reckon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves according to Chriſt, and as they are in him, who by his Spirit worketh his mind in them, and conformeth them to him ſelf, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. and 5.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25, 26. and 5.1.—5.1 C <hi>o</hi> 6.11. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.4.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:113873:16"/>
               <p n="2">2 By reaſon of the blindneſſe, darkneſſe, and enmity, that by reaſon of ſinne is the nature of man: For it ſufficeth not for mens perſonall entrance into the Kingdome, that in, and through Chriſt, God is light, and in him is no darkneſſe at all, unleſſe men be brought into this light, and this light be in them that they may walke in it, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.5.7. and 2.8.9. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.4.5. nor yet is it enough for mens perſonall entrance into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that the enmity in their State, and condition be removed, unleſſe alſo the enmity in their nature be removed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.21. neither is there any ſtudy, or labour of man in any wiſdome or workes of righteouſneſſe of his own, that can bring him into this light of God, and take this enmity againſt God out of his nature; but onely the ſpirit of Jeſus Chriſt (which when he offered up himſelfe a Sacrifice to God for men, he received in the man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.18.) Diſcovering and teſtifying of Chriſt, and the vertue of his Blood, and the rich grace appearing therethrough, that brings out of darkeneſſe into his marvelous light, and reconcileth the heart, and powers to God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.26. and 15.26. and 16.14.15. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.4.5.12.13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7.9. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14 18, 19, 20. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</p>
               <p n="3">3 In reſpect of the firſt, and naturall Birth, and that which men are by propagation, and nature from the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> whoſe Image they therein, and thereby partake of, and beare, and ſo are by nature dead in ſins, and treſpaſſes, Children of wrath, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.46.48.49. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.5. <hi>Iob.</hi> 14.4. and 15.14. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3 So that however Chriſt as the publike perſon hath wrought ſalvation in himſelfe for men with God, and is juſtified, and glorified at Gods right hand; yet unleſſe a man be borne againe, borne from above, even of water, and the Spirit, the free and rich grace of God manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Application of the precious Blood of Chriſt to the heart, And that by the holy Spirit of Chriſt in that Knowledge, and Application of the precious Blood, giving him an eſcape from the Pollutions that are in the world through luſt, and makeing him partaker of the Divine nature; That ſo as he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partooke of miſery by having his being from <hi>Adam,</hi> and partaking of his nature, he may partake of juſtification and lyfe, by having his being in Chriſt, and partaking of his Divine nature; without
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113873:17"/>this new Birth; he cannot enter the Kingdome of God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.3.5.6. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17.20. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.3, 4, 5, 6, 7. And indeed, till ſo borne from above, men are Aliens from God, and Chriſt, and the lyfe of God in Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. and 4.18. And however it be true, that in Chriſt, and that he hath done, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and received, God hath given us eternall lyfe, and this life is in his Sonne: yet this is alſo true, that whoever of us hath not the Sonne, the ſame hath not lyfe, lyfe is received, and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed onely in the receite, and enjoyment of the Sonne, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.11.12. And that is, when through his ſpirituall Diſcovery and ſprinkling of his Pretious Blood, and Diſpenſation of his grace there-through to the heart, a man is brought to believe on him; And ſo quickoned, borne, and renewed, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.5.10. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 55.1.—9. And ſo ſuch he gives the priviledges of the Sonnes of God; who to receive him, and are ſo borne, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.12.13. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13.14. So that the truth is, the neceſſity in reſpect of mens per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall entrance into the Kingdome, and being eternally ſaved, to be ſpiritually ſprinkled, and waſhed with the Blood of Chriſt; is ſo great, as there can be no greater, there being no other way to the enjoyment of remiſſion of ſins, Humiliation for ſinn, Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before God, wiſdome, righteouſneſſe, Sanctification, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, nor any fruitfulneſſe that God will accept; But by this pretious Blood of Chriſt which he ſhed, and with the vertue thereof offered himſelfe to God by his ſpirit ſprinkled on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: And his rich, and abundant grace, manifeſted through the ſame, by the ſame ſpirit ſhed abroad in the heart, and ſo lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God, in which reſpect Chriſt onely is the way for all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to the Father, and without whom there is no coming to God, nor doing any thing he will accept: <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3, 25. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.4. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18.19. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.17.18. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.10.—19.</p>
               <p>This neceſſity of Chriſt his ſprinkling his Blood on the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the whole Goſpel, and all the writings thereof, and Teſtimonies and examples therein do ſhew, and ſo doth the Law alſo rightly underſtand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:113873:17"/>
               <head>CHAPTER 6.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A digreſſion, to ſhew how the Law ſhewes the neceſſity of this Blood-ſhedding, Death, and Sacrifice of Chriſt:</p>
               </argument>
               <p>BEfore, in Chapter 4. was ſhewn, how the ends of the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Blood, Death, and Sacrifice of Chriſt was ſhaddowed in the leviticall law, and types of old, and the neceſſity of the acting, preſenting, and applying the ſame, now if we view the morall law, even the law of workes, the holy, and righteous law of God; It alſo will ſhew, and urge the neceſſity of the Death, and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſt, in all the reſpects aforeſaid, and that every way: If we conſider this holy law, 1. In reſpect of it ſelfe, 2 In reſpect of the ends of giving it, and 3. In reſpect of the power it hath in this lyfe in the conſciences of men till ſet free by Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The Law it ſelfe is holy, ſpirituall, and righteous:<note place="margin">Rom. 7.12. Mat. 22.38.39. 1 Iohn 3.4. Rom. 7.7. Iam. 2.10. Mail. 1.6.</note> It is a holy Law, pointing us all to live to God the holy one, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Will, and Commands, enjoyning to love God with all our heart, ſoule, and ſtrength, and our neighbour as our ſelves, and to walke in that love of God, and our neighbour, and ſo it forbiddeth every ſinn, and commandeth every Duty: And it is a ſpirituall Law, requiring the Inmoſt heart, and Spirit; And the utmoſt and perfect obedience of the whole man; ſo as the leaſt riſing motion to any evill it forbiddeth and concludeth it ſinn: yea and the leaſt want of the through, ſpirituall, and perfect per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of all, or any one point it condemneth for ſinn, and for that ſinn putteth under the guilt of the breach of the whole Law: And it is a righteous law requiring of man noe more then is due from man to God, and which ſhall be the righteouſneſſe of a man before God, if he fulfill it, ſo as the law find no fault in him,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.13. and 10.5. Gal. 3.10.12. Rom. 6. Deut. 27.15-26.</note> and it promiſeth life to the obſervers, and will performe it, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the righteouſneſſe of the Law, and it ſentenceth to death, and curſe every one that ſinneth againſt any point, or cometh ſhort of the leaſt title it requireth; ſo that this Law is holy, ſpirituall, and righteous in its Commandements of Duty, In its Juſtifying the doers of it, in its convincing the Tranſgreſſors, and in its leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113873:18"/>Tranſgreſſors to the curſe; And indeed ſo holy, ſpirituall, and righteous is this law, that in their own perſons, and performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, noe one man ſince <hi>Adam</hi> fell, but onely Jeſus Chriſt our Lord hath fulfilled it to every <hi>Jota,</hi> or can be Juſtified, and have lyfe by it: For.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Though a man had ſuch knowledge of the Law, that he could ſee all his Duty therein required, And had alſo ſuch a heart to keepe this Law that he had reſpect to every Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in it, and did his utmoſt to avoid every ſinn, and to perform every duty, and that conſtantly in all his converſation: yet if he attaine not to the utmoſt the Law requireth, but fayle of that, if it were but once, and but in one point; the Law puts him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the guilt of ſinn, and danger of Curſe, and Death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. the wages of ſinn is Death, and <hi>James</hi> 2.10. whoſoever ſhall keepe the whole Law, and yet offend in one poynt, he is guilty of all, and <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. Curſed is every one that continueth not in all things that are written in the booke of this Law to do them, and <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. all have ſinned, <hi>Iames</hi> 3.2. In many things we offend all; ſo that by the deeds of the Law ſhall no fleſh be juſtified, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A man having once ſinned, and fallen under the guilt of ſinne, and ſo into the deſert of death, and curſe, as all men have, there is no after-righteouſneſſe of his performance that can take away that ſinne; which unleſſe it be taken away, he cannot be juſtified before God, though in his after righteouſneſſe he could anſwer the whole Law, but onely for that one offence: whence thoſe ſayings, <hi>Job.</hi> 9.15.20.21.22. nor can any teares, confeſſions, or waſhing themſelves with ſnow water, take off this ſinne that they may appeare righteous before God, <hi>Job.</hi> 9.30.31.32. Nor can any gifts or ſacrifices of Bulls and Goats, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.4. nor of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Rams, or ten thouſand Rivers of Oyle, or the firſt borne of Beaſts, or of a mans body, ſatisfie for, and take away ſin, <hi>Mich.</hi> 6.6.7.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Neither can there be any mangling, impairing, or abating, much leſſe aboliſhing of this holy and ſpirituall law that the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty will tolerate, nor did Jeſus Chriſt come to deſtroy this Law, but to fulfill it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.17.18. Think not that I am come to deſtroy the Law or the Prophets, I am not come to deſtroy, but
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:113873:18"/>to fulfill: For verily I ſay unto you, Till Heaven and Earth paſſe, one jot, or one tittle ſhall in no wiſe paſſe from the Law, till all be fulfilled, neither did Jeſus Chriſt come to be an Arbitrator or Dayes-man, to plead with God, and lay his hand upon him, that he might abate to men ſome part of their duty required in the Law, and to lay his hand upon men to enjoyn and cauſe them to perform ſome part of their due to the Law, to give ſome ſatisfying to God, &amp; ſo make God &amp; men friends that way, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Iob.</hi> 9.33. No ſuch matter; but Jeſus Chriſt himſelfe in his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon while he was here on earth, did perfectly fulfill this Law, ſo as no ſin could be found in him; but he was in reſpect of his own particular perſon, righteous and juſt, even by that Law. And had he not been a publick perſon in our ſtead, and ſo had our ſins; that Law could never have charged him, for he kept it fully, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.29. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.46. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22.<note place="margin">Rom. 3.19 Gal. 4.4. Eſa. 53.2.6. 2 Cor. 5.19-21. Gal. 3.13. Rom. 4.25 2 Cor. 5.14. Rom. 7.4. and 4.25.</note> But as the publick perſon in the roome of mankind. He was made under the Law to redeem them that were under the Law; and ſo being under the Law for us, he had all our ſins that Law could charge us with, imputed to, and laid upon him; and all the curſe and death which Law could and did ſentence us to, impoſed upon him. And ſo he ſuffered the curſe, &amp; died the death for our ſins; yea for us all, ſo as all are dead: And ſo he hath ſatisfied the Law, that we are dead to the Law by the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt. And this Jeſus Chriſt as the publick perſon is riſen again for our juſtification, and hath aſcended to heaven, and with the vertue of his own blood offered himſelfe a ranſome and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to God, having obtained eternall redemption and life for men,<note place="margin">Heb 9.12. Eſa. 55.5. Iohn 16. Heb. 9.14. and 12.24. Reu. 1.5.</note> to diſpenſe to ſuch as beleeve on him. And now ſendeth forth of that Spirit he hath received, diſcovering this grace, to draw men to believe on him: and in the hearts of ſuch as through grace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in Chriſt, he by his Spirit applieth, ſprinkleth and waſheth with that pretious blood, ſo as he enableth them to receive the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of the Law, which himſelfe hath made, and to anſwer Law-charges therewith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.24.25. &amp; 5.2.—11. &amp; 8 34. And to receive and own to themſelves as theirs by faith the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that he is become, and to reſt on him, and approach in that to God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3.7.8.9. and by the ſame Spirit in, and with the rich grace herethrough ſtreaming, he reneweth them, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.4.5. and worketh love in them, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18.21.22. yea, a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113873:19"/>more excellent love then Law diſcovered, in that it is a love of God in and for Chriſt, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.10.—19. and love of our brother as Chriſt hath loved us, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.1.2. And this love fulfils all righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, yea from a better principle then law could have affoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.10. the Spirit in working this love, writing the law in the inward parts, 2 Cor. 3.3. and leading to deny all evill, and live godly, &amp;c. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11.12. and yeelding to and walking after the Spirit, a man ſhall neither fullfill the luſts of the fleſh, nor be under Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.16.18. but have the righteouſneſſe of the Law, (the life it promiſeth, and cannot give yea a better life) fulfilled in him, and have an abundant entrance into the Kingdom, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.8. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 11. And thus by Chriſt himſelfe in his body, in all his converſation was the Law fulfilled; and by him in his own body, as the publick perſon, was the Law ſatisfied for all it had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us: and by him through his Spirit applpying that ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to our hearts, he enables to beleeve and receive it; and in that beleeving ſheads abroad his grace in the heart, that leads to all righteouſneſſe the Law requireth, though from a better principle that will in due ſeaſon perfect the ſame, and hee alſo will fill us with eternall life. And without this coming, death, reſurrection and ſacrifice of Chriſt, the Law could never have been fulfilled and ſatisfied: and without his ſpirituall application to the heart, it will never be anſwered by us, or fulfilled in us; whence that thankſgiving, or profeſſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.25. &amp; 8.1.2.3.4.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The ends of the making known, and giving this holy, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, and righteous law, was neither to juſtifie thoſe to whom it was given, nor to give them lyfe, nor to kill, and deſtroy from God for ever; for if it had been given to give lyfe, and juſtifie, and bring to the inheritance; it had been againſt the covenant and promiſes of God, and ſaith therein; which to conceive, God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, far bee it from us, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.18, 21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.14. And if it had been given to get righteouſneſſe by it, or to deſtroy from God for ever; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t had been againſt the grace of God teſtified in the Death, and reſurrection of Chriſt, and faith therein; which God forbid, and far be it from us to conceive, <hi>Gal.</hi> 20.21. and 3.11.12.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13.—7.24.25. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. Beſides, the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113873:19"/>giving the law in the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> a Mediator of the firſt Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament; ſheweth, that it was not given to juſtifie; for then no need of a Mediator, nor was it given to deſtroy from God for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; for then he would not have given a Mediatour, Gal. 3.17. And yet the law was given for good, holy, and mercifull ends; For God in his mercy having found a ranſome, and given us life in him, and confirmed a Covenant in him, <hi>John</hi> 1.4. 1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.1.2. which grace ſhould have led men to repentance, and faith in God, and living to him; But through blindneſſe,<note place="margin">Eſa. 44.20. and 55.2. Gal. 3.19.</note> and hardneſſe of heart; men ſlighted this great Salvation, and put confidence in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolls, and ſuperſtitions, and lived in, and to themſelves; And becauſe of Tranſgreſſions, the law was added till the ſeed ſhould come, and this law to diſcover that righteouſneſſe which is due from men to God:</p>
               <p n="1">1 To kill men in reſpect of themſelves, of all that lyfe which they have in, and from themſelves by any excellencyes, parts, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, or workings of theirs, in, and by themſelves; By diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering their ſinfulneſſe, and the Immeaſurableneſſe of it, and the curſe, and wrath due to them, that ſo they may charge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with it, which without the law, they would not doe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. and 4.15. and 5.13.20. By ſpoyling them of all hope of lyfe by their own workings, that they may ſay Amen to the curſe,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.6.</note> and yeeld themſelves as dead, and loſt, and ſo receive the ſentence of death in themſelves, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.26.</p>
               <p n="2">2 To occaſion their ſubmiſſion to Chriſt, and ſo their high prizeing of the grace, and righteouſneſſe, and lyfe in him, that they may fall downe before him, and be quickned, and made alive by him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.19. who by ſprinkling his blood, and giving in his grace by his ſpirit, enliveneth them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.4.5. And ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3. Chriſt is the end of the law for righteouſneſſe to every one that believeth, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. &amp; 3.22.24. which alſo ſheweth the neceſſity of the pretious Blood of Chriſt, which he ſhead, and preſented to his Father for men to be by his ſpirit applyed to men, without which they can have no true peace, and freedome with God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 13.8. and 8.32-36.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The power this law hath in the conſciences of men in this lyfe, till they know, and believe in Chriſt, and be ſet free by him,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113873:20"/>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.34-36. this holy, ſpirituall, and righteous law, in reſpect of the ſpirituall affections, and ſervices therein required, was once in the heart of mankind; when God made man in his own I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage; And made him, and all men in him, as in the firſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like perſon, righteous; then was it the naturall bent of man to love God, and his neighbour, and to walke in that love uprightly, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26, 27, 28. and 2.7. <hi>Ecleſ.</hi> 7.29. And then while theſe righteous affections, and ſervices were naturally ſpringing, and ſtreaming in men; man was not under the power of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements thereof; with the promiſes and threats; But when man ſinned, and fell, He loſt theſe righteous affections, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices out of his heart, and inward, and naturall bent; And became corrupt, averſe, and full of enmity againſt God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.10-13. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.29. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12.18.19. And then fell under the power of this law with its Commands, Threats, and Promiſes; And the effect of this law as a ſpirit of Bondage entred into him: for ſuch the power of the work of God in his grace, both ſhewn in the creation, and procured for men by the Redemption, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to men for the redeemers ſake, that it ſtill proclaimeth to men, and teſtifieth, that it is mans duty and that he is hereby bound to love God with all his heart, ſoule, and ſtrength, and his neighbour as himſelfe, and to walke in that love, And the leaſt ſhort coming hereof is ſinn, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 35.10.11. and 37.24. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.6.7. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.4. For though man by ſinn loſt his inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in God; yet God loſt not his right and Authority over man, But when man by ſinn, loſt the inward and living principle of the law out of his heart; Then through the Authority of God o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver man, and the power of God in his works; man fell under the power of the law; And the effect of the law as a ſpirit of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage entred into his heart, and that with ſuch force; that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the knowledge given him, whether by the works of God in creation, and providence, or the law declared, and written, that it bindeth downe, and embondageth a man, that he can no otherwiſe have hope, or looke to God for acceptance and life, then as he conceives himſelfe to keepe this law, nor avoyd the feares of wrath, and Death, as he diſcernes himſelfe a tranſgreſſor of it, and as their conſcience witneſſe; ſo doe their thoughts ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, or excuſe one another, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15. And ſo from the law,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113873:20"/>ſin takes occaſion to become oft more violent in its motions to ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.5.8. And from the law ſinn hath its ſtrength to accuſe, and terifie, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.56. And in deſires of avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing danger, this ſpirit of bondage ſo laden with ſinn pollutes the conſcience to be dictating to ſeeke peace in workes of the law and to be ſpeaking peace there from, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.32. and 10.3. which ſtill genders to bondage, and leaves under the curſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.21.30. and 5.4. and 3.10. And this power hath law with its effect in the conſciences of men in this lyfe, till they be ſet free by Chriſt; for the law can juſtifie none that have at all ſinned, nor gives any hope for any repentance after ſinning, nor any power or freedome for coming in to God againe, this is the work of Jeſus Chriſt, the Sonne of God, to juſtifie from ſinn, and give repentance, and freedome to come in to God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8 34-36. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.31. So that onely by Chriſt, by his ſpirit applying his pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ious blood to the heart, and ſtreaming in his rich grace there through, the conſcience is purged from the accuſation of ſinn, and from ſpeaking, or ſeeking peace by dead works; And gives in an inward living prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple to ſerve the living God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. And ſo waſheth from ſinn, <hi>Reu.</hi> 1.5. Reneweth, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.4. And ſetteth them at Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for the things of the Kingdom, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1. enduing them with the Spirit of adoption of love, power and a ſound minde, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7. And thus the law rightly underſtood in it ſelfe, and the ends of giving it; And the power it hath in the naturall conſcience ſhews the neceſſity of the Pretious Blood of Chriſt to be by his ſpirit applyed to, and ſprinkled on the conſcience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Excellency, and dignity of this Precious Blood of Chriſt that is preſented to the Father, and his Sacrifice being alſo preſented to the heart.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>FOR the Excellency, Dignity, and worth of the Blood, Death and Sacrifice of Chriſt, preſented, and offered to God for men, and preſented, tendered, and applyed to men; It is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:113873:21"/>compariſon or expreſſion; yet we may underſtand a little thereof, if we view, and conſider it in fowre reſpects, 1. In reſpect of the Sacrifice it ſelfe, 2. In reſpect of the appearance, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration thereof, 3. In reſpect of the glorious, and abundance of love herethrough appearing, 4. In reſpect of the unvaluable, and inexpreſſible hope it giveth to all that receive it, beſides the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to be after ſpoke of.</p>
               <p n="1">1 In reſpect of the Preſentation, and Sacrifice it ſelfe, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth to be of moſt excellent Dignitye, and worth in many no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table reſpects, as to ſay.</p>
               <p n="1">1 In reſpect of the Prieſt that offered this Sacrifice, who was immediately called of God, as <hi>Aron</hi> was, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.4.5. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely above and greater then <hi>Aron,</hi> and all the Prieſts of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: for they had ſinns of their own alſo, firſt to offer for, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they offered for the ſins of the people, But this our high Prieſt had no ſinn of his own to ſatisfie for, but his offering was wholly, and altogether for us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.26.27. And their High-Prieſts were men that had infirmities, and ſo dyed; But this High-Prieſt, though the very man that dyed for us, yet riſen from the Dead, and alive for ever-more to interceide for us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.23-25. and 5.5.6. Yea they were made Prieſts according to the law of a carnall Commandement, But this High-Prieſt after the power of an endleſſe life, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.16.17. They without an Oath, this with an Oath, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.21. They the Sonnes of men, But this High-Prieſt is the Sonne of God; even God-man, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.28. and 1 4-8. They went, and preſented the Blood in an earthly holy place, but this High-Prieſt entred into Heaven it ſelfe, to offer, and appeare before God for us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.7.8.12.24. They though they offered to God; yet they tooke no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in their offerings, but this High-Prieſt offered to God, and he hath accepted him, and ſet all his wellpleaſedneſſe in him, and ſet him at his right hand, and given all Authority to him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.1-12. and 1.4.8. Oh conſider how great an High-Prieſt we have; And how excellent then the Sacrifice that he hath offered, and by vertue whereof he interceideth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. &amp; 3, &amp; 5, &amp; 7, &amp; 8.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In reſpect of the Sacrifice it ſelfe which he offered; for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry High-Prieſt is ordained to offer gifts, and Sacrifices; And it is of neceſſity that he have ſomwhat alſo to offer, and that in the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:113873:21"/>Heavens, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.3.4. And ſo he hath offered a gift, a Sacrifice for ſatisfaction, for ranſome, for propitiation, and for a memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, to intercede with for us; And this was not Gold, or Silver, nor Bullocks, and Lambs, &amp;c. nor the Blood of others, as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prieſts offered, but his own moſt Pretious Blood, his own moſt holy Body, even that very Body in which he had borne our ſinns to the Tree, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24. In which he dyed for our ſinns, and roſe for our Juſtification, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.25. Yea the Body, which is the Body of the Sonne of God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.14. In whom the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the God-head dwelleth bodily, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.9. This is the gift, the ranſome, the Sacrifice; he offered himſelfe, his own Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy without ſpot to God for us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12.14. and 10.5-10. Oh how fit, how ſatisfying, and of what infinite value is this Blood, and Sacrifice of his!</p>
               <p n="3">3 In reſpect of the Altar on which this Sacrifice was offered, and by which it was borne and carried up to God; The Altar of Gods appointment, whatever it be, is greater then the gift, or Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and Sanctifieth the gift, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23-19. Now thoſe other Prieſts offered upon an Altar of earth, or earthly ſubſtance, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.24 But what is the Altar on which this High-Prieſt offereth this excellent gift, that is greater then it, and ſanctifieth it? ſurely this can be no other, but the Divine nature which is greater then the Humane; In reſpect of which Humane, clad with our Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities he ſaid; The Father is greater then I, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.28. And by the power of this Divine nature he was ſupported in, and through his ſufferings <hi>Eſa.</hi> 50.1-9. Rayſed from the dead—<hi>Rom.</hi> 4.24. and 6.4. Aſcended to heaven, <hi>Act</hi> 5.30.31. And offered himſelfe to God: And ſo it is expreſly ſaid, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. he through the eternall ſpirit offered himſelfe without ſpot to God. And thus alſo was God manifeſted in the fleſh, Juſtified in the Spirit &amp;c. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. And ſo by ranſome of the union of the humane nature, with the Divine in the perſon of the Sonne of God, one Chriſt, God-man; This Blood, and Sacrifice, if it be rightly underſtood, may be truly called the Blood, and Sacrifice of God, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. found by God, <hi>Iob.</hi> 33.24. And offered by God unto God, according to the will of God, though it was the Body, or humane nature offere: for men: And this doth ſanctifie,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:113873:22"/>and dignifie the offering, that it is of Infinite value and prevalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.5-10-19. &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In reſpect of the Declaration, and appearance of this preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Blood, and Sacrifice; And ſo of Chriſt, that by the eternall Spirit hath offered it to God for men, and received the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to apply to men, and his gratious ends in both the faithfull, and playne declaration of this by ſuch as by ſpirit have received it, and as the Spirit hath taught them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4.6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. Declares this Pretious Blood, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to be of great excellency, worth, and Dignity: In that in ſuch declaration (as he promiſed.)</p>
               <p n="1">1 The holy Spirit cometh along, and ſheweth, and teſtifieth of theſe things of Chriſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.26. and 16.14. and manifeſted the ſavour of his Knowledge, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.15. And goeth to the heart of men that they might believe, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.7, 8, 9, 10. And writeth the minde of Chriſt in the Believer, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. and 13.3 5. So that in the hearing of this Doctrine, and Object of Faith, and in no Doctrine, or obſervation of any law of workes, the Spirit of Chriſt cometh, and teſtifieth, and is received, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1-5.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The free grace, and abundant love of God to mankind in the gift of his Sonn. To be a ranſome for all men, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3, 4, 5, 6. And the Saviour of the world, And the propitiation for their ſins, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.10.14. That whoſoever believeth on him might not periſh, but have everlaſting life, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.17. And his acceptation of his Sonne for men, and taking his wellpleaſedneſſe in him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.17 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.1-12. His filling him for men, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.18. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 41.1. His readineſſe to receive in, and through his Sonn, and that his Sonn ſhall give eternali life to all that in his Diſcovery, ſee, and believe on him <hi>John</hi> 6.40. and 1.12. yea, even his peculiar, and delightfull love, and well pleaſedneſſe in his Sonn, and all that by grace are made one in his Sonn, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.9. and 16.27. All this appeareth (and as living water ſtream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) In the Declaration, and appearance of this Pretious Blood, and Sacrifice, as it was offered to God, And is applyed to the heart, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24 25. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.6-12.13.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The great, and compleate ſalvation, redemption, reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Propitiation, and righteouſneſſe that is in him, and which he
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:113873:22"/>is become, which by himſelfe,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.24. 1 Cor. 15.3.4. Rom. 4.25. 1 Iohn 2.2.</note> and in his own Body he hath wrought in dying and ſhedding his Blood for our ſinns, and riſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for our Juſtification; And through the eternall Spirit offering himſelfe a ſpotleſſe and unvaluable Sacrifice to God, in which he hath made Purgation of our ſinns, ſlaine enmity, obtained eternall redemption, and made ſuch ſatisfaction in heaven, that he hath thereupon received life to diſpenſe to men, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. and 9.12.14. and 10.1-12. And the power, and fitneſſe of the ſame Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Blood, and Sacrifice by the Holy Spirit applyed to the heart, to purchaſe, redeeme, and reconcile to God from among men, and to waſh, purge, and renew the heart, &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. <hi>Ren.</hi> 1.5. and 5.9. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.4.5. And ſo worke Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in men. All this appeareth in this Doctrine, or playne faith-and ſpirituall Declaration of this Pretious Blood, and Sacrifice, ſo as therethrough from the threefold witneſſe in heaven that are one, there come theſe three on earth to men, the Spirit, and the water, and the Blood, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5, 6, 7, 8-12. By all which this Blood, and Sacrifice appeareth of infinite Excellency, and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p n="4">4 In reſpect of the rich, free, bright, and abundant love appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this Sacrifice of the Sonn of God, for as it was the love of God to give his Sonn, &amp;c. as aforeſaid; even ſo in all that he doth to us, in mercy for his Sonns ſake, his love and goodneſſe appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth therein, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136. And his goodneſſe is his glory, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.18.19. and ſo:</p>
               <p n="1">1 His love, mercy, and goodneſſe appeareth in this, that by Chriſt, and for his ſake, the earth, and the Inhabitants thereof are upheld, the Sunn to ſhine, &amp;c. continued, mercy ſhewn, &amp;c. All witneſſing his goodneſſe, and leading to repentance, as is fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewn, and ſo it is ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. The heavens declare the glory of God, &amp;c. And thus, all his workes prayſe him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.8.9.10. And thus for Chriſt his ſake, his love, and glorious good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe appeares to all in his workes.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Yet his love, mercy, and goodneſſe, did more ſpecially ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in giving them his Oracles, his Covenant, and Ordinances, and though but in Promiſes, Propheſies, and Tipes of Chriſt, as then yet to come; yet his glory appeared therein, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:113873:23"/>ſuch ſpeciall love, as it might then be truly ſaid, he had not dealt ſo with any Nation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.2. and 9.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.18.</p>
               <p n="3">3 But now in this giving, and ſetting forth his Sonn, who hath come, and dyed for our ſins, and with the vertue of his own Blood entred the heavens, and offered himſelfe a Sacrifice to God, and received Spirit, and ſending him forth in the word of Salvation which himſelfe wrought, and firſt began to preach, and ſo God ſpeaking to him by his Sonn, who is the brightneſſe of his glory, and the expreſſe Image of his Perſon, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2.3. and 2.3. The wiſdome of God, and the power of God; yea, wiſdome, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, ſanctification, and redemption to them that believe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1-24.30. In which face of Chriſt, the light of the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the glory of God, yea, his face ſhineth, and is beheld, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4 6. and 3.18. Oh the Infinitneſſe of the Breadth, Depth, length, and height of this love of God, appearing herein! <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.18.19. In which ſtill the Excellency, and Dignity of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice appeareth.</p>
               <p n="4">4 In reſpect of the great hope this Pretious Blood, and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice giveth, and engendereth in all that in believing receive the ſame: as.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Remiſſion of ſinns, and acceptance into favour, and peace, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.43. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1.2.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Purgation of Conſcience, and Sanctification of the whole man, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Seaſonable victorie over all enemies, and Temptations, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.4.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.24.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The Holy Spirit to teach, guide, and conforme to Chriſt, and ſo bring to the Kingd ome, and inheritance, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.26. and 16.13.14. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5.</p>
               <p n="5">5 And to ſay all in one word, eternall life, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1, 23. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.25. All which ſhew forth the Excellency, and Dignity of this Pretious Blood, and Sacrifice of Chriſt, beſides the vertue, and power now to be ſpoke of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:113873:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. 8.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the vertue, operation, and prevalency of this Pretious Blood, and Sacrifice of Jeſus Chriſt: And firſt. As offered to God.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE vertue, operation, and prevalency of the Blood, and Sacrifice of Jeſus Chriſt is very great; ſo as that which was propheſied concerning him, is and ſhall certainly be fulfilled; <hi>Eſa.</hi> 53. When thou ſhalt make his Soule an offering for ſinn, He ſhall ſee his ſeed (ſo great a Generation, as none of us can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare) He ſhall prolong his dayes (live ever, and cauſe his ſeede to live for ever with him) And the pleaſure of the Lord ſhall proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in his hands (his workes, and Judgements acceptable, and proſperous.) He ſhall ſee the Travell of his Soule (even be the Lord of all, and be acknowledged Lord by all.) By his knowledge ſhall my righteous Servant juſtifie many (even all that believe on him through his teaching.) And this is the ground; for he ſhall beare their iniquity, therefore will I divide him a portion with the great, and he ſhall divide the ſpoyle with the ſtrong (he ſhall have the Kingdome, and be the judge, and give to each, their portion, and Doome.) Becauſe he hath powred out his Soule un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Death, &amp;c. All which is true in Chriſt, who is the truth; And in a meaſure true too, and in all that believe on him, and ſhall one day appeare true to all men, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.8. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.7-11. And that the Truth of the vertue, Power, and Prevalency of this Pretious Blood, and Sacrifice of Chriſt, may be rightly and profi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tably underſtood, and believed by us; let us conſider what is ſaid thereof by the Spirit of truth, in the Scripture or word of Truth, concerning the vertue, power, and Prevalency of this Pretious and Sacrifice of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As it was preſented and offered to God: 2. As grace is therethrough ſhewn and tendered to men. 3. As it is ſpiritually applied to, and worketh in, the hearts of thoſe that through grace believe. 4. And as he teſtifieth, and exerciſeth the power of it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them that have perſiſted in obſtinacy, and refuſing to believe.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:113873:24"/>In all which its power and prevalency doth appeare, and ſhall by all men be one day confeſſed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As this pretious Blood and Sacrifice was preſented &amp; offered to God; it hath ſo verily and mightily prevailed with him, that he hath obtained and received of the Father the firſt, next, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediat end of his ſuffering and Sacrifice; and alſo the Father hath filled and fitted him for the ſecond ultimate and utmoſt end of his ſuffering and ſacrifice. In both which, the prevalency and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctualneſſe thereof with God for men, is evident and manifeſt: let be conſidered,</p>
               <p>The firſt, next and immediat end of the ſuffering and Sacrifice of Chriſt, was to work a ſalvation for mankind with God. And that himſelfe might be the Lord, the Saviour, and the Judge, <hi>John</hi> 3.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.9. 1 <hi>John.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2 9. And this firſt end con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth, and may be comprehended in theſe particulars:</p>
               <p n="1">1. To put, or take away ſin, even the ſinne of the world (that was in the way between God and mankind, out of the way) by the ſacrifice of himſelfe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.26. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.19. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5, as is fore-ſhewne, That ſo he that was made ſinne, and a curſe for all, might himſelfe in the room of all, be juſtified as the publick man, with ſuch a full and fruitfull juſtification, that all may be ſo farie juſtified in him, that whoſoever of them are by his grace and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, brought in believing to be one in, and with him, ſhall alſo in their own particular perſons be juſtified in, with, and through him, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.4.—10. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.15.16. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.43. And hath not his Blood and Sacrifice offered to God, prevailed with God for, and effected all this? doth not the Spirit in the Scripture affirm plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and expreſly, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5. In him is no ſin, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3? And that when he had by himſelfe purged our ſin, he ſat down on the right hand of, &amp;c. with <hi>Heb</hi> 11.12? And doth not God affirm him to be the juſt, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.1? and the holy one, verſ. 20? and his righteous ſervant, that by his knowledge ſhall juſtifie many, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.11. And ſaith not the Scripture expreſly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23.24.25? All have ſinned, and come ſhort of the glorie of God? being juſtified freely through his grace, through the redemption that is in Jeſus Chriſt, which God nath ſet forth to be the propitiation, through faith in his blood for the remiſſion of ſinnes? And <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18. As by the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of one unto all men to condemnation, even ſo by the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:113873:24"/>of one unto all to juſtification of life. And then it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes as the fruit of this, verſ. 19. For as by the diſobedience of one, many were made ſinners, ſo by the obedience of one many ſhall be made righteous; ſo is he juſtified, ſo hath he by ſacrifice prevailed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To remove, ſtay, and take away the enmity that (by reaſon of ſin &amp; death entred &amp; the dominion of the law) was between God and man in the very way, and in the ſtate and condition of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, ſtanding as a partition, &amp; Iron Bar, to keep God from ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mercy to men, and men from any paſſage of coming in to God. The removing of this was one end of the ſuffering and ſacrifice of Chriſt, as alſo the enmity occaſioned between Jewes and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, by the Law of Ordinances, in rites and ſacrifices, and ſo to make peace. And ſo it is expreſly ſaid of his ſufferings and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53.5. The chaſtiſement of our peace was upon him; and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. God was in Chriſt reconciling the world to himſelf. And of his prevalency for this with God for men, doth not the Spirit in the Scripture affirm, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85.10. Mercy and truth are met, righteouſneſſe and peace have kiſſed; and that he, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.20. hath made peace through the blood of his croſſe, and <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.13-16? Now in Chriſt Jeſus yee who ſometimes were farre off, are made nigh by the blood of Chriſt; for hee is our peace, who hath made both (thoſe mentioned verſe 1, 2, 3) one, and hath broken down the middle wall of partition between us, having aboliſhed in his fleſh the Law of Commandements in ordinances, for to make in himſelfe of twain one new man, ſo making peace. And that he might reconcile both unto God in one body by the croſſe, having ſlain the enmity thereby or in himſelf. And this preceding peace-preaching; and yee are become dead to the Law by the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.4. who hath aboliſhed death, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. and taken out of the way all that was contrary to us, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.14. and ſo is affirmed to be (1 <hi>John</hi> 2.2.) the Propitiation for our ſinnes, and not for ours onely, but alſo for the ſinnes of the whole world; ſuch his prevalency with God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To redeem and buy all of God, that they might not periſh its that neceſſity of periſhing into which they had ſold themſelves, nor be judged to eternall death by and according to that Law, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which they were fallen, nor carried away by the Divell as their
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:113873:25"/>rightfull Lord, by vertue of his firſt conqueſt over mankind. But that they all might be releaſed, and given over to his own diſpoſe, and ſo he be the Lord of all, as it is ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.9. For to this end Chriſt both died, and roſe, and revived, that he might be the Lord both of the dead and living. And ſo effectuall was his ſacrifice, and ſuch the prevalency of it with God for men in this reſpect, that he is affirmed to have bought even thoſe that deny him, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. And on this ground it is ſaid, whether we live therefore, or die, we are the Lords, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.8. And he is Lord of all, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.36. Yea God hath made this ſame Jeſus both Lord and Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.36. And in this particular end, many particular ends, as branches thereof are included, for which alſo he hath prevailed. As to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſome.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That he might uphold and preſerve the earth, and the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants thereof, and the heavens for them till the end come: In which he hath prevailed, and ſo it is ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.3. The earth and all the inhabitants thereof are diſſolved; I beare up the pillars of it, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.17. And by him all things conſiſt. And <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. He up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth all things by the word of his power, when he had by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe purrged our ſinnes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That he might for the time of this naturall and dying life, remove and take off from men ſo much of that ſorrow, weakneſſe, pains, and curſed terrors, which the falling into ſinne did neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate to be on men, as in his love and wiſdome hee ſees fit. And in this alſo he hath prevailed, and ſo it is ſaid, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.28. In him wee live, and move and have our being, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.8. The Lord is gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and full of compaſſion, ſlow to anger, great in mercie, The Lord is good to all, and his tender mercies are over all his works, verſ. 9.</p>
               <p n="3">3, That he might exerciſe patience, ſhew mercy, and uſe ſuch means as he pleaſeth to move and lead men to repentance, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after him, and ſubmiſſion to him, and in this alſo hee hath prevailed, and ſo it is ſaid, <hi>John</hi> 1.4.5. In him was life, and the life was the light of men, and the light ſhineth in darkneſſe, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. The Lord is patient and longſuffering to us-ward, not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to repentance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. The goodneſſe of God leadeth thee to repentance, <hi>Acts</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:113873:25"/>14.17. &amp; 17.26.27. that they ſhould ſeek the Lord, and live to him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.7.8. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14.15.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That he may rule over all, and diſpoſe of their wayes, conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and trials, &amp;c. And in this alſo he hath prevailed; and ſo the Father in approbation of his Sacrifice, ſaid, Ask of me and I ſhall give thee the Heathen for thine inheritance, and the utmoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſſion, &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.8.9. And himſelf ſaith, All power is given unto me in heaven and in earth, &amp;c. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18. And the Spirit in the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.7. He ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth by his power for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.19. And his Kingdome ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth over all.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That after the end of this life he may raiſe all men from the firſt death, and make them alive, and ſet them before him, that they may bow to him, and acknowledge him Lord, to the glory of God. And in this alſo he hath prevailed; and ſo the Spirit in the Scripture ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.21.22. ſince by man death, by man alſo the reſurrection from the dead: For as in <hi>Adam</hi> all die, ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive. And himſelfe ſaith, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.32. And I, if I be lifted up from the earth, will draw all men unto me. And even becauſe of his obedience in ſuffering, it is ſaid, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9.10.11. wherefore God alſo hath highly exalted, and given him a name which is above every name, that at the name of Jeſus every knee ſhould bow, &amp;c. And that every tongue ſhall confeſſe, that Jeſus is the Lord, to the glory of God. And ſo <hi>David</hi> confeſſed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86.9. All nations whom thou haſt made, ſhal come and worſhip before thee, O Lord, and ſhall glorifie thy name. Thus muſt all come before him one day, and then he ſhall ſeparate and diſpoſe of them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.32, 33.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Another particular end in this firſt, next, &amp; immediate end of the ſuffering and ſacrifice of Chriſt offered to God, was, That hee might ſhew forth to men this rich and abundant grace. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.4.7. And ſo it was,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That this full Goſpel, and therethrough repentance and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes, might be preached in his name among all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.46.47, And for this he hath prevailed, ſo as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf came and preached peace, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.17. And firſt began to preach the Goſpel of this ſalvation himſelfe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3. and then left the commiſſion for preaching the ſame unto his Apoſtles and faithfull
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:113873:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:113873:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:113873:27"/>Diſciples that by grace come to be united to him, and endued with ſpirituall gifts, <hi>John</hi> 17.18-21. 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 5.18.19.20. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3.—9. And left his charge to preach it to all Nations, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.13.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And alſo that by his laying down his life in witneſſing to the truth of the Goſpel he taught, and the Fathers acceptance of his ſacrifice, the truth of the Goſpel might bee confirmed for all that heare it, that they might beleeve, <hi>John</hi> 18.37. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.13. And in this alſo he hath prevailed; and ſo it is ſaid, he ſpake the truth which he heard of God, <hi>John</hi> 8.45. And the Apoſtles have ſaid. They ſpake the words of truth, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.25. and that with great plainneſſe of ſpeech, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.12. by manifeſtation of the truth, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2.5. for ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16. We have not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed cunningly deviſed Fables, when we made knowne to you the power and comming of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; but were eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſes of his majeſty: for he received from the Father honour and glory, when, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And alſo that himſelf might be the prime motive, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to us for faith, and love, and walking in both converſation, and miniſtration in patience and meekneſſe through ſufferings in hope to the death, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. <hi>John</hi> 13.1-15. And in this alſo he hath prevailed, ſo as himſelf points to himſelfe for the prime motive and example, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.12—.20. And the Spirit in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſets him forth to us for motive and example, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12.—14. and bids us looke to him, and conſider him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2-7. and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.1.2.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Yea and that he might ratifie the New Teſtament of preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promiſes for all that in the heavenly call are brought in to believe in him, that they through the Spirit may wayt for the ſame, through faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14.15.16. <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.28. In which alſo he hath prevailed, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. ſheweth, with <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.15.—26. and 5.5. And ſo the whole Goſpel is by the blood and ſacrifice of Chriſt confirmed and ſealed for truth.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That he might alſo having life in himſelfe, quicken whom he will, and ſo give eternall life to all that beleeve on him, and leave, and give up ſuch as will none of his counſell and ſo perſiſt in refuſing to beleeve on him. In which alſo he hath prevailed, <hi>John</hi> 1.17. &amp; 3.18.19 &amp; 5.20.28. &amp; 6.37.40.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:113873:27"/>
               <p n="6">6. That he may at the laſt judge all men according to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel which himſelf firſt began to preach, and then gave his ſervants to preach. And in this alſo hee prevailed, as is evident in that himſelfe ſaid, <hi>John</hi> 12.48. He that rejecteth me, and receiveth not my words, hath one that judgeth him; the word that I have ſpoken the ſame ſhal judge him at the laſt day. And his ſervant by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16. In the day when God ſhall judge the ſecrets of men by Jeſus Chriſt, according to my Goſpel. And ſo it is ſaid of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31. He hath appointed a day wherein he will judge the world in righteouſneſſe by that man whom hee hath ordained, whereof he hath given aſſurance (or offered faith) unto all men, in that he hath raiſed him from the dead. And ſo as <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.9. to this end he both died and roſe, and revived, that he might be the Lord of both dead and living. So it is affirmed on that very ground, verſ. 11, 12. &amp; 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. We muſt all appear abefore the judgment ſeat of Chriſt, &amp;c. yea and ſuch as come then to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by him that ſo died for them, and offered himſelfe a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and ranſome for them; and uſed mercy and extended meanes to call them to repentance, are charged with ſinne for that they have not believed, <hi>John</hi> 16.8.9. and that they have troden under foot the Soone of God, counted the Blood of the Covenant wherewith they were ſanctified, an unholy thing, and offered deſpite to the Spirit of grace, at leaſt that he called and they refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1 24. And this ſhall be their condemnation, light came, and they loved darkneſſe rather, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.19. They by following lying vanities, have forſaken their own mercies, <hi>Iona</hi> 2.8. And loſt their own ſouls, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.26. And by denying the Lord that bought them, brought upon themſelves ſwift deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, 2 <hi>Pet</hi> 1. and ſo are rightly called,<note n="*" place="margin">Jude <hi>12</hi>
                  </note> Frees twice dead. And the deſtuction and torment into which they ſhall be caſt, is called the ſecond death, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20 6.14.</p>
               <p>And thus mightily and verily hath the pretious Blood and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Chriſt offered to his Father, prevailed with God, ſo as indeed Jeſus Chriſt hath thereby put away ſin, aboliſhed death, removed enmity out of the condition of mankind, bought all men of God, and obtained eternall redemption; ſo as he is become the Lord of all, and hath remiſſion of ſinnes, and life to diſpenſe. And through him the earth is upheld for men, mercy ſhewed to, and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:113873:28"/>means uſed towards them to draw them to repentance, and faith, and they all given of God into his diſpoſe, and he hath power and ſhall raiſe them all from the dead, and judge them all according to the Goſpel, ſuch as have in beleeving been brought to him, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden in him in the day of grace, hee will ſentence to eternall life; and ſuch as have through the day of grace perſiſted in refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him, or departing from him, he wil ſentence to a ſecond death. And that men might have knowledge hereof, and faith herein, to bring them in to him, and confidence to abide in him, and bee left excuſeleſſe in their refuſall; he hath alſo ſealed and confirmed the Goſpel for a certain truth, in the report of the Propitiation, and life on beleeving for all men, and the New Teſtament for beleevers. And all this true, whether men believe it, or no. And ſo far hath the ſacrifice, as offered to God, prevailed: and yet further in his having a fitneſſe for that to be after ſaid. And in reſpect of all hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſaid, the light ſhineth in the darkneſſe, but the darkneſſe comprehendeth it not, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.5.</p>
               <p n="7">7. And now to remedy this alſo, that the light may be ſeen and known through the means uſed, there is yet another end of his Sacrifice offered; namely, that hee might fit at his Fathers right hand, and receive and bee filled with the holy Goſt in our nature glorified to ſend forth to the ſonnes of men, and to fill and lead his people: and ſo to be as in his own place, a reprover of the world, and an advocate and comforter of his people. Himſelfe when he was in the world, did teſtifie of it, That the works there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of were evill, <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.7. And hee declared himſelfe the Bread of life, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6. the Son of God, and Doore of the ſheep, <hi>Iohn</hi> 10. yea the Way, the Truth, and the life, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.6. and did teach his Diſciples and keep them, and manifeſt his Fathers Name and Words to them, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.6, 7, 8. and hee being in that eſtate, and manner of miniſtration not long to abide in the world, did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to ſend them another Advocate and Comforter to bee in his ſtead with them for ever, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.16. and that this holy ſpirit ſhould beare witneſſe of him. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.26. and convince for reprove the world, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.8, 9, 10, 11. and guide his Diſciples into all truth, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.13. mind them of his ſayings, teach them all things, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.26. &amp;c. yet even when while Chriſt in his own perſonall body was in the world, he told this for truth unto his Diſciples,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:113873:28"/>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.7. <hi>It is expedient for you that I goe away, for if I goe not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, the Comforter will not come unto you. But if I depart I will ſend him unto you.</hi> And when he promiſeth ſuch portion of Spirit, it was at that time ſaid, The H. Ghoſt was not yet given, becauſe Jeſus Chriſt was not yet glorified. <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.39. Now in his aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and offering himſelfe in Sacrifice to God for men, hee hath prevailed for this alſo, as appears in that is ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.18. <hi>Thou haſt aſcended on high, thou haſt led captivity captive, thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived gifts in the man</hi> (that is in the humane nature, and for men, to give gifts to men, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.8.) yea the rebellious alſo that the Lord God might dwell among them. And ſo where there was a performance-evident and eminent, in viſible deſcent, &amp; divine ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration through ſome to the convincement of many, and drawing in many, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. <hi>totum.</hi> It is ſaid, This Jeſus hath God raiſed up, whereof we are all witneſſes; therefore being by the right hand of God exalted and having received of the Father, the promiſe of the H. Ghoſt, he hath ſhed forth this which yee now ſee and hear: and ſo the Spirit of the Lord doth reſt on him, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 42.1. and he is annointed with it, to preach good tidings, &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.1, 2, 3, 4. So that as himſelfe hath made peace. ſo he hath received Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to preach, and give peace, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.14.16.17. As he hath procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red meanes to be uſed to call men; ſo hee hath received Spirit to ſend forth according to the means to breath and operate ſecretly therein towards, and with men, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3. to enlighten every man, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.9. to manifeſt the being and goodneſſe. of God to them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.19. to reprove their evils, <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.23. to lead to repentance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. that they might ſeek and find God, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.26. and hee opens his words and gives his Spirit to to them, <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.23. And as he hath himſelf preached the Goſpel, and confirmed the truth of it with his blood, &amp; left it with his ſervants to miniſter; ſo he hath received, and is filled with Spirit immeaſurably, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.34. to ſend forth in the miniſtration thereof, to cenvince the world, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.8, 9. to bring down every high thought, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4.5. to diſcover grace to men that they might believe, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.7. and come to Chriſt, Iſai. 55.5. to purge the conſciences of beleevers, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. and witneſſe their ſonſhip, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16. And as hee hath ſhed his blood, and preſented himſelfe with the vertue of it, in offering himſelfe a ſacrifice to God for men, and ſo made a purgation of ſinnes, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:113873:29"/>wrought ſalvation, and righteouſneſſe, and obtained eternall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption for men; ſo hee hath received an office, and ſpirit at his Fathers right hand to offer and call men to to the receite of the ſame, <hi>Pro.</hi> 8.4.7. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 45.22. And by the ſame ſpirit to apply the ſame grace, ſprinkle the vertue of the ſame Blood, and Sacrifice on ſuch as believe, to waſh, cleanſe, ſanctifie, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them to himſelfe therewith, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 61.1-5. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.25.26. whence they that come to Jeſus are ſaid to come to the Blood of ſprinkling <hi>Heb.</hi> 12 24. And to ſay in a word: As himſelfe is the gift of God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.10. and full of grace, and truth, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.14. and eternall life is in him, and given us in him, that whoſoever hath him hath it, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.10.11.12. So is he filled with the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of ſpirit, to diſcover, and diſpence this gift, grace, truth and eternall life, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 42.1-8. and 61.1-4. whence alſo, grace, mercy, and peace, are mentioned for the Holy Ghoſt, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe from the Father, and the Sonne diſcovering, giving to, and effecting in believers, grace, mercy, and peace, as is ſeene by comparing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1 5. and 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.6.7. with Rom. 1.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3. 2 <hi>Cor,</hi> 1.2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.2. And ſo in all the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> ſalutations to the Churches, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Rom,</hi> 4.5. And ſo, and in every reſpect as a foreſaid hath the Pretious Blood, and Sacrifice of Chriſt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with God for men, and this ſet forth in the Goſpel for men, as a very truth, yea to, and for ſuch as do not yet believe, but are yet impenitent, and diſobedient; that they might believe, and repent, it being the foundation of, and Door to repentance, and faith.</p>
               <p>And ſo of the firſt conſideration of the vertue, efficacy, and prevalency, of the pretious Blood, and Sacrifice of Chriſt, even as it was offered to God, and hath prevailed with God for men. Now let us conſider the efficacie in the three following conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:113873:29"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>2. Of the vertue, operation, and effectualneſſe of this Pretious Blood, and Sacrifice of Chriſt, As through its prevalency with God, grace, and mercy is ſhown, and extended to men and how fit, and forceable to prevaile with them.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT is before ſhewn; that through the prevalency of this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Blood, and Sacrifice of Chriſt with God for men, mercy is ſhewn, and meanes is uſed towards men; And that though men are ſo dead in ſinne, that they have no power, ſpirit, or will to diſcerne God, or come into him by theſe meanes, yet Jeſus Chriſt by his Sacrifice hath prevailed with God, and received of him in the humane nature the ſpirit to ſend forth in, and according to the meanes, to diſcover the grace procured by his Blood, and Sacrifice, and ſo to call, and draw in men to God as is ſhewn; And of the Prevalency of the Blood, and Sacrifice of Chriſt with men towards God, in this Diſcovery of grace by his ſpirit, is that here to be noted; not what humane ſtuddies, artificiall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and forced motives effect, But what by vertue of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Chriſt; the ſecret, ſpirituall, and ſupernaturall breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and motion of the ſpirit of Chriſt effecteth in, and according to the meanes procured by his Sacrifice; And ſo.</p>
               <p n="1">1 In his manifeſtation, and Diſcovery of grace, and mercy in thoſe mercies of God vouchſafed in his workes of creation, and providence continued for Chriſts ſake to the ſonnes of men, is effected for, and to men.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Some Teſtimony that God is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.19.20. And that notwithſtanding men have ſinned, yet he is God, and mercifull to them, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.17. And that he is a rewarder (that is ready to ſhew favour, and extend mercy) to them that ſeeke him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. And ſo the heavens declare the glory of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. And his ſpirit ſtriveth with men, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3. And he calleth all, <hi>Pro.</hi> 8.4.</p>
               <p n="2">2 It giveth ſecret reproofes of evills found, <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.23. And ſecret moveings to repentance of the evills reproved; And faith
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:113873:30"/>in his goodneſſe diſcovered, and motions to ſeeke his favour, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.29.30.31. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 45.22.</p>
               <p n="3">3 It effecteth a certaine light, and diſpoſition in men, that is ſome what more then naturall, even an inſpiration from the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, giving underſtanding to diſcerne ſomthing of God, and that with ſome inclination towards his goodneſſe, which becauſe it hath not got dominion in men, they are yet but naturall, though ſomthing be vouchſafed them that is more then naturall, by which a capabillity to heare ſome of the teachings according to God is for the time given them, and ſo it is ſaid, he enlighteneth every man that cometh into the world, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.9. And there is a ſpirit in man, and the inſpiration of the Almighty giveth them underſtanding, <hi>Iob.</hi> 32.8. And the ſpirit of man is the Candle, (or Lamp) of the Lord (which he hath ſet up and lighted) ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the inward parts of the Belly, <hi>Pro.</hi> 20.27. and this is the great fault of men that they take not notice of this mercy, <hi>Iob.</hi> 35.10.11. none ſaith, where is God my maker, who giveth ſongs in the night, who teacheth us more then the Beaſts of the earth, and maketh us wiſer then the fowles of heaven? And thence come corrections olſo, to hide pride from man, to ſeale his Inſtruction, &amp;c. <hi>Iob.</hi> 33.16-19. to 29-30.</p>
               <p n="4">4 To ſuch as do not willingly harden themſelves againſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs and ſpeakings of this grace thus farr extended, but turne thereby, he maketh knowne his words, by dreames, viſions, or a rumour of the Goſpel ſome way, ſo as he worketh in them, ſome ſutable repentance, and faith, and feare of him, and mercifull af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, &amp;c. leading to himſelfe, as is evident in his own Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.23. And the examples ſet before us, <hi>Iob.</hi> 33.13-31. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.1, 2, 3. All which is the fruite of his free grace through the Sacrifice of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36. And ſuch as harden themſelves againſt his goodneſſe, are hereby left without excuſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4.5. And juſtly given over to wrath, as is ſhewn, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18.24. And ſo farr of the univerſall efficacy with all men.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In, and through the Goſpel; when the ſpirit goeth out in diſcovery of the Pretious Blood, and Sacrifice of Chriſt: And the grace therethrough procured for, and tendred to men; the effects and prevalency with men is greater.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:113873:30"/>
               <p n="1">1 It begins to effect in all where the ſpirit doth ſo come in the Goſpel, ſome reproofe, or convincement of the vileneſſe of ſinne, the emptineſſe in worldly things, and the vanity of fleſhly righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and alſo of a fulneſſe, and ſufficiency in Chriſt, and of ſinne for not believing on him, and alſo it allureth to a love, and likement of the Doctrine of Chriſt, with ſome motions to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, faith, and ſeeking the Lord, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.7, 8, 9.10, 11. and 2.23.24. and 6.34. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.42. and 26.28. And ſuch, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in his words are his Diſciples, and ſhall know the truth, and the truth will make them free, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.31-36. And if here they take occaſion to ſtumble, and oppoſe, they may be juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived, and given up, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.39-46. and 28.23-28.</p>
               <p n="2">2 It ſinketh to the heart, effecteth farther in many, an inward, and piercing ſorrow for their former vileneſſe, emptineſſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion with wearineſſe of their old diſpoſition, hopes, and wayes, prizings, and longings after union with Chriſt, and theſe deſires accompanied with ſome taſts of his goodneſſe, and love to his people, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37. Nor will he faile or be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to theſe abideing, to ſtabliſh them in due ſeaſon, <hi>Hoſea.</hi> 6.1.2.3. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 61.1, 2, 3, 4. And when thus farr brought; to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from him cannot be leſſe then wilfull ſinning <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.26-29. And yet is this a common ſalvation where the Goſpel is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved.</p>
               <p n="3">3 This diſcovery of grace, and operation thereof abidden in, doth yet proceed farther, enabling the heart to part with its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer hopes, and purpoſes, and to believe in Chriſt: So as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives remiſſion of ſinns; And hath the beginnings of Confidence with love of the Brethren effected; And theſe are believers, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the heavenly Call, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24.25. and 5.1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.1.6. To whom that hope is now given, <hi>Heb.</hi> 14. and 9.15. And now in ſuch a believer ſo excellent is the force of this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing grace, that it worketh an effect like that mentioned, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.7.8.9. And ſo in this ſecond conſideration, we ſee a little of the vertue, and efficacy of the Pretious Blood, and Sacrifice of Chriſt, and its prevalency with men, as the knowledge of grace therethrough is given to men; In which is diſcovered in the Goſpel a heavenly motive, and cord of love to call, and draw to Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:113873:31"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:113873:31"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:113873:32"/>
               <head>CHAP. 10.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>3. Of the vertue, operation, effectualnes, &amp; prevalency of the pretious Blood and Sacrifice of Chriſt, as it is ſpiritually applied to, ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on, and working in the heart of thoſe, who through grace, are brought in to beleeve in Chriſt.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>VVHen Jeſus Chriſt by his Spirit diſcovering his grace, hath brought on the heart to beleeve on him, then doth he by the ſame Spirit, mind them of, inſtruct them in, and apply to them the vertue of his pretious Blood and Sacrifice, and the rich and free grace appearing therethrough: and ſo with the ſpiritual ſhines of grace, and application of his Blood, and ſtreaming in his love, doth he ſprinkle and waſh, and cleanſe them, &amp;c. So it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.24.25. Then will I ſprinkle clean water upon you, and yee ſhall be clean from all your filthineſſe, and from all your Idols will I cleanſe you, &amp;c. And ſo it is affirmed of his love to the Church, that he gave himſelfe for it, that hee might ſanctifie and cleanſe it with the waſhing of water, by the Word, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26. And it is teſtified of beleevers, of whom ſome had been notoriouſly evill, But ye are waſhed, but yee are ſanctified, but ye are juſtified in the name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spirit of our God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. and ſo they have confeſſed of Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. He hath loved us, and waſhed us from our ſinnes in his own blood. Whence all that by faith come to him, are ſaid to come to the blood and ſprinkling, <hi>Heb.</hi> 24. And of the vertue, power, efficacy and prevalency of this pretious hlood and Sacrifice of Chriſt, in and with beleevers, when in their believing it is thus ſpiritually applied, it is that in this conſideration wee have to take notice of, and it is already in ſome meaſure ſhewn: which may be here recalled. And ſo
<list>
                     <item>1. It verily and indeed crucifieth the fleſh, with the affections and laſts. Whence they that beleeve are ſaid to have done it, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24. It breeds inward ſorrow for, and loathing of ones ſinfulneſſe, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. and takes down pride, breeding a low eſtimate of ones ſelf, as the ſinner and curſed one for whom Chriſt was made ſin, and a curſe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.14 and it makes all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Phariſaicall excellencies appeare contemptible, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:113873:32"/>7, 8. and maketh dead to ſinne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4.11. and ſaveth from the pollutions that are in the world through Luſt, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. &amp; 2.20.</item>
                     <item>2. It alſo verily ſpeaketh, and giveth peace, yea even the peace of God, which paſſeth underſtanding, and that will keep and guard the heart and mind in Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.24. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1, 2, 11. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.7. And ſo freeth from the Law of ſinne and death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24.25. &amp; 8.2.</item>
                     <item>3. It verily redeemeth and purchaſeth from among men to God, ſo as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> prevailes with the beleever to be the Lords; and for the Lord, and ſo makes him of one mind with God and Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9. &amp; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16.</item>
                     <item>4. It waſheth, comforteth, and reneweth the heart, and all the powers to bee conformable to Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.4.5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18.</item>
                     <item>5. It firmeth the heart in confidence in Chriſt, and expectation of his giving in Spirit, according to his Promiſe, to teach, comfort, preſerve, and guide into all truth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5.—10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20.</item>
                     <item>6. It inflameth with love to God and Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.19 and moveth love to men, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14.15.19. and eſpecially to brethren, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.21. &amp; 5.1. And in this charity it ſprings up joy, patience, &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22.23.</item>
                     <item>7. It fits and makes ready to beat the reproach of Chriſt, and to ſuffer for him and his people, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3 16. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.11.</item>
                     <item>8. It ſaves from falling, and gets victory in temptations, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.1-14.</item>
                     <item>9. It preſerves from vain glory, and makes fruitfull in good words and works to glorifie Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.1.3. and 1.20.21. <hi>John</hi> 15.</item>
                     <item>10. It breeds humble and great boldneſſe to approach to the throne of Grace, and have acceſſe to God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16. &amp; 10.19. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.1.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.16.</item>
                     <item>11. It fits the heart for a ſweet, humble and profitable receit of ſpirituall viſits, and entercourſes of love, and a profitable uſe in venting them ſeaſonably. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.—16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7.—13 &amp; 12.1.—10.</item>
                     <item>12. It leads to a holy uſe of all Gods Ordinances, Creatures,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:113873:33"/>and dealings with us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.12-24. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.4.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32-36.</item>
                     <item>13. It prepares to enter through ſufferings into glory, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth to the ſame, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.11, 12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Rev..</hi> 14.15.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>And theſe and ſuch like are the efficacies of the ſpirituall appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the pretious Blood and Sacrifice of Chriſt, which effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are in beleevers, and in none elſe, what ever appearances any frame to themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 11.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>4. Of the vertue and operation of this pretious Blood and Sacrifice of Chriſt, upon them that have periſhed in Obſtinacy, and refuſing to beleeve.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>JEſus Chriſt is the Son of God, and ſhall ſee of the travell of his ſoule, and ſo the fruit of his pretious Blood and Sacrifice, even upon them that would none of him: The Lord <hi>Jehovah</hi> having in acceptation of his ſacrifice given over all into his hands and ſet his delight on him, ſo as all ſhall ſubmit; and thoſe that will not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, ſhall yet be ſubdued to acknowledge him Lord, to the glory of God, when alſo the vertue of his Blood and Sacrifice ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on them (like the heat of the Sunne on ſore eyes) to afflict them: So as all his enemies ſhal be found liers, and made his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool, Iſai. 53.11, 12. Phil. 2.10, 11. Deut. 33.29. Pſal. 110.1. And this may be evidenced</p>
               <p n="1">1. By the greatneſſe of the grace that was procured for them by this pretious Blood and Sacrifice of Chriſt, and received for them into his hands, to diſpenſe; as remiſſion of ſins, juſtification, eternall redemption, and life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24. &amp; 5.18. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.10, 11. And that ſo verily, that in refuſing, they are by the Spirit that diſcovered grace through the vertue of this Sacrifice, ſaid <hi>Iona</hi> 2.8. to forſake their own mercies, <hi>Ma.</hi> 16.26. to loſe their own ſouls, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. to bring upon themſelves ſwift deſtruction.</p>
               <p>It was great grace at firſt to make man in the Image of God, and a world of creatures for him, and to put him in Paradice, and to give him a tree of Life, &amp;c, and to depart herefrom, and ſin againſt it, a great tranſgreſſion.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:113873:33"/>
               <p>But man fallen, to worke redemption for him in ſuch a way, and therethrough to extend mercy, and meanes to win him in to partake of it, was much greater grace; and ſo greater tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to turn from it, and abuſe the ſame, and refuſe the offers of it. Theſe are the ungodly indeed in a high degree, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Iude</hi> 4.5.</p>
               <p n="2">2 By the greatnes of the wrath this ſin provoketh, &amp; fire it kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleth: It did deſerve death, and provoke wrath, when man firſt ſinned, &amp; fell from God; but that wrath God executed on his Son in our nature, and herein dying for our ſinnes, and riſing for our juſtification, and offering himſelfe a Sacrifice to God for us, hath put away ſinne, and aboliſhed death, and ſatisfied juſtice, and ſo hath appeaſed that wrath, and quenched that fire, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5, 19.21. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.29. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. &amp; 9.26. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.5. 2 Tim. 1.10. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.14. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.2. It doth deſerve death, and provoke wrath, and kindle a fire in judgments on men, that by the mercies &amp; means, by vertue of the Sacrifice of Chriſt procured for, &amp; extended to them men do not ſeek God, &amp; by repentance &amp; faith come in to him, to live to him, but ſtill go on after their own luſts, choſing their own wayes, and living to themſelves, notwithſtanding all his goodneſſe extended through Chriſt to them, to lead them to repentance, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.17. &amp; 17.26-31. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4, 5. But this wrath is appeaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and this fire quenchable. And for ſuch as in the day of their viſitation, when Spirit comes forth in the meanes, doe receive his reproofes, and obey his call, and are prevailed with to belief of his Teſtimony, repentance of their evils, and faith in his goodneſſe, and ſabmiſſion to him, to live to him; to ſuch this wrath alſo is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed, and fire quenching, and will be altogether, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.43. <hi>Rom</hi> 3.25. &amp; 5.1, 2. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 54.1-10: in due ſeaſon: But when God and Chriſt by his Spirit in the means uſed, and through the redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and purgation wrought by Chriſt, hath been viſiting, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning, moving at their hearts, and ſtriving with them, to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect repentance and faith in them, and ſo to bring them to himſelf; and they after the knowledge of the truth refuſe, reſiſt, or depart from it willingly, and will none of God, none of Chriſt, will not be brought in to him this way, to have all their life and confidence in his grace, and guidance by it; but perſiſt in their wilfull refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, or Apoſtaſie, till he leave ſtriving, and give them up to their
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:113873:34"/>own luſts, and Satan: This deſerveth &amp; kindleth ſuch wrath, as wil not be appeaſed, and ſuch a fire as will not be quenched, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6; 3: <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.23, 24, &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.11. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.13. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.37, 38. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4, 5.2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>Jude totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And the execution of this is called, <hi>The wrath to come. Luke</hi> 3.7. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. fire unquenchable, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.17. <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.48. hell fire, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.9. <hi>Mark</hi> 9.47. the ſecond death, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.14.</p>
               <p n="3">3 By the greatneſſe and inexcuſeable folly, rebellion and filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this ſinne, it being an under-valuing, neglect, and refuſall of ſo great ſalvation and redemption firſt obtained, and then firſt preached by the Lord himſelfe; yea, a denying him that bought them, and ſo a treading under foot the Sonne of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. a hardening the heart againſt the mercies and meanes that through the pretious Blood &amp; Sacrifice of Chriſt was procnred for, and extended to them, to lead them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and ſo counting the blood of the Covenant an unholy thing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. a turning from him that ſpeakes from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and ſo reſiſting and offering deſpite to the Spirit of grace that ſtrove with them to bring them to God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.25 &amp; 10.29. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.51. In a word, by their preferring darkneſſe before light, when light came, <hi>John</hi> 3.19. exalting their own wiſdom, workes, and choyce, and objecting, and taking offence at the means, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and Spirit of Grace, and turning from it after it hath ſo farre been extended to them; they crucifie again, make of no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count and efficacy to themſelves the Sonne of God, and put him to an open ſhame, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.6. A great ingratitude, and fearfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt ſo great and gracious a God and Saviour, and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſo reall an offer and tender, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 81.11. Great folly and madneſſe to refuſe ſo great and reall mercy and ſalvation and alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether excuſeleſſe, they cannot ſay we fell and were loft in <hi>Adam,</hi> &amp; no redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was wrought for us, wherby we might have been ſaved <hi>Our Fathers have eaten ſowre grapes, and the childrens teeth are ſet on edge;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 18.2. Rom. 5.12 18.</note> for the later part of the plea is falſe, &amp; God wil puniſh it: for though they were loſt in <hi>Adam,</hi> and could no way redeeme themſelves, yet in Chriſt redemption was again wrought for them: Nor can they ſay this mercy was altogether hidd, and no meanes uſed towards them, that they might have ſought, and found him, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.17. and 17.26. nor will this pleaſure; we had in our ſelves no will or power to chooſe lyfe; For
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:113873:34"/>though it was not in them, yet it was in him; And his ſpirit by which he tendred grace wanted not power, <hi>Mich.</hi> 2.7. He doth not looke to gather where he hath not ſowne, though wicked Servants ſo ſay; But on his examination they will be dumb, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.26. and 22.12. Sinnes of ignorance, and weakneſſe, to which through the fall men are neceſſitated, and for which yet there is a remedy, though they are directly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Father, and indirectly againſt the Sonne, and holy ſpirit: ſinnes againſt the meanes procured by Chriſt, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended through him to lead to repentance, and faith, and ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ordinary light, warnings, and motions; are againſt the Father, and directly againſt the Sonne, yet all manner of theſe ſorts of ſinne ſhall be forgiven unto men, but the willfull and rebellious ſinning in refuſing, and oppoſing the grace it ſelfe in Chriſt, and evidenced by the ſpirit, after light obſtinately refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to have all life in, and guidance by that grace the ſpirit diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers in Chriſt; But blaſpheming the ſame: This ſinning is directly againſt the Father, and the Sonne, and the Holy Ghoſt, and ſhall never be forgiven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.31. <hi>Marke</hi> 3.28.29.</p>
               <p n="4">4 By the evilneſſe, and remedileſneſſe of the ſtate, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, ſuch ſinning throwes theſe men into; And that may be ſeene in two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1 That whereas they were once dead through <hi>Adam;</hi> and a ranſome was given for them by Chriſt, and life procured for them, and this ſet forth in the Goſpel, and in the meanes ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to them with ſome quickning motions of the ſpirit, and hope of life, there being no other meanes or Sacrifice; They having wilfully caſt aſide this, have rent themſelves out of this booke of life, renounced this life that was ſet in hope before them, and are become Trees twice dead, and pluckt up by the rootes, ſo as there is no more hope for them, <hi>Jude</hi> 12.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That whereas; when they were fallen in <hi>Adam,</hi> though truth and Juſtice pleaded for their Death; yet mercy was for them, and found out a ranſome in which, truth, and juſtice did meete, and joyne with mercy nor their good; And though Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice might have riſen againſt them for their ſtrayings in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and unbeliefe; yet compaſſion, and mercy had patience,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:113873:35"/>and forbearance to waite for them, but now by his ſpirit he hath been ſtriving with them, and they will none of Chriſt, but harden themſelves againſt him, and oppoſe, and offer wrong, and violence to Chriſt, and his word, and people; even mercy alſo with Juſtice, and truth is turned againſt them; not that there is any change in God, but they have put themſelves into ſuch a condition, that his mercy becomes croſſe to them, the light is pleaſant to the eye, and that it troubles the ſore eye, the change is in the eye, not in the light, ſo Gods love, and mercy is the ſame for ever; His delight is in his Sonne, and his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in his people made one with his Sonne: yea, ſo great that when men harden their hearts againſt his Sonne, the Goſpel, and ſpirit of his Sonne, and turne to oprreſſe thoſe that are veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of mercy; The more he loves his Sonne, and the dearer his people are to him; the more doth his mercy move him to plead their cauſe, and plague their enemies, and ſo he ſmote <hi>Egypt,</hi> overthrew <hi>Pharoh,</hi> and his Hoſt in the ſea, ſmote great and mighty Kings, &amp;c. For his mercy endureth for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136.10.20. Oh heavy when mercy ſtands againſt them!</p>
               <p n="5">5 By the greatneſſe of torments, and puniſhments to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted on ſuch ſinners; which as the Scriptures ſets it forth, is very terrible; for it is the ſame that at firſt was prepared for the Divell, and his Angels, who ſinned freely, and without a Tempter, or any cauſe, <hi>Iude</hi> 6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. So it appeares that.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The Death on mankind for the firſt tranſgreſſion was an Allenation from God, a Death in ſinne, and a Death in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and torments due to ſinnings againſt the grace of God manifeſted in the Creation: And had there been no remedy, or prevention, this death and puniſhment would have been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall; for men in particular ſuffering it, could never have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome it to get out of it (only by reaſon of Gods preventing mercy, in keepeing man from cating of that Tree of life, of which, if he had eaten, his Body had been immortall, and ſo capeable of eternall ſufferings) He ſhould ſuffer eternally in his ſoalc; And his body with the ſting, and povſon of ſinn, and curſe ſhould be alwayes ſuffering till it turned to rottenneſſe, and ſo to duſt againe; and this is the firſt death, which came
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:113873:35"/>on all men at firſt, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. and 3.19. And this Jeſus Chriſt hath in dying for our ſinnes, and riſeing for our Juſtification as the publike perſon overcome, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. and obtained of his Father power to eaſe men in this life of ſo much paines of this mortalilty as he pleaſeth, and to raiſe them all from this firſt Death at the laſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.21.22.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The Death or puniſhments on men for ſinning againſt the grace of redemption, in hardening themſelves againſt the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and bounty of God, and meanes through Chriſt procured, to leade them to repentance, and ſo for their turning herefrom, and going after their own wayes; are afflictions, and troubles on ſoule, and body, name, and eſtate, having ſome mixtures of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rcy, and being to hide pride from man, and force them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, &amp;c. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. <hi>Iob</hi> 33. And theſe are called, wrath, Judgements, puniſhments, corrections, out of which yet there is a way, and meane of eſcape, <hi>Iob</hi> 33. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 27.4.5.</p>
               <p n="3">3 But the Death and torment for theſe that have perſiſted in in reſiſting, the ſpirit in the meanes, and refuſing this life in Chriſt, and to have him raigne over them, till they be given o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to ſatan is more terrible, and is eternall, on ſoule, and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy raiſed and made immortad, and ſo capeable of eternall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering; And this is called the ſecond death; Hell fire, The lake of fire, unquenchable fire, and even that which was at firſt prepared for the Divell, and his Angels, into which all theſe ſhall goe, who by their wilfull perſiſting in rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the truth, and walking in lyes, and murthers become of the wicked one, the Children of the Divell, and the ſeed of the Serpent. And ſo ſhall ſhare of the ſame puniſhment, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.12. <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.41.44. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. onely in the ſting and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting worme, that never dyeth, but alwayes tormenteth, there is now this more to theſe miſerable men, then to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels; The remembrance of a Remedy ſince their firſt fall, which they have refuſed, which will torment exceedingly, but that cannot be in the Divels torment.</p>
               <p n="6">6 And yet there is one thing more, in which appeareth the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectualneſſe of the Blood, and Sacrifice of Chriſt, on theſe rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious refuſers, and that proveth the appearance of the ſame, to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:113873:36"/>be in all theſe 5. forementioned poynts; And that is the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and condemnation of theſe Rebe's in that.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The Lord Jeſus Chriſt that ſhed his Blood, and offered this Sacrifice, ſhall even by vertue thereof be their Judge, even he that dyed, and roſe, and revived for them, to be their Lord, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4 9.12. he that bought them, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. even he ſhall be their Judge, and they ſhall appeare before his judgement ſear, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. yea even becauſe he dyed for them, God hath exalted him, and they ſhall come before him to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him Lord, by whom they might have been ſaved, and ſhall be judged righteouſly, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.10.11. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 45.23. And of this God hath given aſſurance, and offered faith to all men in that he raiſed him from the Dead, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.31. And this is one efficacy of his Sacrifice on ſuch as refuſed him (in whom they might have enjoyed the comfortable efficacies) that they ſhall acknowledge him Lord, and be judged by him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. And they ſhall yeeld it right, it ſhould be ſo.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That which ſhall be layd to their charge in this Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that by which their ſinnes ſhall be evidenced, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated againſt them, their ſinnes that will be layd to their charge will be their ignorance of God, and not obeying his Goſpel, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. Their unbeliefe with all the fruits there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.8.9.10. Their Impenitency, and not profiting by, but hardening their hearts againſt the meanes by the Sacrifice of Chriſt procured, and extended, to leade them to repentance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4.5. Their evill thoughts, and hard ſpeeches of him, and his goodneſſe, in his word, wayes, people, <hi>Iude</hi> 15. and ſo for every Idle word, and all their Idolatries, and unmerciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ungodly deeds, which through their diſobedience to his goodneſſe they have runn into, <hi>Iude</hi> 15. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.36. yea every ſecret thing ſhall then be manifeſt: That by which the vileneſſe of their ſinnes, and juſtneſſe of their Judgement ſhall be evidenced, will be the put chaſe Chriſt hath made for them, and they denyed him that ſo dearly bought them, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. The mercy extended to them, againſt which they har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened themſelves, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5. And all the meanes, yea even the Goſpel ſent to move them to ſeeke the Lord, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.16-24.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:113873:36"/>yea the very blood and Sacrifice of Chriſt, by which all the reſidue was procured for them, which they have contemned, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. yea and the Spirit of grace, with all his ſpirituall hints of light, motions, reproofs, and allurements which they have deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24.25, &amp;c. All which will then appear as aggravations of their ſinne and judgement; and this is another ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy of the blood and Sacrifice of Chriſt, on ſuch as have refuſed him, that when the day of grace is paſt, it will occaſion the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencing and aggravation of their ſin and judgement.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The order, rule, law, or medium, by and according to which the judgement ſhall proceed, and that is the Goſpel; in which Chriſt had before been ſet forth a ſaviour for them, the propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for their ſinnes, and full of Spirit to ſend forth, and ſo inviting them to repentance and faith, with aſſurance of renovation, remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and life on believing, and warning that the iſſue of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wayes would be death. This Goſpel, as it is the word which Chriſt and his Apoſtles ſpake; ſo ſuch is the truth and verity of it, that even the rejectors thereof; it ſhall judge, and hee ſhall judge them by and according to it, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.47.48 49. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16. And this is another efficacie of the pretious Blood and Sacrifice of Chriſt on ſuch as have rebelliouſly refuſed it; that by the declaration or word thereof, and according to that declaration ſhall be the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.1.18.20. &amp; 10.18. <hi>John</hi> 15.22.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That which ſhall convince of ſin, and ſet home the ſentence of ſinne, and of judgement to the heart, and ſo kindle the fire that never ſhall be quenched; is even the ſame Spirit of the Lord, which by vertue of his Death, Reſurrection, and Sacrifice, he in his aſcenſion (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.18.) received; and in the day of grace was ſtriving with them. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3. to have convinced them, and began to kindle a fire that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would have co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed nothing but their fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affections and luſts, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.7. their carnall wiſdome and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and then have healed them and given them life, <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.23.24 but they would none of his reproofes, but quenched this heat, and reſiſted this Spirit, till he left ſtriting with them. But now will this holy and Almighty Spirit from the Lord that bought them, return again upon them, and contince them of ſinne, becauſe they have not beleeved on Chriſt &amp;c. <hi>John</hi> 16.8, 9 10. and ſo ſet home the ſentence to their heart, that they cannotavoid it; and by his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:113873:37"/>Almighty breathing word, like a ſtream of Brimſtone, kindle that fire that never ſhall be quenched, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.33. And this is another efficacy of the Sacrifice of Chriſt on ſuch as have rebelliouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed him; that the Spirit, he, by vertue of his Sacrifice received to ſend forth to call men, ſhal yet ſet home the ſentence even on thoſe that rejected him.</p>
               <p>Oh then in that day, though to their woe, they ſhall ſee and confeſſe (what ever before they thought, or others told them) that Chriſt died for them, though they periſh; that Chriſt bought them, though they have denied him; that hee had wrought re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption for them, though they have ſold themſelves again to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; that there was mercies for them in him, though they forſook them; that he ſtrove with them, to win them to him, though they reſiſted him; that his word and wayes were good, though they beleeved not: And now to behold him that ſo dearly bought them, and graciouſly cal'd them, and they rewarded him with hatred for his love, to come in fury to judge them, and to perceive the Blood and Sacrifice that once would have ſpoken peace to them, to riſe up againſt them; the Goſpel that once declared good tidings to them from the verity of it, to bee a condemning word to them; mercy that once waited for them, to be now turned againſt them; the holy Spirit that was once moving in them to draw them from ſinne to God, to bee now ſentencing them under ſinne, and unto death: O what a terrour will this be! And how will the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the redemption wrought by Chriſt, the mercy once ſhewn, and the doore to life once opened, through which they might have been ſaved, now adde to the terrour, and the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of all the vanities, falſe Doctrines, and humane applauſe, for which they have turned aſide, will but encreaſe the vexation, and (now while they ſee thoſe that embraced and followed Chriſt whom they deſpiſed, to goe into the joy of their Lord, into eternall life) to ſee their own ſin, and judgement in the height, and the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible preſence of the Lord driving them into the lake of fire that burneth ever, and out of which there is no eſcape! Oh how great this terror! yea how eaſeleſſe, how tormenting, how intollerable, unavoidable, and remedileſſe! How endleſſe will the eternall ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in that fire be, when the leaſt drops of thoſe mercifull effects of the Sacrifice, that are in this day tendered, and ſo refuſed, will
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:113873:37"/>not be vouchſafed; nothing then but biting, gnawings, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in every part of ſoule and body? Now conſider this yee that forget God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.22. leſt he teare you in peeces, and there be none to deliver.</p>
               <p>Thoſe, that know and beleeve all theſe forementioned efficacies of the pretious Blood and Sacrifice of Chriſt, they know alſo this terror of the Lord, &amp; they are perſwaded and reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled to God, in beliefe of the reconciliation God hath wrought in Chriſt for the world, and they in witneſſing the ſame, doe perſwade and beſeech others now in this day of grace, to be reconciled to God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10, 11, 19, 20. &amp; 6.1.2. in which the comfortable efficacies will be found.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 12.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The uſefulneſſe of this pretious Blood and Sacrifice of Chriſt, known and beleevingly remembred.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THat we may have the better underſtanding of this, it is alſo to be underſtood, 1. Of what the Propoſition is. 2. Of what knowing is here meant. 3. Of what faith it is here to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. 4. What remembrance is here meant. And 5. what is meant by uſefulneſſe; that in all wee may conceive according to Scripture ſenſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, for the propoſition, It is of the pretious Blood and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſt, and that is to be underſtood both of it ſelfe primely; and of the Doctrine of the Goſpel in which it is ſet forth inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally: and that as is before ſhewn; concerning</p>
               <p n="1">1. The manifold ſenſe in which thoſe tearms are uſed in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as for his Death, His reſurnection, His Preſentation and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering to God, The prevalency with God, the ſpirituall applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to believers, and prevalency in them; and the rich love of God, and ſatisfaction to God, and conſcience and Spirit appearing and ſtreaming there through, as is ſhewn Chap. 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ends of this pretious Blood and Sacrifice, and that in reſpect of Chriſt, according to his double Miſſion into the world, and his double buſineſſe in leaving the world; and in reſpect of mankind according to the double miſery and enmity againſt God
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:113873:38"/>they were fallen into.</p>
               <p>And in reſpect of the Church according to the double need ſhe hath of Chriſt; &amp; in all of them, the ends of the ſhedding his bloud, the end of his offering his ſacrifice with the vertue of his bloud to God, The ends of the diſcovery and ſpirituall application of it to men, as is ſhewn Chap. 3. and 4.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The neceſſity of this pretious Bloud and Sacrifice, both of his dying, and reſurrection; and of his preſentation and offering it to God, and of his ſpirituall diſcovery, and application to men, as is ſhewn Chap. 5. and enlarged by ſome conſideration of the Law, Chap. 6.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The excellency and dignity of this pretious Bloud and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and that in the Sacrifice it ſelf, in reſpect of the Prieſt, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, the Altar: In the Declaration, in reſpect of the three Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, the Spirit, the Water, the Bloud: In the abundant grace, and the great hope appearing therein, as is ſhewn Chap. 7.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The vertue, operation, and prevalencie of this pretious Bloud, and Sacrifice of Chriſt, as it was offered to God, as is ſhewn Chap. 8.</p>
               <p>And as through that prevalency with God, mercy is ſhewn to men, as is ſhewn Chap. 9. And as it is ſpiritually applyed to the heart of Believers, as is ſhewn Chap. 10. And as it will be laid to the charge of ſuch as have rejected it, as is ſhewn Chap. 11.</p>
               <p>And all this is to be underſtood about the pretious Bloud and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Chriſt, and in the Doctrine of Chriſt; and ſo is the meaning of the Propoſition.</p>
               <p n="2">2 For the knowledge, or knowing here meant, and of which the Scripture meaneth, when it ſpeakes of the knowledge, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt, which he giveth to men;</p>
               <p n="1">1 It is not that knowledge, or knowing which is naturall, <hi>Rom:</hi> 3.10. and 11.34. Truth it is, that as God through Chriſt, and for his ſake for a time preſerveth the naturall life of man; ſo through Chriſt, and for his ſake, he giveth, and preſerveth unto men for the time of this naturall life, their naturall underſtanding, reaſon, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaind conception, <hi>Job</hi> 35.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.32. By which they may learne and underſtand ſome things in the workes of God, <hi>Job.</hi> 36 24, 25. And ſome things in the Narration, or Hiſtory of the Scriptures, or Word of God, <hi>Rom:</hi> 2.17.21. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.26, 27. And it
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:113873:38"/>is alſo true, that God hath imprinted and manifeſted his wiſdome, even ſome teſtimonies of his being and goodneſſe in his workes of Creation and Providence, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 19.1-6. <hi>Act.</hi> 14.17. <hi>Rom:</hi> 1.19, 20. and 2.4. And in the Scriptures or Word of God hath ſet forth Chriſt the wiſdome of God, what he hath done, what he is, and what he will do, and doth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24, <hi>Io.</hi> 5.39, 46. <hi>Rom:</hi> 4.23.25. And yet this is alſo true, that in reſpect of all men that are but na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, and have but their naturall life and underſtanding, though preſerved in mercy for Chriſts ſake; This light ſhineth in darkneſſe and the darkneſſe comprehendeth it not. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.5. Men by their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall wiſdome do not find out, or attain to know God in the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God ſet forth in the bookes of Creatures, or Scriptures, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1.21. The naturall man cannot know the things of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, which he teacheth concerning the things of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 2.14. So that the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall man, with all his naturall powers and parts, cannot attaine the right knowledge of the things of God in Chriſt, by all his ſearch, either in the Workes of God, or in the Word of God, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.15.</p>
               <p n="2">2 It is not that knowledge which is both naturall, and artificial, attained by knowledge of Arts, in uſe of Arts, and artificiall helps, whence that interrogation, &amp; challenge, <hi>Iſa</hi> 33. where is the Scribe? &amp;c. A truth it is, that through Chriſt, and for his ſake, God bleſſeth mens induſtly in ſtudy of Letters, Tongues, Arts, and Sciences, that are naturall and honeſt; and alſo their honeſt induſtry in uſe and exerciſe thereof; So as many thereby become very knowing, wiſe, prudent, and skilfull Orators and Diſputers: In ſtudy of the works of God, they may attain excellent knowledge about the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of ſoyles and ſeaſons, the nature of Beaſts, Birds, Plants, the nature, diſpontion, and manners of men, and ſo be very skilfull for husbandry, trading, and merchandize, Government of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weales,<note place="margin">Iſa. 3.1.4.</note> Lawes, Warre, Phyſick, &amp;c. And this is a great mercy to a Common-wealth and a correction to want them: And in ſtudy of the Scriptures, ſuch may attain excellent knowledge, for tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Tongu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, underſtanding and explicating Hiſtories, diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Times and ſome Proprecies, and of the ſcope and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of places, and ety<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ologie of words, which is a mercy to the Nation where they live (while they keep their bounds;) yea, and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:113873:39"/>to the Churches alſo, <hi>Matth.</hi> 2.5, 6. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.54,—57, <hi>Iſa</hi> 3.1,—4. But yet this is alſo true, that the verity, excellency, depth, pretiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, enjoyment, and efficacy of the things of God in Chriſt, theſe Rabbies and Princes of the World for wiſdome and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, cannot by this wiſdome find out, diſcern, approve, or receive, though they reade, and ſtudy the words in which it is expreſt; yet in thoſe words it is hidden from them, and they by their wiſdome in all their ſearching cannot finde out this myſterious wiſdome of God in Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1 20.21. and 2.7, 8, 14. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.25. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.21. So as naturall and artificiall knowledge and wiſdome can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reach, or attaine the right knowledge of the things of God in Chriſt, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.2, 3, 4.</p>
               <p>So that the knowledge, or knowing here ſpoke of, is not naturall or artificiall, but ſupernaturall, as ſhall be ſhewn anon.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Neither yet is this ſuch a knowledge, or knowing, of which, nature is no way capable of the receit of it, or ſuch as doth deſtroy the naturall or artificiall knowledge, or as if they could no way conſiſt, and be together in the ſame ſubject, <hi>Act.</hi> 18.24, 28. and 7.22, 23, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.24, 25. The body or humane nature of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, neither did, nor could raiſe it ſelf; yet was it capable of being raiſed, and was by the Divine Power not deſtroyed, but rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; And yet the reſurrection, though it was of the humane nature, yet it was not at all by the humane, but by the divine nature, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Spirit and Power of God, that not the divine, but the humane nature was raiſed, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.23, 24, 30, 31. <hi>Rom:</hi> 4.24. and 6.4. The eyes of blind <hi>Bartemeus</hi> could by no naturall meanes attain to ſee, but they were capable of receiving ſight by the guift of God, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.46. — 52. And for the better underſtanding this buſineſſe, wee may conſider, that it is appointed to men once to dye, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.10. and when they do dye, and give up the Ghoſt, then all their naturall and artificiall knowledge and wiſdome dyes together with them; And as they ſhall be one day raiſed again by the Spirit and power of Chriſt; ſo then the knowledge they have, ſhall not be naturall or artificiall, but only that which they ſhall have from the power of God that raiſed them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.11, 12. And the members of Chriſt by vertue of their union with him, ſhall have all knowledge tending to happineſſe from him by the divine nature filling them with light, and leading both ſoule and body, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.2.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:113873:39"/>So that they ſhall then know perfectly and ſee, as they are ſeen, and know as they are known; But here in this life as their bodies, ſo their naturall powers are ſpiritually humbled and mortified, that they may in the regeneration be quickned by,<note place="margin">Rom 8.10 11, 12.23.</note> and made ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Spirit, not annihilated, or ſlain; nor is the man perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and totally made alive in the regeneration here wrought, nor will be, till perfectly and totally dead, in reſpect of all naturall life; <hi>but the Spirit is alive for Righteouſneſſe ſake,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 13.9. And the Spirit quickneth alſo the mortall body, and ſo he may as pleaſeth him, The naturall powers and faculties, for ſuch ſervice as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.29.</note> The to tall redemption of the body, being yet waited for, our knowledge yet imperfect; ſo then, though neither natural, nor artificiall knowledge, bee the knowledge of ſpirituall things, nor doth, nor can attain it; yet the ſpirituall knowledge may conſiſt, and be together with them in the ſame ſubject, and having humbled and ſlaine the pride of them, may make ſuch uſe of them in ſome ſervices as the Spirit pleaſeth; and as it is a puniſhment or corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction during this life, to have the body by Diſeaſes diſabled from ſervice, and tormented with pain, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.28. ſo is it to have the naturall reaſon and underſtanding made uſeleſſe, or diſtracted; So that this knowledge, or knowing here meant, is not ſuch as ſlaies, or makes the other altogether uſeleſſe: As for that doting upon na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall or artificiall knowledge, the humane wiſdome, or the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Rabbies and Prince; of this world, by which many ſo magnifie it, as the only, or neceſſary, or at leaſt the beſt mean, to find out and diſcover the things of God: It is a groſſe and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous conceit, and God hath executed judgment on that Idoll, and ſtained the pride of that glory, and ſo will do ſtill, in that the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God is hidden from them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.25. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.21. and they know it not, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7, 8 14. And few of them are called to it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26. And thoſe that are, have their former wiſdome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fooled, and they abaſed in the acknowledgment of the vanity of it, before they receive the ſpirituall wiſdome, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19, 20. And the truth is, this magnifying of humane wiſdome and knowledge, is the very enmity of Chriſt, and the very Spirit of Antichriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.4.9. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4. that moves to the building of <hi>Babell</hi> to Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try or Superſtition, to be as God, in the Temple of God, to appoint Doctrines, Lawes, Officers, and to perſecute the Truth, and the Children of the Truth: As for that ſaying, that this naturall and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:113873:40"/>artificiall knowledge, this humane learning and wiſdome, is an Handmaid to Divinity: Though this be but the Doctrine of men, and no where affirmed in the Word of God, yet if it be rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, it might by collection appear agreeable thereto; for if it ſhould be meant an handmaid or help to find out, and attain Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, that were rather to be a Mother then a handmaid, and this is before proved falſe: And if any object, in men ſanctified, it may, that is alſo falſe, <hi>Job.</hi> 11.7, 8, 9. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.2, 3, 4. He that hath ſeeing eyes will not be befooled, to take a candle to find out the Sun; And again, if by handmaid ſhould be meant a guide, and help, to limit, order, and better, the teaching of the Spirit, the divine light, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and motions of grace, that they may be more profitable and effectuall; this is rather to be a Miſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is then a Handmaid, and if ſuffered in this, it would ſoone corrupt from the ſimplicity of Chriſt. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.22, 23. And againſt this the Apoſtle hath proteſted, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.1, 4, 5. But if by a handmaid, bee meant a handmaid indeed, that which is taken of its Throne, and ſubmitted to Divinity, even to the Divine Spirit, and grace of Chriſt, to uſe as a Servant accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to its pleaſure, and divine wiſdome, and motion, for tranſlating etymologizing, and diſcanting on words, for analyzing places, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring places, uſing Similies, &amp;c. Then if keeping the ſervants place is uſefull, as grace leads to the uſe of it; And in this ſence I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſome godly men have uſed this ſaying, and where it is ſo uſed it may be included in this ſaying, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 103. <hi>Bleſſe the Lord, O my ſoule, and all that is within me bleſſe his holy Name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 But the knowledge, or knowing here meant is ſupernaturall, ſpirituall, and divine, and that appeares in three things that are to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in this knowledge, though diſtinct, yet never ſeparate in this knowledge, or knowing.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that the Giver or Teacher of this knowledge, is the holy Spirit, even God in Chriſt, and the Spirit proceedin from both, <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.6. For the Lord giveth wiſdome, and out of his mouth cometh knowledge and underſtanding, <hi>Iſa</hi> 48.17. I am the Lord thy God, which teacheth thee to profit, <hi>Iſa</hi> 54.13. All my children ſhall be taught of the Lord, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.23. When the Spirit of Truth is come he will guide you into all Truth, and this is in a heavenly manner, as the Scripture ſhewes.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 By a divine, not bodily, but ſpirituall light, ſhine, or revelation,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:113873:40"/>in unbaring or manifeſting to the ſoul, or mind, the things of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.32. In which after yee were illuminated, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. hath ſhined in our hearts, the light of the knowledge of the glory of God, <hi>Math</hi> 16.17. Fleſh and blood hath not revealed it unto thee, but my Father which is in heaven, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. God hath revealed to us by his Spirit.</item>
                  <item>2. By a divine infuſion, or inſpiration to the heart of a Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſtreame, motion, or evidence and perſwaſion of the truth and goodneſſe of that of Chriſt diſcovered, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 44.3. I will powre my Spirit upon thy ſeed. <hi>Job</hi> 32.8. The inſpiration of the Almigty giveth them underſtanding. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 30.21. Thine eares ſhall heare a word behind thee, ſaying, This is the way. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 50.4. The Lord hath given mee the tongue of the learned (ſaith Chriſt) that I ſhould know how to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 52.6. They ſhal know in that day, that I am he that doe ſpeak, behold it is I.</item>
                  <item>3. By a Divine power or Spirituall ſtrength, ſo as he cauſeth the blind to ſee, and the deafe to heare, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 29.18. and openeth the heart to attend, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.14. whence he is called, The finger of the Lord, &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.28. Such is the Teacher, and teaching, by which this knowledge is attained.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Secondly, the Object of this knowledge, That which the holy ſpirit teacheth, and glorifieth in teaching, is Chriſt and the things of Chriſt, as the verity, ends, neceſſity, excellency, and vertue of Chriſt and his pretious Blood and Sacrifice, the infiniteneſſe and freeneſſe of Gods love appearing therethrough, and the promiſes and hope given therein; yea Chriſt the wiſdome of God, and the power of God, and wiſdome, &amp;c. to us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24.30. <hi>John</hi> 16.14. He ſhall glorifie me, for he ſhall take of mine, and ſhall ſhew unto you. <hi>John</hi> 15.26. he ſhall teſtifie of me, <hi>John</hi> 14.26. hee ſhall teach you all things, and bring all things to your remembrance, whatſoever I have ſaid unto you. And ſo 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. &amp; 4.6.</p>
               <p>Thirdly. the manner of knowing is likewiſe ſpirituall, and that is both,
<list>
                     <item>1. By that new light, diſpoſition, and ſpirit he hath put in the heart, which is as a new and ſpiritual eye, to ſee ſpirituall things, which is not by a humane diſcourſe, collecting one thing from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, judging to know unſeen cauſes from ſome ſeen and ſenſible effects, like humane wiſdome, and the ſpirit of the world; but ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:113873:41"/>diſcerning in the very light, and of the very evidence of the Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12.16. ſo as they may prove the effects ſound from their knowledge of the cauſe, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.19. So <hi>John</hi> 1.14. We beheld his glory, the glory of the onely begotten of the Father, full of grace and truth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.9. In thy light we ſhall ſee light. And in this, as no mans humane wiſdome and learning doth further his diſcerning, ſo no mans ignorance, or want thereof, ſhall hinder, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.130. The entrance of thy word giveth light, and giveth underſtanding to the ſimple. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.25. Thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt tevealed them unto Babes. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.20. we know that the Sonne of God is come, and hath given us an underſtanding, that wee may know him that is true.</item>
                     <item>2. By a certain inward experience of the beauty, excellency, and ſweet ſavour of the things known; a pleaſing delightfull, and reviving taſt and ſavour, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14 15.16. manifeſteth the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of his knowledge, a ſweet ſavour of Chriſt, a ſavour of life unto life, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8. For the excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt, for whom I have ſuffered the loſſe of all things, and do count them but Dung, that I may win Chriſt 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3. If yee have taſted that the Lord is gracious, to whom coming, &amp;c. And this is the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge here meant:</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>A ſupernaturall and ſpirituall knowledge of Chriſt, and the things of Chriſt taught by the Spirit of Chriſt, with light, motion and power, giving an underſtanding to diſcern, and heart to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the things knowne. In which knowledge as there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers degrees: ſo ſome are but Babes and Novices in it, and ſo in reſpect of ſome others, unlearned and unskilfull in it: others more skilfull; yea ſome Fathers, and very ſtable. And this is the knowledge the Spirit in the Scripture ſpeaketh of when it ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of the things of Chriſt and his Spirit. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.1.—15. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12.13.14. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. which whoſo wanteth alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, whomſoever he hath heard preach the Goſpel, what books ſoever he hath read, and what knowledge ſoever he hath attained in the Scriptures, what degree, what office, or profeſſion ſoever he hath; yet he hath not ſeen the image of the Father, nor heard his voyce, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. <hi>John</hi> 1.14. &amp; 5 37.38. &amp;c. And ſo knoweth not the Father nor the Son, nor the things of the Spirit, nor ſuch as
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:113873:41"/>are born of the Spirit, 1 <hi>John.</hi> 3.1. <hi>John</hi> 15.21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12.14.15.16. And ſo the knowing here meant is ſupernaturall, ſpirituall, and experimentall, bee it little or much, more or leſſe, and ſo yet wavering or ſtable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 13.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>3. Of what Faith it is here to be underſtood, and <hi>4.</hi> of what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="3">3. FOr the Faith here meant, it is a Divine and Spirituall faith: for the better underſtanding whereof, theſe ſeaven things may be conſidered about it. 1. The object of it. 2. The Mover or Worker of it. 3. The nature and act of it. 4. The motion in, and of it. 5. The ſubject in which it is, and immediate inſtruments in, and with which it moveth and worketh. 6. The power, life, or principle in in it. 7. The oneneſſe of it in diverſity of the degrees, and acts.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For the object that the eye of this Faith is ſet on, &amp; on which it looketh, to which it runneth, on which it leaneth and reſteth; This object is Divine, and but one, even God. In the Lord put I my truſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.1. and 11, 1. and 121.1. and 123.1. and 9.10. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.4.</p>
               <p>Yet this object is conſiderable in a threefold reſpect, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. In reſpect of the moſt inmoſt, and utmoſt object, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, foundation, and fountain of all help, ſafety and ſatisfying, and that is God himſelfe, even the divine Nature in his infinite wiſdome, power, mercy love, truth, &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42. God our refuge and ſtrength. &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.2. Rock, Fortreſſe, Deliverer, &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.1. Light and ſalvation even God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.24. that raiſed up Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord from the dead, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.9.10. which raiſed the dead, who delivered, &amp;c. and doth deliver, &amp;c, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. By whom we beleeved. 1.5.5. truſteth in God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2, 13.</p>
               <p>In reſpect of the inmoſt and abſolute <hi>Medium,</hi> through which this faith diſcerneth, &amp;c. commeth to, and faſteneth on God, and without which there can bee no diſcerning of, or comming in to God, or cloſing with him at all. And this inmoſt and abſolute mediate object, is Jeſus Chriſt the Sonne of God, made Man of the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> who is the Saviour of the world,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:113873:42"/>and the Head and Husband of the Church, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.3.4. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.14. <hi>John</hi> 4.42. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.32. and 1.22.23. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.6. I am the Way, the Truth and the Life, no man commeth to the Father but by me. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.18. Through him we have both an acceſſe by one Spirit unto the Father, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.7. that through him all might beleeve, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.4. Such truſt have we through Chriſt to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Whence alſo this faith is called, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.4. and 2.5. faith in Chriſt: and <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.15. believing in him. And ſo Chriſt Jeſus is object of this faith; and that
<list>
                     <item>1. In reſpect of what he hath done for us, in dying for our ſins, and riſing for our juſtification, and offering up himſelfe a Sacrifice and ranſome to God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.25. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6.</item>
                     <item>2. In reſpect of what he is (through that hee hath done) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come for us; as namely, that nee is (<hi>Eph.</hi> 2.14.) our Peace, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.2. the propitiation for our ſinnes, 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 1.30. wiſdome, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, ſanctification, and redemption. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.3. our Lord and Saviour.</item>
                     <item>3. In reſpect alſo of what (through that he hath done, and is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come for us) he now doth in heaven for us; and that is, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.24. appeare in the preſence of God for us. And <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. ever liveth to make interceſſion for us. And ſo <hi>Heb.</hi> 9 14.15.</item>
                     <item>4. In reſpect of what he will doe in and for all ſuch as through grace beleeving in him, accept that he hath done, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.11. and depend on him according to that he is and doth, for that he will do in and for them; as namely, that he will ſupport and uphold them, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 43.1, 2. and cauſe all to work together for good to them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. and ſend forth his Spirit from the Father to them, to beare witneſſe of him to, and through them, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.26.27. to mind them of his words, and teach them all things, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.26. to take of the things of Chriſt, and ſhew to them, and ſo glorifie him to them, and thereby comfort them, and lead them into all truth, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.14 16. &amp; 16.13.14.15. to make them fruitfull in their miniſtration, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.5.16. convincing the world, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.7 8, 9 10. calling in to Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14-16. and 3.3. and anſwering their enemies, <hi>Matth</hi> 10.20. and to ſanctifie and preſerve them to the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.24. And thus is Jeſus Chriſt the next and neereſt object, and the onely abſolute and inmoſt <hi>Medium,</hi> through which
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:113873:42"/>this faith faſteneth upon God, or the Divine Nature, which is the moſt inmoſt and outmoſt object.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, in reſpect of the Inſtrument, and outward <hi>Medium,</hi> through which Chriſt, and ſo God in Chriſt, is beheld, beleeved, and truſted in: and this is the word of God, that which declareth Chriſt, and Gods love, and gracious mind in and through him: and ſo the name or great report, and fame of the glory or goodneſſe of God in Chriſt, in his love, mercy, power, wiſdome, &amp;c. Whence he is ſaid to have magnified his word above all his name, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138 2. and ſo this faith is called, <hi>A beleeving the Goſpel, and receiving his words, Mark</hi> 1.15. <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.22. and 5.47. And ſo this faith and truſt is in praiſing God in his Word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56.10. and glorifying his word, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.48. And ſo the object of this faith is, God in Chriſt, in and according to his word.</p>
               <p>The firſt next Inſtrumentall and outward mediate object of this faith, is the word and Goſpel, with the promiſes thereof, which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covereth Chriſt, and God in Chriſt, and that, in which, and for which we are to truſt in him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.49.50.</p>
               <p>The ſecond inward, inmoſt, and abſolute mediate object of this Faith, is Jeſus Chriſt, in that which hee hath done, is become, doth, and will doe, which the Word reporteth and aſſureth, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3.</p>
               <p>The laſt, inmoſt, and utmoſt object of this Faith, is God in Chriſt, in his infinite wiſdome, love, power, &amp;c. which appeareth in, and through Chriſt, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10.</p>
               <p>And ſo the object of faith altogether in one, is, God in Chriſt, as diſcovered in his Word by his Spirit. This, and this onely is the object of this faith.</p>
               <p>So that no Arme of Fleſh, or device of men, not multitude of men, Ammunition, or Forts; not riches, nor ſtrength, nor wiſdome, nor any ſelf-wrought righteouſneſſe, or workes, can be in any ſort the object of Faith, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.23. <hi>Job.</hi> 9.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Either the inmoſt, and utmoſt object of faith and truſt, God onely is that, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.24. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17.</item>
                  <item>2. Or the inmoſt and abſolute mediate object, through which men beleeve and truſt in God; Chriſt Jeſus is only that, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.19. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4.7.—18.</item>
                  <item>3. Or the Inſtrumentall and outward mediate object, through
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:113873:43"/>and according to which, men beleeve and truſt in Chriſt, and in God in Chriſt; his Word onely is that, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56.4.10.</item>
               </list>
               <p>As for prayers and endevours in uſe of means, when they iſſue from, and be the fruits of this faith and confidence in God in Chriſt according to his Word; then in this confidence, bleſſing may bee expected in them, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.27.29. But they cannot be the object either as Rule, or <hi>Medium,</hi> or Object, as aforeſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.32. &amp; 10.2.3. The Word, the Rule: Chriſt, the <hi>Medium:</hi> God, the Object: and ſo God in Chriſt, according to his word, is onely and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the object of this faith.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for the Mover or Worker of this faith; that which produceth it, and in and by which it is raiſed and wrought; it is not the force of any humane diſcourſe, reaſoning, or Argument, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.1.4.5. nor is it the iſſue or birth of any fervent endevours, or workings of men, in, and according to the law of works, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2. yea though endeavoured and done to get Chriſt, the righteouſneſſe of God thereby, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.31.32. and 10.2.3.4. neither yet is it a concluſion, or ſpring from the appearance of any inward or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward changes, effected in a man by any ſuch reaſonings, or endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourings, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11, 12. 2 Cor. 10.7.12.18. But this Mover and effector verily is</p>
               <p n="1">1. The appearance of the grace of God, in and through the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, even of that free and immenſe love of God in the gift of his Sonne to be the Saviour of the world, and the ſatisfaction made by Chriſt, and the fulneſſe of grace and truth in him. This grace of God appearing in and through Chriſt, moveth to believe, encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth and draweth thereto; whence this faith is called, <hi>The gift of God by grace, and not of works, Eph.</hi> 2.8.9. and they that have it, are ſaid to have believed through grace, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.27.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Spirit proceeding from the Father and the Sonne in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of this grace, effecteth this faith; and ſo the hand of the Lord, that is, the Spirit of the Lord, or the demonſtration of the Spirit and power, is ſaid to bring to believe in God, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4.5.</p>
               <p>And in reſpect of both theſe, this grace and Spirit working faith, it is ſaid, After the kindneſſe and love of God to manward, appeared; he ſaved us by the waſhing of regeneration, and renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.4.5. And ſo the beleevers are ſaid to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:113873:43"/>be borne of water, and of the ſpirit, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.5. And ſo as the ſpirit worketh faith, ſo for working it, he doth not glorifie the workes of the Law, or any frames, or workes of men. But he glorifies Chriſt, and Gods rich grace in Chriſt, to beget faith, and hope in men, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.13.14. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. And ſo to ſay in a word; It is the ſpirituall appearance of rich grace, in, and by which this faith is wrought; Grace is the mover.</p>
               <p n="3">3 For the nature, and Act of this faith; There be three things together meeting in one, in this Act of believing, or this faith of which is here teached, as Scripture, and experience of Believers ſhewes; that is to ſay,</p>
               <p n="1">1 An aſſent, and credit-giving to the report, or Teſtimony of the Goſpel, and that which by the ſpirit is evidenced, and appeareth through the ſame report: the want of which the Prophet complaines of, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 53. Who hath believed our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port? which not-believing, the Apoſtle calles, making God a lyer, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.10. And this aſſent and credit-giving to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Goſpel, was in thoſe, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.48. They magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the word of the Lord, (counted it good, and true) and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Teſtimony, and ſo did the Theſſalonians likewiſe, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. And this is the firſt Act, without which; no faith at all, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.47. and 8.24.</p>
               <p n="2">2 An inward, and hearty approbation of the goodneſſe of that reported in the Goſpel, in reſpect of that Chriſt hath done, and that he is become, and that he doth, and that he is ready to do. And in reſpect of the rich, free, and great love of God appearing therein, ſo as all other Excellencies are but loſſe, and Dung in compariſon of it, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.7.8 9.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Through this aſſenting and believing-approbation; there is an inward, and hearty reſting, and relyance upon Chriſt, and God in Chriſt, for the diſpenſation of this grace, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting that which appertaines to him to do, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1.2.5-10.</p>
               <p>Firſt, creditting the ſavings of the Goſpel; and through thoſe ſayings, Believing Chriſt himſelfe, and the ſpirits Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of him, and in that believing, truſting in God in Chriſt, for that promiſed, and ſo believing the ſayings, receiving Chriſt,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:113873:44"/>and truſting in God through Chriſt; is the nature, and Act of this believing.</p>
               <p n="4">4 For the motions, orſtrings in this believing or faith; they are,</p>
               <p n="1">1 An inward and hearty acknowledgement of, and ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Jeſus Chriſt, as the Lord, and Saviour, and ſo to this grace appearing in him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15. He dyed for all, that they which live, ſhould not henceforth live unto themſelves, but unto him that dyed for them, and roſe againe, and ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.8. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we live, we live unto the Lord, and whether we die, we die unto the Lord, &amp;c. verſe 9. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19-20. Ye are not your own, yet are bought with a price, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.17. Ye have obeyed from the heart, the forme of Doctrine to which ye were delivered. True it is, that all men ſhall one day be brought ſo farr to the knowledge of the truth, that they ſhall therein be brought to confeſſe Jeſus the Lord to the glory of God, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4.6. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 45.23. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.10.11. But now, in this day of grace, from the appearance and force of his lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kindneſſe, in beliefe of his goodneſſe to ſubmit to, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Lordſhip, and grace of Chriſt; is the motion, and ſtring of this faith, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 3.5.</p>
               <p n="2">2 An inward, and hearty acceptance, and receiving of Chriſt, and this grace of God in Chriſt, for Pardon, Peace, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and life, ſo <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.12. As many as received him, &amp;c. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6. Received Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, <hi>Act.</hi> 26.18. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive forgiveneſſe of ſinnes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. We have Peace, &amp;c. verſe 11. We have received the Attonement, verſe 17. Receive the Abundance of grace, and of the gift of righteouſneſſe, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.12 He that hath the Sonne, hath life. And this accepting, and receiving; is another motion in this faith.</p>
               <p n="3">3 An approach, acceſſe, in coming, or nigh-drawing to Chriſt, and this grace in him, and for farther oneneſſe, and enjoyment thereof, he alſo herein building farther upon himſelfe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2. By whom alſo we have acceſſe by faith into this grace, &amp;c. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.18. Through him we have both acceſſe by one ſpirit unto the Father, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2, 3, 4. Ye have taſted that the Lord is gratious, to whom coming, as unto a living ſtone, &amp;c. And this approaching is another motion in this faith.</p>
               <p n="4">4 A hearty content, and well-pleaſedneſſe takeing in, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:113873:44"/>with Chriſt, and this grace in him, which is a feeding thereon, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3. And rejoyce in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.4. Chriſt who is our life, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.5.6. I have a goodly heritage, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.56, 57, 58.68 69. He that eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood, dwelleth in me, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And thus doth this faith move, in a ſubmiſſion to, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of Chriſt, receite of the grace in him, approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God through him, and well-pleaſedneſſe, takeing in him our Portion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.5.9. Such the moveings in, and of this faith.</p>
               <p n="5">5 For the ſubject in which this faith is, the Inſtrument with which it moveth, and worketh, in and to all this, beholding, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting, believing, truſting, acknowledgement, receite, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching, &amp; content-taking; It is the heart, the principall, the choyce, and inmoſt ſtrength of the minde, will, and affection, even the ſpirit of all, which is uſually called the heart in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.9.10. And ſhalt believe in thine heart; for with the heart man believeth unto righteouſneſſe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. That Chriſt may dwell in your hearts by faith, ſo that this faith is not in, or with the minde, or conception onely, or with a light af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; but in, and with the whole heart, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.37. And ſo it is with.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The minde, and underſtanding highly prizing Chriſt, and this rich grace in him, as the moſt excellent, pretious, and choice Pearle, and Riches. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.7.8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.3.10.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The will reſolutely chuſing, receiving, and accepting Chriſt, and this grace in him, as that which is moſt pleaſing, and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.24.25. and 119.30.37.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The affections cloſing therewith, as that which is moſt deſirable, and ſatisfying, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.5, 6, 7. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1, 2, 3, and 2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
               <p n="4">4 A ſpringing, and reviving apprehenſion of truth, and goodneſſe of that believing, however fainting before, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.10.12. As old <hi>Iacob,</hi> though before fainting at the newes, yet when he believed the report of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> being alive, <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.27.28. His ſpirit revived &amp; he ſaid, it is enough, my ſon <hi>Ioſeph</hi> is yet alive, &amp;c. And as <hi>Mary, Luke</hi> 1.46.47. My ſoule doth mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:113873:45"/>the Lord, and my ſpirit rejoyceth in God my Saviour, and as <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 103.1.2, 3. Thus is this faith in the heart, and with the heart man believeth (not only righteouſneſſe, but) unto righteouſneſſe, and ſo with the heart, moveth, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="6">6. For the ſtrength, power, and principle, in, and of this faith; It is the divine power, and ſpirit of Chriſt, entring with his motion, or infuſion, effecting: and ſpirituall ſeed, or diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fition in the heart, in which, the divine power, and ſpirit of Chriſt, that wrought this faith, operateth in and with this faith, which faith is therefore rightly called, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12. The faith of the operation of God, who hath raiſed Chriſt from the Dead: and the working of his mighty power which he wrought in Chriſt, when he raiſed him from the dead; is affirmed to worke in thoſe that by it, believe: <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.19.20. And by reaſon of this ſpirituall diſpoſition effected in the heart of the Believer; it is called, The ſpirit of faith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. And by this ſpirit of faith it is that the believer in believing is ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled,</p>
               <p n="1">1 To behold, and diſcerne the object of faith, Chriſt in his fulneſſe and beauty, and the rich grace of God in him, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.14.16.18. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 29. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.1.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Moved and overcome in the appearance of this grace to believe. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3, 4, 5.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Enabled to aſſent to, and receive the Teſtimony, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.5. And to believe, and accept the grace it ſelfe, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13.14. And to depend on God for all the hope to come. <hi>Rom.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.5.10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.5.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Prevailed with in the motions to the ſubmiſſion to, and acknowledgement of Chriſt 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3. To receiving him, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.12.13. To approaching to God in, and by him, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.18. and to Content-taking in him, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10.11.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Hath the new minde, ſpirit, and heart effected, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.27. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.20. And the minde and law of Chriſt written therein, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3.18.</p>
               <p n="6">6 The ſprings, fruits, and operations of love, joy, peace, &amp;c. Riſe up, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22.23. Diffuſing the vertue, and operation, in all the powers and faculties of he man, <hi>Mat</hi> 13.33. Purifying the heart unto unfained love of the Brethren, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2, 22. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:113873:45"/>up motions, and ſo ſpringing forth in prayer, praiſe, confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, works of mercy, &amp;c. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13.</p>
               <p>And all notions about the Doctrine of faith, and Profeſſion of faith where this ſpirit of faith is wanting, is but dead faith, <hi>Iames</hi> 2.17.26. And all workes wrought by humane force, not produced by this ſpirit of faith, are but dead workes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1.2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. but this ſpirit of faith is the life of faith, and that which makes faith lively, in all that is ſaid of it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2.4.14.</p>
               <p n="7">7 For the one-neſſe of this faith, in the diverſity of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and Acts of it; the Scripture ſheweth,</p>
               <p n="1">That there are divers degrees of this true, and Divine faith: the firſt Degree is little and ſmall, in compariſon, as a graine of Muſtard-ſeede, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.31. <hi>Luke</hi> 17.6. And called little, or weake in faith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.30. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.1. The ſecond De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree is ſtable, ſtedfaſt, or ſtrong faith, abiding in Chriſt, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring temptations, and tryalls, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.23. and 2.5.1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.7.8. The third degree, is effectuall, and victorious, working faith, and overcoming, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.3. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.4. Though there are diverſity of meaſures, or Degrees, and Growth therein, in each Degree, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.3. And in reſpect of the diverſity of Degrees in faith; ſome are called Babes; ſome, ſtrong men; and ſome; Fathers, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.12.13.14.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That the Acts, or Actings of this faith be divers, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold, as to ſay a areceiving Act, a ſpringing Act, and a flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſtreaming Act: as in the Scripture, and experience; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers find.</p>
               <p>Firſt, a receiving Act, this faith wrought by the ſpirit of grace in the heart receiveth the hiſtory, or record, and Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of God in the Goſpel concerning Chriſt, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.9.10.11. The grace of God in Chriſt teſtified, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.5. and 5.17. As remiſſion of ſinnes, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.43. Juſtification, Peace, Sanctification, Liberty of acceſſe to God, and hope of glory, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1.2.3. <hi>Act.</hi> 26.18. Divine power, and ſtrength of relyance on God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5.10.11. And yeelding up according to the leadings of grace, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1-4. Whence alſo ſuch exhortations to believers, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1.2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.1.2.12.13. and that 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.4. and 5.4.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:113873:46"/>
               <p>Secondly, a ſpringing Act, for from this faith wrought by the ſpirit in the heart; ſpringeth up love of God, and Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, and joy in God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.11. And love of brethren, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.23. and 4.21. and 5.1. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. and patience, and meekneſſe, &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. According to that is ſaid, <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.38.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, a flowing, or ſtreaming Act, from the ſprings, the motions, flowing to put forth accordingly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10. And this more ordinarily, to pray, give thankes, declare his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhew mercy, &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. or more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, in ſome miraculous operations, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.20. <hi>Luke</hi> 17.6. <hi>Marke</hi> 16, 17, 18.</p>
               <p n="3">3 That notwithſtanding the divers Degrees in this faith, and the divers manner of Acting, and Acts of this faith; yet the faith it ſelfe is but one, and onely one, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.4. As there is but one body, even one true Church, or Sanctuary that is uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Chriſt, and ſhall be in, and with him for ever, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.9. And this Church one ſeed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.17. One Sonne, <hi>Hoſea.</hi> 11.1. One Chriſt, one body, though the members be many, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. And as there is but one head, husband, and Lord of this body, and Church with all its members, which is Jeſus Chriſt the Sonne of God, and our Saviour, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.22.23. and 4.15.16. and 5.30. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. And as there is but one Baptiſme, whereby we are baptized into this one Body, whereof Chriſt is the head, and that is by the ſpirit, and with the waſhing of water, and the word; And this is into the Death; and unto the reſurrection of Chriſt, and ſo for conformity in one, and therethrough conformity in the other, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3, 4, 5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.4.5. And as there is but one God &amp; Father, to whom we come, in coming to Chriſt, and he the Father of Chriſt, and of every of us, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.6. And as there is but one ſpirit, proceeding from the father, &amp; the ſon, effecting, &amp; breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one ſpirit, minde, diſpoſition, or heart, &amp; that the ſpirit mind, diſpoſition, and heart of Chriſt, into which all that are bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into Chriſt, are made to drinke, and ſo are one ſpirit, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.4 even ſo likewiſe, (as in the place fore-cited) there is but one faith.</p>
               <p>True it is; The word Faith, in Scripture, is uſed diverſly; ſomtime for the object of faith, even the ground, and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:113873:46"/>of faith, and that which is to be, and is beleeved, and beleeved in, and to that end to be preached and heard, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.5. &amp; 10.6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.23. &amp; 3.5. Sometimes the word is uſed for the grace of faith, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.4 &amp; 2.5-12. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8. Sometimes for both the object, and the grace united with the object together, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. &amp; 9.30. And yet however taken; there is but one faith. The object in every reſpect is one. The Goſpel, or word of grace, though it hath many branches and uſes, yet is but one and the ſame Goſpel. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.4. with <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.7.8.9. The Goſpel, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.5.23. Even ſo the Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſet forth in the Goſpel, though ſet forth, as he is indeed, the Sonne of God, and the Sonne of Man; yea, God Man, and declared in reſpect of what he was, and what he became for us, and what he hath done, and what he is for us, and with what he is furniſhed, and what he is to us. And as he is the Saviour of all men, eſpecially of them that beleeve, and the Judge of all, &amp;c. yet he is but one, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.4. with 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. the Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 4.42. Even ſo God the Father that is in Chriſt, is one God, (though his works be manifold) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.20. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. even ſo the holy Spirit that proceedeth from the Father and the Sonne, and diſcovereth Chriſt, and God in Chriſt, and beareth forth the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, however his gifts and operations be many and manifold; yet the Spirit is but one, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4 11. yea the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Spirit are, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. one God, <hi>Mark</hi> 12 32.34. ſet forth in one Goſpel. And ſo the object of faith is one; and ſo faith alſo, though ſo taken.</p>
               <p>The grace of faith, or the beleeving it ſelf that is wrought in the heart by the Spirit of grace, however there are diverſity of degrees in the ſame, both in the ſtrength of beleeving, and alſo in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the diſcovery of the object beleeved, &amp; in the effects ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, and alſo the Acts manifold, as is ſhewn: yet the faith it ſelfe is but one. And this is evident in the forenamed place, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.4. where both faith, and the object of faith, and the means, and the hope, and the people that receive it, are all mentioned diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; ſo that the word faith there meanes, the grace of faith, and it is expreſly affirmed to be one, <hi>There is one faith.</hi> As for humane and worldly faith, or a ſhew and pretence of divine faith, and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall profeſſion thereof, it is no faith at all in Scripture lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage: there is no vertue in gtting or retaining it, nor danger
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:113873:47"/>in departing therefrom in reſpect of any ſpirituall life. As for that beliefe of the report of the Goſpel, and profeſſion thereof, which is deſtitute of the life and operation of the Spirit of faith; it is no more faith then the body of a man is a man when the Ghoſt is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up and departed, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.26. So as there is no other true and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving faith, but one; the receiving the hiſtory, and record, the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving remiſſion of ſinnes, juſtification and ſanctification, and power for divine operations or miracles, the ſprings, the ſtreames, the acts, as is ſhewn, are all by one and the ſame faith. And ſo it is one and the ſame faith, that in diſcovery of the object is tendered, and to which called, and which by the divine teſtimony is effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and which in abiding is after confirmed, and which groweth and worketh by love: it is ſtill one and the ſame faith, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1. And this faith cloſing with, and the believer therein united, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one with the object of faith; it is ſtill one, and then ſtable and ſure to abide, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.2.3. And this is the faith, Scripture ſpeaks of.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, for the remembrance here ſpoken of, it is not that humane exerciſe of thoughts, in running over, and recording the words, ſtories, ſeverall doctrines, reaſons and uſes, &amp;c. that one hath heard, and read, thereby to habituate them in memory, that one may have them to think, and ſpeak of at all times, though there bee a good uſe of ſuch remembring, notwithſtanding ſome turn it to an evil, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.63. But the remembrauce here ſpoken of, is a beleeving remembrance, when in this faith, the death, reſurrection, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Chriſt, with the vertue of its preſentation to God, and of its application to us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.3.4. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.8. the love and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er there-through teſtified, and diſpenſed, the hope therein given, and that therethrough tendered to be wrought, is believingly</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the diſcoveries, teſtimonies and ſayings thereof noted, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and heeded diligently, as <hi>Jacob</hi> obſerved the ſaying, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.11. and <hi>Lydia</hi> on the opening of her heart attended to the things, &amp;c. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14. As <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, <hi>Set your hearts to all the words which I teſtifie, Deut.</hi> 32.46.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The grace, conſolations, hope, and inſtructions tendered in their diſcoveries, to accept and retain in the heart, with the choyce eſtimate, love, deſires, and ſubmiſſion, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.15. <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.20.21,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:113873:47"/>22. as <hi>Mary</hi> kept the ſaying in her heart, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.51. and <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 119.11.16.24.72.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The motions and teachings of this grace, yeeld up to, and vent forth <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1.2, <hi>Phil,</hi> 2.1.2.12.13. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11.12. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24. as <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 16.7.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The taking all occaſions, and being minded by all occaſions for the revived remembrance of theſe things in and of Chriſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.8. By the creatures of God, the heaven, the earth, and the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, which (being by ſin diſſolved) are through the Sacrifice, mediation and power of Chriſt, upheld, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.3. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.17. and ſo ſhewing forth his glory, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.1-6.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By the particular mercies of God extended as a fruit of the Sacrifice of Chriſt, and that life that is in him, <hi>John</hi> 1.4.5. carrying forth ſome teſtimony of his goodneſſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.17. and leading to repentance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. Theſe give apt occaſions to remember theſe things.</p>
               <p n="3">3 By the chaſtiſements God layeth on men, eſpecially, the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of Believers for the Goſpel, apt to mind us of him that bare all our ſorrowes, <hi>Iſa</hi> 53.4. And hath ſanctified ſufferings for us, to whom we are to be conformed, and who is ready and able to do us good by them, and to deliver, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4, 5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2-7.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The Word of God minding us of theſe things. In <hi>Moſes</hi> writing, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.45. In the Shadowes and Sacrifices of the Law, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. and 10. In the Prophecies, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.24. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.2, 3. In the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Invitations, and Promiſes, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.1-6. with <hi>Act.</hi> 13.34. In the full and plain Narration, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.3, 4.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The Ordinances of God mind us of theſe things, as Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4. and 15.1-4. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.14. Writing, <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.31. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.1-5. Confirming, <hi>Jud.</hi> 20.21. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.18. and 5.10.11. Prayer, &amp;c. The Dore for which is opened by Chriſts ſacrifice, and mediation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.19, 20, 22. and 4.15, 16.</p>
               <p n="6">6 The grace of God with the fruits thereof, given by the Spirit of Chriſt into the believing heart, aptly mindes of theſe things, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1.5-11.</p>
               <p n="7">7 The beholding believers through grace brought out of the ſtate and fellowſhip of the world, into union and fellowſhip with Chriſt, and one another in him, mindes us, not only of the bloud of Chriſts ſhed, and his ranſome given for all men, by which he hath
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:113873:48"/>bought all of God; but of the vertue of his bloud alſo by his Spirit diſcovered, and applyed, and they there through redeemed, and purchaſed from among men unto God, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Yea, even the beholding men, as men, though in their naturall condition, doth aptly mind of theſe things, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14.15 — 20.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Yea, even the follies, diſobedience, &amp;c. of ſuch men, are fit oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions to put theſe things to remembrance, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Yea, even our own ſins, being that for which he was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, <hi>Iſa</hi> 53.6. and the combates within, all freedome being given in, and through him, doe give occaſion of remembrance of theſe things, as is ſeen, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24, 25. and 8.1, 2, 3, 4. and ſo wee might proceed.</p>
               <p>So that in the believing the truth, and goodneſſe of the things of Chriſt ſet forth in the Goſpel, with ſuch a love retaining them in the heart, as by all occaſions to be ſtirred up to this receiving, attending, accepting, and yeelding up thereto, is the remembrance here meant. And to have the word of Chriſt dwell plenteouſly in us, teaching, &amp;c. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. The way to this remembrance is, in the acknowledgment of our own weakneſſe, and the vanity of all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane helps, through the beliefe of his love towards us, and what he hath done for us when we were enemies, and his more ſpeciall love, in making his grace known to us, to depend on him for his ſpirit, to mind us of him, and his words, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.6-11. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.5. for which he hath given us his promiſe, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.26. and 16.7. — 15.</p>
               <p>And this remembrance in the believing heart is profitable.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 To preſerve, and ſave from falling, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.2, 3, 4.</item>
                  <item>2 To return, and raiſe out of falls, and decayes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.3.</item>
                  <item>3 To meet with comforts, teachings, &amp;c. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 63.5, 6, 7.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And thus of the faith, and remembrance here meant.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:113873:48"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the uſefulneſſe here meant, what, and how manifold it is.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE uſefulneſſe of the pretious bloud, and ſacrifice of Chriſt believingly remembred; ſo as there-through God is depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on; Is in, and to the believer two-fold. 1 In reſpect of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. 2 In reſpect of others: and both wayes manifold.</p>
               <p>Firſt, In reſpect of the Believer himſelf, it is four-fold:</p>
               <p n="1">1 Receiving. 2 Springing up. 3 Streaming forth. And 4 waiting.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The firſt uſe is receiving: and ſo believing, and receiving, are uſed one for another, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.12. And the receit in believing view, and remembrance is manifold, as is fore-ſhewn, namely, 1 Of the Word of Chriſt, the Record and Teſtimony God gave of him, 1 Cor: 15.1.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In receit of his teſtimony, is received the mind of Chriſt, ſo far as to receive information, light, and diſcerning in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of
<list>
                     <item>1 That which Chriſt hath done in his death, reſurrection, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion, and ſacrifice offered to God, what for all men, and what for all that by the heavenly call believe on him, as is ſhewne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</item>
                     <item>2 That which (by vertue of this which he hath done) he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and that in generall for all men, as that he is the propitiation for their ſins, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.2. And the Mediator between God and them, procuring for them patience, mercies, and ſome meanes for their Call, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. And that in ſpeciall for thoſe that in the heavenly call are prevailed with to believe on him, as that beſides both the fore-mentioned for all men, hee is in ſpeciall manner for them an Advocate, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.1. Yea, even the Mediator of the New Teſtament, that hy his ſpirituall application of the vertue of his ſacrifice, they may receive the promiſed inheritance, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.25, 26. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14, 15. Yea, he is their King, and Teacher, and the high Prieſt of their Profeſſion, and to them wiſdome, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſanctification, and redemption, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. and 7. and 8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1, 30.</item>
                     <item>3 That which by vertue of the ſormer he now doth, and will
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:113873:49"/>do, and that both in generall for all men, as the extenſion of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured patience, mercies, and means, to bring them to the knowledg of the truth, <hi>Prov,</hi> 1.23. and 8.4 &amp;c. &amp; <hi>Pſalm:</hi> 75.3. <hi>Act:</hi> 14 17. And ſuch as refuſe light when it cometh, he will one day bring them to acknowledgment of the truth, and then judge them, <hi>Jſa:</hi> 45:23. <hi>Phil:</hi> 2.10.11. <hi>Rom:</hi> 2.16 And alſo in ſpecial for thoſe that through the acknowledgment of truth in the day of grace believe on him, how he preſents them in himſelf ſpotleſſe before God, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.22. interceding for them, <hi>Heb:</hi> 7:25. and will ſend forth his Spirit to teach, comfort, and ſanctifie, uphold, lead, and preſerve them to the Inheritance, &amp;c. <hi>John</hi> 14.1, 2, 3, 26. and 15:25 and 16.13, 14, 15. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4, 5. <hi>Pſalm:</hi> 138:8.</item>
                     <item>4 The great and rich love of God through all this diſcovered, <hi>Epheſ:</hi> 2.4, 5. His generall love of compaſſion to all men, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3:16.17. <hi>Tit:</hi> 2, 11, 12. and 3.4. and his peculiar and ſpeciall love of delight to thoſe in the heavenly Call united to Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ:</hi> 5:25, 26. <hi>Pſalm:</hi> 149.1.</item>
                     <item>5. The great terrour, and heavy inexcuſable condemnation for all that when light comes, ſet light by, and will none of Chriſt to raign over them, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2:2: and 10:29. <hi>Luk</hi> 19:27. 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.10:11.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>And in this enlightning they receive a right judgment concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God, and Chriſt, and Man, and ſinne, and righteoeſneſſe, life, and death, &amp;c, <hi>Phil:</hi> 3.3 — 9. and ſo its ſaid, we have the mind of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 2, 16.</p>
               <p n="3">3 In receiving this divine teſtimony and information, is received alſo an encouragement of the grace it ſelf teſtified in Chriſt, <hi>Rom:</hi> 1.5. as remiſſion of ſins, &amp;c. as fore-ſhewn, and the ſpirit of adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with divine power, &amp;c. <hi>Gal:</hi> 3.2. <hi>Rom:</hi> 8:15. as before.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The ſecond uſe is for ſpringing up, as in believing-minding theſe things are received; ſo from this received in the ſame belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving-mindfulneſſe of Chriſt, ſpringeth up
<list>
                     <item>1 A high eſtimate of Chriſt, and the things of Chriſt, and deſire of him, with a low eſtimate of ones ſelf, and all ones owne things, <hi>Phil:</hi> 3.7, 8, 9.</item>
                     <item>2 An inward ſorrow for all ones evill thoughts of God and Chriſt, and ſins, againſt ſo gracious and loving a God, and Saviour, <hi>Act:</hi> 2.37. <hi>Zach:</hi> 12:10.</item>
                     <item>3 A fervent love of God, and Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, with peace
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:113873:49"/>towards God, and joy in God. 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1:7, 8. <hi>Rom:</hi> 5.2, 5, 11.</item>
                     <item>4 Love of brethren, and compaſſion towards men, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.23. &amp; 4:21. and 5.1. 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.14.</item>
                     <item>5 Deſires of Gods glory, the Churches proſperity, and Mens converſion, and the coming again of Chriſt.</item>
                     <item>6 Deteſtation of evill, with love of God, and ſo patience, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c. <hi>Gal:</hi> 5-17, 22, 23.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>And theſe, and ſuch like ſpring up in believing-remembrance of the ſacrifice, and mediation of Chriſt, according to that, <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.38.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The third uſe is for ſtreaming forth; for as in believing-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the ſacrifice, and mediation of Chriſt there, are ſuch receivings, and ſuch ſprings, as fore-ſhewn; ſo in the ſame belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving-remembrance, the ſprings ariſing from the receites doe move, and ſtream to flow, and vent forth, and is called a ſhewing forth the vertues of him that called, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 2, 9. bringing forth good things, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.35. A working cut the ſalvation that is a mans own in and with him, <hi>Phil:</hi> 2:12, 13. which is from the force of the ſpirit, grace, and love of Chriſt received, ſpringing up in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, fruits of zeale, charity, &amp;c. fore-mentioned, ſtreaming, and boyling to flow forth in motions and bowels, ſtirring thereto. And this, according to the channels opened, and occaſions given, <hi>Iob.</hi> 32, 8, 18, 19, 20. 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5, 14, 15, 19, 20. And grace received, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1, 2, 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.20.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 To deny ungodlineſſe, and worldly luſts, <hi>Tit:</hi> 2.11, 12. <hi>Gal:</hi> 2.16, 17, 21.</item>
                  <item>2 To oppoſe falſe doctrines, and wayes, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.11.14.</item>
                  <item>3 To attend the Ordinances of God, and ſeek his face therein. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 27.4. and 23.6. To pray to him, and give him thanks, <hi>Pſal,</hi> 116.2, 10, 13. Recount his favours, and ſing his praiſes, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 145.1. — 11.</item>
                  <item>4 To confeſſe Chriſt Jeſus the Lord and Saviour, in holding forth the word of life, exalting Chriſt, and yeelding themſelves ſervants for Chriſt his ſake, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10.2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4, 5, 13. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12.16.</item>
                  <item>5 To uſe equity and mercy, to give to every one his due for the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:113873:50"/>Lords ſake, and to doe good to all, eſpecially them of the houſhold of faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.10. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1-4.8. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.8.9 10. whence for all theſe, the exhortations to beleevers, run in ſuch a ſtrain ſuitable to the law of grace. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1.2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.1.2.</item>
                  <item>6. To confeſſe it their finne, wherein ſoever they have ſhut up theſe bowels (undervalued the grace beleeved, deaded the ſprings, or ſtopt the ſtreames, either by forgerfulneſſe, or neglect of yeelding to its motions, or turning aſide to any other motions) and ſeeking pardon and healing of the ſame in returning to Chriſt, &amp;c. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.17. &amp; 1.9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.75. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.15.</item>
                  <item>7. In ſome, at ſome time, to ſome miraculous operations in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of that which is ordinary. <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.20. <hi>Luk</hi> 17.6. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.17.18. And theſe and ſuch like are the flowings forth of the ſprings from the grace received in the beleeving-Remembrance of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Blood, Sacrifice, and mediation of Chriſt.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth uſe is, for Patience, for as in believing-Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the vertuous Blood, Sacrifice, and mediation of Chriſt, and Gods rich love therein, ſuch grace is received, ſuch fruits doe ſpring, and ſuch ſtreames flow forth: ſo alſo (it being ſome time after believing, and walking in faith, before all that is ſet in hope be received, and in that time, many thoughts, trials, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations to be gone through, ſo that there is need of Patience, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.36. 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1, 6, 7.) In this believing remembrance of the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and mediation of Chriſt, patience is ſtirred up, and effected in exerciſe, and preſerved, ſo as from that beheld in, &amp; received from Chriſt, ariſeth a ſweet confident expectation, and patient abiding, and waiting through all Tryals, Sufferings, and ſervices for his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of all his righteous Promiſes in his own ſeaſon, and ſo for his preſerving us to the inheritance, and for his owne viſible coming again, and receiving us to himſelf, that we may be with him, and raign with him for ever, <hi>John</hi> 14:1, 2, 3. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16, 17, 18. and 5.1 — 6. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2 11, 13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.26.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for the Believer in reſpect of others, this believing-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the vertuous Sacrifice, and mediation of Chriſt, is very uſefull, and profitable, and that in three reſpects:
<list>
                     <item>1 In reſpect of a right view, and eſtimate of them.</item>
                     <item>2 In reſpect of a right demeanour in word, and converſation to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them.</item>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:113873:50"/>
                     <item>3. In reſpect of a right confidence concerning them.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. In reſpect of a right view and eſtimate of them; the beleeving-remembrance of the death, ſacrifice, and mediation of Chriſt, leads and moves the judgement and mind of the believer.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To eſteem all that are onely naturall men, as thoſe for whom Chriſt hath died, and given himſelfe a ranſome, and bought them, and is the propitiation for their ſinnes, and mediator between God and them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2 5.6. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.2. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 21, 2. And in this reſpect to be loved, pitied, prayed for, and to have the Goſpel declared to them, and to be ſerved for their good, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11.14, 15, 20. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. to ch. 2.1.—6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.14, 15.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.18.—23. &amp; 10.33. And ſo to afford them all that honor and reſpect of the place, the diſpoſing hand of ſuch a redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer hath put them in, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.16-19. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To eſteem all that are not onely ſo ranſomed, but by the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious providence of our redeemer, put in our charge and tuition, as the price of his blood graciouſly given, and committed to us by our Lord, to be brought up for him, and nurtured in the knowledge and feare of him, the Lord of us both, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. &amp; 33.5. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.4.9. <hi>Job.</hi> 13.14.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To eſteem all that are through grace brought in to beleeve in Chriſt, as the Sons and Daughters of God, Brethren and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, and of us the Houſe of God, whoſe we are, and to whom we belong, fit objects for ſpeciall love and fellowſhip, ſo as Chriſt may be loved and ſerved in them; and they with ſpecial love and ſervice for Chriſt his ſake, <hi>John</hi> 1.12, 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.26. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.19, 20. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.30. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12, 13. &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To eſteeme all of theſe called ones (that are not onely redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of God by blood-ſhedding, but unto God by his precious Blood ſpiritually applied, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9: 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18.19.) as we have been in any ſort inſtruments by whom God hath called them, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13.17. or, are by his grace and providence, both led to ſome ſpeciall charge and overſight of them, 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 5.1.2. ſo as to thoſe we are more peculiarly related for more abundant care and ſervice for them, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28.</p>
               <p n="5">5. To eſteem thoſe who after light, and knowledge of the truth, have reſiſted it, and departed from it, turning the grace of God into laſciviouſneſſe, and oppoſing the power of godlineſſe, perſiſting
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:113873:51"/>herein, till given up of God, as ungodly, reprobate, and the feed of the Serpent to be contended with, turned from, and ceaſed praying for, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.6.16-30. <hi>Iude</hi> 4.—19. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.16.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in reſpect of a right demeanour, in word and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For words; it will mind us of right and true Goſpel, and right words, which we need not cloak, curtaile, or equivocate in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery, nor be aſhamed of; but ſpeak with boldneſſe and plainneſſe, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.5, 6, 7. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18, &amp; 4.1. 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.12. having that in them which is true, and meet to be ſpoken to every man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.18.—21. to reprove and confute all falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, wayes, and hopes, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4, 5, 6. to inſtruct in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and way of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16.17. to preſſe to convincement, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.15. to comfort the convinced, &amp; to allure to good thoughts of God in Chriſt, &amp; ſo to beleeve, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15.16.17. to encourage to abiding in the faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.1-6. to exhort and provoke to love and good works, Tit. 3.8. to ſet forth the peculiar priviledges of ſuch as in beleeving are made one in Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2, 15, 26, 33. &amp; to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them to conſtancy in their holy profeſſion, and fellowſhip, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.1.19-25. And ſo to ſeaſon all our words with grace, that they may ſavour of, and adminiſter grace to others, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.20, 30. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.6. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.16.</p>
               <p n="2">2 For converſation; it will mind to bee putting on bowels of mercy, kindneſſe, humbleneſſe of mind, meekneſſe, long-ſuffering, forbearing and forgiving, &amp;c. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12. to bleſſe them that curſe us, &amp;c. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.44.45. to walk in wiſdome, and blameleſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them that are without, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15. And faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fruitfully among the brethren, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.1:10. and ſo to pray for good for all, 1 Tim. 2.3, 4. and peculiar good for beleevers, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.8.9, 10.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For confidence; it will mind of that which will make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident in him, to vouchſafe his preſence by Spirit, ſo farr as to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt the ſavour of his knowledge to others by us, for allurement, or convincement, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.17. and ſo confirm his words ſpoke by us, that even the rejectors ſhall one day confeſſe the truth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and be iudged thereby, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 44.25.26. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2, 10, 11. <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.48. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16. and ſuch as receive them, ſhall have a proofe of his owne gracious preſence, and ſpeaking there through, <hi>Matth.</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:113873:51"/>10.40 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 13.3. ſo as wee ſhall bee fruitfull, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8.9.</p>
               <p>And to conclude, the beleeving remembrance of the Death, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, Ranſome, and Mediation of Chriſt, is uſefull for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of all mercies, chaſtiſements, uſe of ordinances, and creatures, with purity, comfort, and profit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.14. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.4.5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15.</p>
               <p>And thus in viewing what the Goſpel ſaith of the precious Blood, Death, and Sacrifice of Chriſt; in the ſenſe of the words, the ends, the neceſſity, the excellency and dignity, the vertue, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, and prevalency, with the afefulneſſe of the knowledge, and beleeving remembrance thereof; we may ſee that there was ſo great and good cauſe for the ſame to bee made knowne, believed, and remembred, and ſuch a fulneſſe in it, that we need not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at it, That the Apoſtles ſhould determine to know nothing elſe in their miniſtration, as 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 2.2. ſave Jeſus Chriſt and him crucified; and that they would glory in nothing elſe, (<hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14.) ſave the Croſſe of Chriſt; and that they ſhould bee ſo dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to put believers in remembrance of theſe things. And our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour appointed the Word preached, Baptiſme, and the Supper of the Lord, for the remembrance of theſe things: ſeeing theſe things rightly underſtood, containe all things necefull to eternall life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 15.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Obſervations from this whole Diſcourſe in all the fourteen Chapters, and now for a litte further enlarging the uſefulneſſe; note theſe confirmations.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THat the doctrine of the Goſpel ſetting forth Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 1. Act. 10.36. 1 Tim. 2.4.5.6 1 Ioh. 5.10.11 12. 1 Cor. 1.30. Pſa. 68.18 Ioh. 16.7-15 Mat 28.18. Prov. 8. Heb. 5 9. Rom. 14.2.12.</note> as now he hath come in the fleſh, and died for our ſinnes, and is riſen for our juſtification, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. and having offered up his own ſelfe a Sacrifice to God for us, is received and exalted at Gods right hand, having obtained eternall redemption, and ſo is become the Lord of all: the propitation for the ſins of the world: the Mediator between God and Men: Wiſdome, Righteouſneſſe, Sanctification and Redemption, and life in him, for all. And hee all
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:113873:52"/>this for, and to all that by the heavenly call beleeve on him, and for them the Mediator of the new Teſtament, that they may receive the promiſes, being immeaſurably filled with the holy Spirit to ſend forth to men, even the rebellious, that the Lord God might dwell among them, and to ſuch as are brought in to him, to lead them into all truth, having all power and authority to call all the ſonnes of men, that they might look, and live to him; to abſolve, and bring to eternall life, all that obey his call, and to judge and condemne all that perſiſt refuſing, and will none of him.</p>
               <p>This Doctrine, as it is now declared in the Goſpel, it is the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary doctrine to be taught, known, beleeved, and walked in, and it is a full ſufficient and compleat Doctrine, or Law, and needeth no other doctrine to be added to it, either to goe before, or follow after, or be joyned with it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.1-4. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.7, 8, 9.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Either to convince the world of ſinne, or righteouſneſſe, or judgement, and to empty a man of himſelfe, <hi>John</hi> 16.7, 11. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3-8.</item>
                  <item>2. Or to call to Chriſt, and ſo to repentance and faith, and there through to receit of remiſſion of ſinnes, renewing, and life in Chriſt, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.14.</item>
                  <item>3. Or to encourage beleevers to abide in the faith, <hi>John</hi> 15.1-10. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.5-23.</item>
                  <item>4. Or to direct and lead Beleevers to ſanctification and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity with Chriſt in heart and life, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3.18. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.10.11.12.14.</item>
                  <item>5. Or, for Beleevers exerciſe, to preſerve, and edifie themſelves, and one another in the faith and love of God in Chriſt, and in the love of one another, through all ſufferings and ſervices of love, till they come to the Inheritance, <hi>John</hi> 15.4 7, 8. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.24, 25. <hi>Jude</hi> 20.</item>
                  <item>6. Or to oppoſe all ſins, and adverſaries, and all falſe Doctrines, wayes, and hopes withall, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 6.4, 7. and 10.4.5, 6. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.17.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Yea, this Doctrine of the Goſpell, as it now ſets forth Chriſt, and life in him; is a compleat, full, and ſufficient Doctrine for all this, without addition: And for better underſtanding the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of the Goſpell; this is to be heeded, That the life in Chriſt, the Redemption compleated in his own body for men, &amp; the redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:113873:52"/>in the Declaration thereof tendered to be wrought in men, &amp; by his Spirit in application of that in himſelf, wrought in ſuch as believe on him; ever from the beginning was, now is, and ever will bee, one, and the ſame, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.4, 5, 9, 12. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.1, 2, 3. <hi>Heb:</hi> 13.8. But the fulneſſe and cleerneſſe of the Doctrinall Declaration, and Diſpenſation, as well as of the ſpirituall commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of Chriſt, and the life in him, hath had its diverſity of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees.</p>
               <p n="1">1 There was ſome diſcovery of this life, even of the redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wrought by Chriſt in himſelf for men, and the power in him to make it known, and tender it to men, and give it into believing men, even at firſt; And that then declared, was Goſpell, even the ſame, though not ſo full, and cleere, as the word of the beginning of Chriſt now, as appears by comparing <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. with <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.4. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.1-3. and 3.5-8.</p>
               <p n="2">2 After ſome time, God was pleaſed to give a more full diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of Chriſt, and this life in him, in opening to and making with <hi>Abraham,</hi> an everlaſting Covenant, to aſſure all the ſpirituall Seed of this life in Chriſt, and the priviledges thereof, by a ſure and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alterable Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. which was not another; but the ſame Goſpell more full come forth, and the ſame that now is, though now more open, and cleer, <hi>Gal</hi> 3.8, 16, 28, 29.</p>
               <p>Yet till Chriſt was actually come; God ſaw it needfull to adde ſtil ſomething, for the nurture, and guidance of his people, that they might eſtimate, ſeek, and lay hold of Chriſt, and this life in him: which ſtill they were apt to ſleight and neglect, and ready either to extenuate their evils, or to magnifie ſome wiſdome and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their own: wherefore God gave them a Teſtament or Law by <hi>Moſes</hi> his ſervant, one part whereof pointing out the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe due from man to God, thereby to diſcover their ſinfulneſſe, and make them ſay Amen to the Curſe; And the other part, to type and ſhadow out Chriſt, that they might, in obſervation therof, look and wait for all grace through him that was co come: And this Law or Teſtament was not the everlaſting Covenant, It was not the Goſpell preached to <hi>Abraham,</hi> but a Law added, becauſe of tranſgreſſion till the Seed ſhould come: and ſo long was the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and preſſing of this Law needfull, and uſefull, as ſubſervient to the Goſpell, &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.19. to drive to Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:113873:53"/>
               <p n="3">3 But when the fulneſſe of time was come, God ſent forth his Son made of a woman, &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.1, 4. And hee being come in the fleſh, and having ſuffered, and being in our nature exalted at the right hand of God; he hath given a new Teſtament, which is a firſt fruits of the everlaſting Covenant, and the bleſſing of the Goſpell, for the nurture of his people: and ſo the old Teſtament decayed, and paſſed, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.13. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.24, 25.</p>
               <p>And thus, though it was the ſame grace and life in Chriſt; yet in reſpect of this full and cleer diſpenſation that is now by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, it was hid in God, and not ſo made known, as now ſince Chriſt came, it was to his holy Apoſtles and Prophets by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and by them in the Goſpel, in which the ſame Spirit ſtill teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.2-9. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.26. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.2, 3, 4. And ſo of the Goſpel as now declared, is the Affirmation in the Obſervation to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood; namely, That the Doctrine of the Goſpel is the onely neceſſary, and full ſufficient, and compleat Doctrine to be taught, known, believed, and walked in, &amp;c. And this doth yet further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, in that
<list>
                     <item>1 This Goſpell is that Doctrine which God gave Jeſus Chriſt to preach, and ſent him, and filled him with Spirit to preach, and he preached it, <hi>Iohn</hi> 12 49, 50 and 17.8, 18. with <hi>Iſa</hi> 4.2.1. and 61.1, 2. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18. <hi>Mark</hi> 1.14.</item>
                     <item>2 This Goſpel is that Doctrine which Jeſus Chriſt hath given to his ſervants to preach, and ſent them into the world, and endued them with ſpirit to preach, and given them in charge to preach it, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.8, 18. and 15.26, 27. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.1, 2, 3, 7. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.18, 19.</item>
                     <item>3 This Goſpell is that Doctrine which the Apoſtles confeſſed to have received of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.11, 12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5 19. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.5. To be ſent to preach, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17. And for the preaching whereof, a neceſſity was laid upon them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16.</item>
                     <item>4. This Goſpel is that Doctrine which the Apoſtles did preach to all men, every where, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.6. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. &amp; 3. &amp; 4 &amp; 5. &amp; 10. &amp; 13. &amp;c. and profeſſed themſelves to have preached, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.1-5. and to determine to know no other doctrine, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.1.—4. and have denounced the curſe on all that ſhall preach any other doctrine, <hi>Gal,</hi> 1.8.9.</item>
                     <item>5. Yea, the fulneſſe, ſufficiency, and compleatneſſe of this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpel, doth yet further appeare many wayes,</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:113873:53"/>
               <list>
                  <item>1. In the Name of it, the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> that is, a joyfull meſſage of good newes, or glad tidings from heaven, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 52.7. with <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15. It is good newes indeed, in that it is truth (<hi>Prov.</hi> 8.4.8.) from God; of peace and good will to men: <hi>Nahum</hi> 1.15. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.10. for mankind; of ſalvation, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4.5, 6. which is in Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 46.9. and ſhall be given to all that in beleeving come in to him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.10, 11, 12.</item>
                  <item>2. In the Titles of it, which are all full of truth, the Goſpel of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.16. the Goſpel of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. the Goſpel of the grace of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.24. the Goſpel of Salvation, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13. the Goſpel of the Kingdome, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.23. the glorious Goſpel, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. the everlaſting Goſpel, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6. the Goſpel of peace, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.15. the word of reconciliation, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. of life, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>3. In the ſum of it, both in the narration and affirmation, ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing the Sonne of God to be come, and what he became, ſuffered, and did for us, and what hee is, and doth, and what hee will do in, and for all that beleeve in him, as this whole Treatiſe hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</item>
                  <item>4 In the holy Spirit that is promiſed to be ſent forth in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of this Goſpel, by which Chriſt will continue his owne preſence with his ſervants miniſtring the ſame, <hi>John</hi> 14.16, 17. &amp; 15.26, 27. &amp; 16.7.—15. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19, 20.</item>
                  <item>5 The effects of the Spirit in the Goſpel, forementioned, both witneſſed to be effected thereby, and examples of its efficacies ſet forth therein, as <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.4. And to conclude all in one word.</item>
               </list>
               <p>In reſpect of the Medium or Doctrine; the Goſpel is the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to be built on, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10.11. the way to walk in, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6. 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. and the Schoolmaſter to guide, and lead in the way, Tit. 2.11, 12, &amp;c. and how full, and prevalent; this whole treatiſe hath ſhewn in particular.</p>
               <p>And as God hath given us foundation; ſo likewiſe one way, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.39. and as Jeſus Chriſt is the foundation, the way, the truth, &amp; the life, and the Prophet and Leader, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. <hi>John</hi> 14.6. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.22,—26. and his Spirit that by which hee diſcovereth, teſtifieth, draweth to, and buildeth on himſelfe, comforteth, ſanctifieth, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth and leadeth his children, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.26. &amp; 15.26. &amp; 16.13, 14, 15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2.14; even ſo the Doctrine of the Goſpel is the Medium
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:113873:54"/>or inſtrument through which, Chriſt by his doth all this, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. &amp; 4.4, 6. whence, all ſuch as abide in the Doctrine of Chriſt, are affirmed to have both the Father and the Son, 2 <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Objection.</label>
               </p>
               <p>But ſome are ready to object: this magnifying the Doctrine of the Goſpel, makes void the Law, and taketh away all uſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of;</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwer.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The truth is, It eſtabliſheth the Law, and leadeth to the right uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs therof, which is met with (not in law-teaching &amp; preſſing, but) in the right teaching the doctrine of the Goſpel: as may be ſeen, by comparing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.21.—31. with 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5.—11.</p>
               <p>For, by the Doctrine of the Goſpell ſetting forth Chriſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and believed; the holyneſſe, righteouſneſſe, goodneſſe, ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and perfection of the Law is known and ſeen, not aboliſhed: but ratified, and fulfilled in and by Jeſus Chriſt, the Son of God. In that, 1. He came, and fulfilled all the righteous affections, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices to the utmoſt, that it requireth. 2 He, as the publike man for us, ſuffered the curſe, it ſentenceth it too for all the ſins it can charge us with. 3 He roſe, juſtified, and preſented himſelf righteous before God in the behalf of us. 4 Hee received ſpirit to ſend forth in the Declaration hereof, that men might believe on him, and in belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving on him; have him for their righteouſneſſe before God, and be freed from being under the obligation of the Law: to be under the obligation of grace, to depend on him, and ſo receive ſpirit from him, to conform them to himſelf, &amp; ſo raiſe up from a better prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple. The righteous affections, and ſervices, law called for, and gave no ſtrength whereby they might be produced, and to give the life law promiſed, and could not give, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.10-27. and 8.2, 3, 4. <hi>Gal:</hi> 5.16, 18, 22, 23. and 6.8. as may be ſeen in that before ſaid, in the 6. and 14. Chapters.</p>
               <p>In receit of which grace in the doctrine of the Goſpell; as the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever is freed from the obligation of the Law: ſo hee enjoyeth the goodneſſe thereof, in the right ends and uſes of it, in that
<list>
                     <item>1 They own themſelves, as in, and of themſelves, the ſinners, and curſed ones for whom Chriſt was made ſinne, and a curſe, and ſo are dead to themſelves, their own ſtrength, wiſdome, and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24. and 2.19, <hi>Rom:</hi> 10.3, 4.</item>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:113873:54"/>
                     <item>2 They ſee the mercy of God in giving the law for ſuch ends, and freeing them from the obligation of it, <hi>Rom:</hi> 7.9-25. and 8.2.</item>
                     <item>3. They are in every thought of this Law, kept from turning to it again for life of juſtification, ſanctification, or glory: and ſo occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſtick cloſer ſtill to Chriſt for all, <hi>Rom:</hi> 7.9-25. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.7, 8.</item>
                     <item>4 They, in remembring any good that law bound them to; count themſelves much more obliged for the grace of Chriſt to doe it, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 8.8, 16. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.1-4.</item>
                     <item>5 They have the commands, as coming from the Goſpell, not to get life; but to teſtifie and exerciſe charity, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5.</item>
                     <item>6 They can, in Chriſt, ſee all the commands turned into Promiſes: ſo, as in hearkning to him, he will effect all in them, <hi>Pſalm:</hi> 81.8, 9. and 138.8.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>So that; the Doctrine of the Goſpell containes all that is meet to be taught: and doth not aboliſh, but eſtabliſh the Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Obſervation <hi>2.</hi>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 That the Doctrine of the Goſpell containeth both the Word, of the beginning of Chriſt: ſetting forth what he hath done; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and is, for all, and hath to beſtow on them when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve: And all the everlaſting Covenant, and new Teſtament ſetting forth, what he is to, and will in due ſeaſon doe for thoſe that in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving are made one with him, <hi>Heb:</hi> 6.1-4. and 8, &amp; 9, as is ſhewn throughout this Treatiſe; The firſt of theſe is to be preached to all men, as the foundation to repentance, faith, &amp;c, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1-9.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is to be opened to Believers for the encouragement of their hope, and for their edification, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Obſer. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 That the grace of God diſcovered by the Spirit of Chriſt in this Goſpell, and put in the heart of the Believer; is through the ſame Spirit, a ſufficient Prop and School-maſter for, and to the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever: to witneſſe peace, to comfort, renew, teach, lead, and preſerve; in wayting for the coming of Chriſt, <hi>Tit:</hi> 2.11, 12. <hi>Gal:</hi> 5.5, 16, 18.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Obſer. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 That the believing-remembrance of this grace of Chriſt is the way of Believers, drawing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt all receites, ſprings, &amp; ſtreams of conſolation, and fruitfulneſſe in themſelves and for others: as is fore-ſhewn; it being the drift of this whole Treatiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:113873:55"/>
               <head>CHAP. 15.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A pointing to ſome Applicatory uſefulneſſe.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1 IN this fore-diſcovery of the Goſpell ſetting forth Chriſt; is Ground of Reproof, of</p>
               <p n="1">1. Thoſe; that ſlander the Goſpell of Chriſt, and of the grace of Chriſt, and the doctrine thereof, as inſufficient to prepare men for Chriſt, or to ſanctifie Believers, or as if it were Antinomianiſme, and a doctrine of fleſhly liberty.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Thoſe; that confound things that are diſtinct, and make them one, and of like large extent, which the Goſpell diſtinguiſheth, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth the one as more generall; the other, as ſpeciall: As, the Reconciliation wrought by Chriſt in himſelf with God for men; And, the Reconciliation which by Spirit applying the former, hee worketh in men to God:
<list>
                     <item>His miſſion, to make propitiation, and offer ſacrifice; And</item>
                     <item>His miſſion, to preach the Goſpell; And to</item>
                     <item>His laying down his life, to ſatisfie Juſtice; And</item>
                     <item>To confirme the New Teſtament; And</item>
                     <item>To ſeale his miniſtration, and teſtifie love, and therein give us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 Thoſe; that put all receit of eternall life, upon the very Act of Chriſts ſuffering, riſing, and offering himſelf a ſacrifice to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; whereas all this did but procure it into his hands to beſtow: and it is the ſpirituall application to the heart, in which the receite is.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Thoſe; that take faith, only for a perſwaſion raiſed by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and arguments from Scripture, and frames, or that thinke faith to be nothing elſe, but a believing to be ſaved by Chriſt, or that one ſtands ſpotleſſe before God.</p>
               <p>All which follies and miſtakes, are diſcovered in this Treatiſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Here is ground of Admonition, and Exhortation, to all that through grace believe in Chriſt, diligently, and conſtantly at all times: and in all things</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:113873:55"/>
               <p>To heed the Goſpels Declaration of Chriſt, and his grace there-through made known: And</p>
               <p>To abide, and walk in the acknowledgment, and faith thereof: And</p>
               <p>To ſuffer the grace there-through moving, and teaching; to have its perfect work in us, and to yeeld up thereto.</p>
               <p>And, how it will work in us, ſave, ſanctifie, renew, comfort, and lead us; is already ſhewn: The experiment of the truth whereof, the Lord fill us with; As prayeth</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>The unworthieſt of all he hath ſhewn mercy to,</hi> Tho. Moore.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
